<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The strong man armed not cast out, but removed to a stronger hold viz, from profaneness to hypocrisie, or, An answer to a book entituled, The strong man armed cast out and his goods spoyled ... written by James Jackson ... written for the vindication to the truths of the Gospel ... by Ra. Austen.</title>
            <author>Austen, Ralph, d. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35295</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15234919</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15234919</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103245</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1139:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The strong man armed not cast out, but removed to a stronger hold viz, from profaneness to hypocrisie, or, An answer to a book entituled, The strong man armed cast out and his goods spoyled ... written by James Jackson ... written for the vindication to the truths of the Gospel ... by Ra. Austen.</title>
                  <author>Austen, Ralph, d. 1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 118 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Parker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jackson, James, fl. 1674-1708. --  Strong man armed cast out.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103245:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Strong Man Armed not Caſt Out,</hi> BUT <hi>Removed to a Stronger Hold: VIZ.</hi> FROM PROFANENESS to HYPOCRISIE.</p>
            <p>OR, An Anſwer to a Book, Entituled, <hi>The Strong Man Armed Caſt Out, and his Goods ſpoyled;</hi> Or, <hi>The Poor Man ſitting at Jeſus</hi>'s <hi>Feet, Cloathed, and in his Right Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> formerly a Pariſh Prieſt, and afterwards a Teacher among the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents: And now Walking with the People called Quakers, as he Teſtifieth of himſelf.</p>
            <p>In which Anſwer is plainly Diſcovered the Ignorance and Darkneſs, the Deluſions, and Falſe Apprehenſions of this <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> Concerning himſelf, and the Churches, and Aſſemblies which he Diſowns, and Separates from. And alſo the Erroneous Interpretations and Applications of the Scriptures, which he mentions in his Book.</p>
            <p>Herein are alſo Diſcovered ſeveral Characters, plain Marks of thoſe Falſe Teachers that the Spirit ſpeaketh expreſly ſhould come into the World in theſe laſt days.</p>
            <p>Written for the Vindication of the Truths of the Goſpel, the Stabliſhing of thoſe who are in the Truth, and the Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of thoſe who have Erred from it: And in all for the Exaltation of the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R.a. Auſten.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 John 3.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> Try the Spirits, whether they are of God, for many falſe Prophets are gone out into the World.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 8.20.</hi>
                  </bibl> To the Law, and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this Word, it is becauſe there is no Light in them.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 8.9.</hi>
                  </bibl> Lo, they have Rejected the Word of the Lord, and what Wiſdom is in them?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Peter Parker,</hi> at the <hi>Leg and Star</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:103245:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <p>IT is certain that <hi>theſe are the Laſt Times;</hi> and that <hi>many Falſe Prophets are gone out into the World;</hi> Deceitful workers, Miniſters of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, transforming themſelves into the Miniſters of Chriſt: It is time therefore, and our Neceſſary Duty, <hi>to try the Spirits whether they are of God:</hi> and verily here is one as dangerous a Perſon, with as ſubtil, inſinuating Doctrine, as I ever yet met with. VVhen I had Read his Book, and Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved how he Exalteth and Magnifieth himſelf, and thoſe of his way, as the <hi>onely Holy People in the World;</hi> and Separateth from all the Godly, their Societies, and aſſemblies, of all perſwaſions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Exception: and not onely ſo, but alſo vilifieth them, Ranking them with the wicked and unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate world, and how he aſſerteth and maintaineth <hi>a falſe Principle,</hi> That <hi>the true Light</hi> (meaning Chriſt) <hi>is in every Man and Woman;</hi> and is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, being believed in, and Obeyed, to bring them to Salvation: and that whoſoever will not Receive, and own this Doctrine, are accounted by him Enemies to Chriſt. VVhen I conſidered theſe things, with many other <hi>Lies in Hypocriſie and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies,</hi> mentioned in his Book, my Spirit was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently moved within me, and I ſaid in my ſelf, Shall this uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtine</hi> thus come forth, and Challenge, and Defie the Hoſts and Armies
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:103245:3"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Light within ſhall be in Hell for ever.</hi> p. 31.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers draw people to Idolatry.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers are under ſpiritual Judgments.</hi> p. 32.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers Perfection in ſin.</hi> p. 34.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers imperfection in grace.</hi> 35. 1 <hi>In knowledge.</hi> ibid. 2 <hi>In Faith and Hope.</hi> 36. 3 <hi>In Love.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Paul <hi>preacheth Chriſt, and not the Light in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man and woman.</hi> p. 38.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Devils fundamental doctrine.</hi> p. 39.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Obſtinate Quakers to be rejected.</hi> p. 41.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers ſin is like the great ſin of the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Jewes.</hi> p. 42.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Advice to the hearers among the Quakers.</hi> p. 44.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers great Idol near falling.</hi> p. 45.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ten Arguments proving the Light within is not Chriſt.</hi> p. 46.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers Humility.</hi> p. 56.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, of the true Church.</hi> 59. 1. <hi>One Body.</hi> ib. 2. <hi>One Spirit.</hi> ib. 3. <hi>One Hope.</hi> 60. 4. <hi>One Lord.</hi> ib. 5. <hi>One Faith.</hi> ib. 6. <hi>One Baptiſme.</hi> ib. 7. <hi>One God.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers Patience.</hi> p. 62.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A falſe perſwaſion of Converſion.</hi> p. 63.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Light within converts none to the Lord.</hi> p. 65.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Natural Light, is Spiritual Darkneſs.</hi> p. 67.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>This Scripture</hi> Joh. 1.9. <hi>groſly miſtaken.</hi> p. 68.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:103245:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers Doctrine is directly-contrary to the Scriptures.</hi> p. 70</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſcience is a natural light.</hi> 72.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chriſt, the true Light, is really in believers, and in none elſe.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Scriptures are the word of God.</hi> p. 74.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Scriptures are Gods Love letters to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</hi> p. 77.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Characters of falſe Prophets whereby they are known.</hi> p. 78. 1. <hi>Departing from the Faith.</hi> p. 79.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Character: Giving heed to ſeducing Spirits, and Doctrines of Devils.</hi> p. 80. 1. <hi>Againſt Chriſt.</hi> ib. 2. <hi>Againſt the Scriptures:</hi> ibid. 3. <hi>Againſt the Church:</hi> 81.4. <hi>Reſting upon their own Righteouſneſs:</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The third Character of falſe Prophets:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lyes in Hypocriſie</hi> p. 82.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The firſt Lye in Hypocriſie</hi> p. 83</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ſecond Lye in Hypocriſie</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The third Lye in Hypocriſie</hi> p. 84.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The fourth Lye in Hypocriſie</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The fifth Lye in Hypocriſie</hi> p. 86.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ſixt Lye in Hypocriſie</hi> p. 88.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers Railing accuſations</hi> p. 89.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The fourth Character of falſe Teachers: their Conſciences are ſeared with an hot Iron</hi> p. 91.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The fifth Character of falſe Teachers: denying the Lord that bought us</hi> p. 92.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:103245:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Apoſtle</hi> Peter, <hi>and</hi> Jude, <hi>both agree in the ſame.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Characters of falſe Teachers</hi> p. 93.</item>
               <item>Enoch <hi>Propheſied of theſe ungodly men</hi> p. 100.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers have ſpoken many hard ſpeeches againſt Chriſt.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers ſeparation from Chriſt and his people proves they are no Chriſtians.</hi> p. 101.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Lying Spirit is gone forth among the Quakers, which ſeduceth them.</hi> p. 105.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Births of the Spirit, and of the Fleſh.</hi> p. 106.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spiritual ſins are greater than fleſhly ſins.</hi> p. 108.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The falſe Opinions of the Quakers ſpring from Pride and Ignorance.</hi> p. 109.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers deceive weak and ſimple minds.</hi> p. 110.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers ſhall not long continue to deceive.</hi> p. 113.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Good Counſel to the Quakers.</hi> p. 115.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Leave the Quakers Meetings</hi> p. 116.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Come to the Aſſemblies of the Saints.</hi> p. 117.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103245:4"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Strong Man Armed not Caſt out,</hi> BUT <hi>Removed to a ſtronger Hold:</hi> VIZ. From PROFANENESS TO HYPOCRISIE.</head>
            <p>WHen Man at his firſt Creation came out of the Hand of God, he was then a Holy, and a Righteous Creature: But we all know (to our ſorrow) he loſt that <hi>Holy ſtate;</hi> and now, and ſince then, he is <hi>by Nature a Child of Wrath,</hi> and <hi>an Enemy to God,</hi> in his mind afar off from him, and moſt unlike unto him: So that there is no Recovering that Holy, and Happy Eſtate again, to have <hi>Fellowſhip and Communion with God, but by Regeneration and Converſion;</hi> from this Carnal ſtate, to a New Spiritual ſtate; by true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Faith in Chriſt, wrought by the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Power of the Spirit of God, in thoſe whom he (according to his determinate Counſel and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge) calleth in due time unto himſelf; in whom he (by degrees) deſtroys the works of the Devil, the <hi>Image of the firſt Adam,</hi> and Creates;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103245:5"/>and works, the <hi>Image or Nature of the Second Adam Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in Righteouſneſs, and true Holineſs; or as it is in ſome other Expreſſions in Scripture, he caſteth out the <hi>ſtrong Man Armed,</hi> that keepeth the Houſe, and Divideth the Spoyls, when this <hi>ſtronger than he</hi> cometh, he turns out this firſt <hi>ſtrong Man</hi> (though Armed, and in his ſtrong Hold of every Faculty of the Soul) and Enters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and takes Poſſeſſion of the Soul, and turns all to his own Uſe and Intereſt, even for his own Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; the Exaltation of his Free-Grace, and that for ever.</p>
            <p>Now, here comes <hi>this great Queſtion</hi> to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated and Determined,
<note place="margin">The Author of the Strong Man Armed, Tryed.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Perſon here menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>James Jackſon, Author of the Book Entituled, The Strong Man Armed caſt out,</hi> (which alſo Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends and includes all others of his Mind, with whom he hath now joyned himſelf.) He is ſtrongly perſwaded (it appears) That the <hi>ſtrong Man, the Devil,</hi> with all his wares and works, is caſt out, and that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is entred, and dwells in his ſtead.</p>
            <p>He tells us in his Epiſtle to his Friends and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, what an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, Diſſolute, Debauched, and Extravagant Courſe of Life</hi> the had Lived, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all <hi>Counſels, Admonitions, Reproofs, Vows, Promiſes, and Engagements,</hi> breaking all theſe as ſo many Bonds and Fetters (alluding to the poor Man that was poſſeſſed with Devils, and Bound with Chains and Fetters, and brake all in pieces, and no Man could tame him.) So did he, to the grief and wounding of his dear Friends. But the Lord working mightily, and <hi>Revealing his Son in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103245:5"/>him,</hi> (he ſaith;) and making a wonderful and great Change, he would not eat his Morſels alone, but thought it his Duty to Communicate theſe things to his Friends and Relations, and to tell them what great things God hath done for him, and hath had Compaſſion on him, in turning him from Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into his Marvellous Light, and from the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Satan, into the Kingdom of his dear Son.</p>
            <p>So that now our work is to bring him and his works to be Weighed in the <hi>Ballance of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> and to try them by the true <hi>Touch-ſtone,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be true Metal or Counterfeit; for many Fooliſh Builders Build upon the Sand, and not upon the <hi>Rock:</hi> Yea, and ſome that Build upon the firmer <hi>Foundation,</hi> yet they Build much <hi>Wood, Hay, and Stubble,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Gold, Silver, and Precious Stones,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.13. but every Man's work ſhall be made Manifeſt, for the Day ſhall Declare it, becauſe it ſhall be Revealed by Fire; And the Fire ſhall Try every Man's work of what ſort it is. Now, this Fire is the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the Scriptures; if Men ſpeak according to his Mind and Will, then it is the Truth; but if they ſpeak, or Act other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then it is not according to Truth, but is from <hi>a Falſe Spirit:</hi> That is, either from the Devil (the Spirit that worketh in the Children of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) or from a Man's own Spirit, or from both.</p>
            <p>Therefore, that we may know which to follow, when Men Differ and Contend about things, this is the ſure and onely way, (according to the <hi>Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Counſel) to try the Spirits, whether they are of God, or not,</hi> 1 John 3.</p>
            <p>But it may readily be asked, how ſhall we know the Spirits, which is which; which is the <hi>true
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103245:6"/>Spirit,</hi> and which the <hi>falſe,</hi> when they ſpeak in men different things, who diſagree in their Sayings and Apprehenſions?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer; That the Spirit of God ſpeaking in any Man,
<note place="margin">How to know the true Spirit from the falſe Spirit.</note> or if any Man ſpeak by the Spirit of God, he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth according to what he hath already ſpoken, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: That is, according to what he hath already ſpoken <hi>in the Scriptures,</hi> by thoſe Holy Men of God that wrote the Scriptures, and were <hi>Inſpired by the holy ghoſt;</hi> and if any man ſpeak contrary to what the Spirit of God hath already ſpoken, and Revealed in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> he is a Lyar, and ſpeaketh from a <hi>falſe Deluding Spirit,</hi> and not by the <hi>Spirit of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells us plainly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. <hi>We ſpeak things which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring Spiritual things with Spiritual. <hi>Paul</hi> had the Spirit of God, and ſpake and taught by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. But if a Natural Man (one that hath not the ſpirit of Chriſt in him) doth go about to compare ſpiritual things with ſpiritual things, he is ſure to miſtake, and ſpeak Erroneouſly; <hi>For the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Man</hi> (as he there ſaith) <hi>perceiveth not the things that are of God, neither can he know, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, becauſe they are ſpiritually Diſcerned:</hi> That is, they are ſeen in the Light, and by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the Spirit of Chriſt, the true Light, and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>So that this being laid down as a Ground and Foundation, <hi>an Infallible truth,</hi> as it is; we may then proceed to the <hi>Examination and Tryal of the Spirits and Doctrines of Men;</hi> for no Man ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the ſpirit of God, will, or can ſpeak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103245:6"/>to the Scriptures; if he do, let it be Reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any Man Preach any other Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel than that which we have Preached unto you, let him be accurſed;</hi> yea, if an Angel from Heaven bring any other Goſpel than that ye have Received, (and is written in the Scriptures) let him be Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, not onely let him or them be Diſowned, and Rejected, but let him be <hi>Accurſed:</hi> ſo Zealous was he, and ſo ſhou'd we be to hold faſt, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Doctrine of the Goſpel,</hi> the Scriptures, given out by God himſelf, ſpoken and written by the Men of God, in their Day, and Generation, by the immediate Dictates, Teachings, and Movings of the Holy Ghoſt, the Spirit of God, ſo that (as was ſaid) whatever Spirit it be (in whomſoever) that ſpeaketh contrary, or not according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is to be diſowned, and rejected, as falſe and erroneous.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, here comes in the Tryal of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; the ſeveral Doctrines, Opinions, and Practices of Men, of any perſwaſions whatſoever: Either they ſpeak according to the <hi>Spirit of God in them,</hi> or from <hi>ſome other Spirit;</hi> if they ſpeak from the ſpirit of God in them, then it muſt needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what he hath already ſpoken, (as was ſaid) for he is one and the ſame Spirit, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not: But if it be otherwiſe, then it may be ſaid, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of ſome in his Time, <hi>This Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion cometh not of him that calleth you,</hi> Gal. 5.8. it cometh not from the Spirit of God, but from a falſe and Deluding Spirit.</p>
            <p>And here now is thy Tryal and thy Judgment, <hi>James Jackſon, Author of the ſtrong Man Armed caſt out;</hi> and all that are of thy Mind and Way;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103245:7"/>who ſpeak contrary to what the Holy Ghoſt hath ſpoken already in the Scriptures, as is hereafter ſhewed in ſeveral particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1. Strong Man Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> That Spirit in thee Declares to all People, That thou art now <hi>Converted, and turned from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of Satan unto God;</hi> that thou art changed from a wicked Profane courſe of Life, unto a Holy Life, walking with a Holy People, and that thou haſt left off to be <hi>a Pariſh Prieſt;</hi> yea, and after that, haſt left off from being <hi>a Teacher among the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> and haſt diſowned, and forſaken the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations and Aſſemblies of the Independents; and art now come and joyned with the People called <hi>Quakers.</hi> And thou telleſt us, That theſe are the <hi>onely Holy People of God upon Earth;</hi> and that all other <hi>Churches, Aſſemblies, and Congregations</hi> (Naming the <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Baptiſts,</hi> and others) are out of the way; and that though they differ in <hi>Forms or Perſwaſions,</hi> yet they agree <hi>in the ſame Faith, Foundation, and Root.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Anſwer hereunto briefly; I ſhall not ſpeak to Reproach thee, or rail upon thee, or any of thy way, as thou haſt done againſt many of the Precious Saints in the Churches of Chriſt, ſaying of the <hi>Independents</hi> (whoſe Aſſemblies thou haſt forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) That there was ſufficient ground for thee to ſeparate from the Tents of thoſe ungodly Men,
<note place="margin">Strong Man Armed, <hi>p.</hi> 8.</note> their Teachers, who are no better than <hi>Filthy Dreamers, Blind Guids, and Belly-gods,</hi> which belch out nothing but <hi>Lies, Slanders, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, and evil ſpeeches</hi> againſt Chriſt, his Ways, Truths, and People; and this (thou ſayeſt) thou
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103245:7"/>ſeeſt, and declareſt againſt them in the Light. I ſay, I will not bring againſt thee <hi>Railing Accuſations,</hi> as thou doſt againſt others; but <hi>the Lord Rebuke thee,</hi> and that <hi>Lying Spirit</hi> in thee, and Convince <hi>thy Spirit</hi> of the Truth.</p>
            <p>Concerning thy leaving off to continue <hi>a Pariſh Priest,</hi> thou didſt well; but thou hadſt done better if thou hadſt never undertaken it; for there are too many ſuch <hi>Prieſts,</hi> like the <hi>Priests of Old, the Sons of Eli;</hi> who (by reaſon of their wickedneſs) made the Sacrifices of the Lord to be Abhorred: There are many in theſe Days <hi>of the ſame Tribe,</hi> who make the <hi>Goſpel of Chriſt, his Ways, Truths, and People</hi> to be evil ſpoken of; yea, they make <hi>the Name of Chriſt to be Blaſphemed, and his People Reproached,</hi> even through them, and by their means: And making others, who are <hi>the true and Faithful Miniſters and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt</hi> to be evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, Reviled, and Diſowned for their ſakes, and becauſe of them; yea, more, They Occaſion <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations in all parts of the Land.</hi> Wo unto them, for they have gone in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the <hi>Error of</hi> Balaam <hi>for a Reward,</hi> and get into the <hi>Prieſts Office,</hi> that they may eat a piece of Bread, that they may get a Living by it: Many of them more ſit for the <hi>Cart, or the Plough,</hi> than the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> having neither <hi>Gifts of Nature, nor of Grace</hi> fit for the Miniſtry. Men that never <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt,</hi> were never <hi>taught of God,</hi> and how then can they Teach others? Nay, inſtead of Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others in the ways of Life and Salvation, they by their <hi>wicked Examples</hi> draw them down to Hell, they are the <hi>worſt of Men upon Earth.</hi> I have In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt ſuch, and am greatly grieved for the Miſery of thoſe poor Ignorant Souls of their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103245:8"/>Pariſhes, who are like to <hi>periſh for lack of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> the Blind leading the Blind, both will fall into the Ditch: The Lord Remove them, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them, and give <hi>Paſtors</hi> after his own heart, according to his Promiſe.</p>
            <p>And for this I Commend thee, <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> that thou didſt leave off thy <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> and alſo deceiving the People as <hi>a Pariſh Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now take heed,
<note place="margin">The Strong Hold of Hypocriſie is ſtronger than that of Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> leſt thou art not yet deceived, in the ſtate and condition thou art now in, leſt <hi>the falſe ſpirit</hi> be not too ſubtill for thee; leſt <hi>Satan (that strong Man Armed)</hi> having quit <hi>one strong hold,</hi> be not got <hi>into another</hi> that is <hi>ſtronger</hi> than the former; for certain it is, the Devil's pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and policy in a way of <hi>Groſs wickedneſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs,</hi> is not half ſo <hi>ſtrong a hold</hi> as the <hi>ſtrong hold of Hypocriſie:</hi> Where Reaſon, Natural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, all outward Occurrences, Moral, Civilized Perſons, all can readily Reprove, and help to draw a Man out of ſuch an Eſtate; but the <hi>strong hold of Hypocriſie,</hi> and Erroneous perſwaſions and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>in a way of Religion,</hi> is more Dangerous, and <hi>a ſtronger Hold;</hi> where nothing but the <hi>ſpirit of God,</hi> and an <hi>enlightned <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> to diſcern the Truth of the word of the Goſpel, can Inſtruct a Man, eſpecially when a Man hath paſſed through many, or divers <hi>States, Forms, Opinions, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions,</hi> and at laſt hath pitched upon <hi>one</hi> that he Judges and Concludes doth Exceed <hi>all the former;</hi> if yet this be <hi>falſe,</hi> and he know it not, he is then in greater Danger than ever, ſeeing his own <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reaſon,</hi> and his <hi>Ignorant dim-ſighted Conſcience,</hi> confirmed by the <hi>ſtrong deluſions of Satan,</hi> (that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103245:8"/>ſpirit that worketh, and Ruleth in the Children of Diſobedience, do all concurre and joyn together, and hold the poor ſoul in Bondage under Darkneſs, which is by many taken for the <hi>true Light of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, Take heed of being deceived in theſe things, thou and thy Friends; for I ſay, the <hi>ſtrong hold</hi> of the Devil, in a way of <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> is not <hi>ſo ſtrong</hi> as his <hi>ſtrong hold</hi> in a way of <hi>Hypocriſie, or falſe Worſhip;</hi> this is Evident both by Scripture and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Chriſt told the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who were Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in a way of <hi>Hypocriſie:</hi> That <hi>Publicans and Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lots,</hi> (great and groſs ſinners, in a way of <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi>) ſhould enter into the Kingdom of Heaven before them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.31. And that I may ſhew my true Love to your ſouls (whether you will Accept it or no) I will Endeavour to ſhew unto thee and them, things in a clearer Light than yet ſhines in you.</p>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>the ſtrong Man Armed (the Devil)</hi> is caſt out of thee, <hi>and Chriſt a ſtronger than he,</hi> is come in, and now keeps the Houſe: How is this made manifeſt? Thy ſaying ſo does not prove it, but thy <hi>Sayings, and thy Doings</hi> prove the contrary; and this I ſhall make good, both by <hi>poſitive Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by Example.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>any Man be in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The New Creature doth Evidence it ſelf where it is.</note> 
               <hi>he is a New Creature,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. He that is <hi>Converted, and changed</hi> from the ſtate of <hi>Nature,</hi> to the ſtate of <hi>Grace,</hi> out of whom <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> is caſt, and <hi>Christ</hi> come in; he is <hi>New</hi> in his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Will, Affections;</hi> yea, <hi>New</hi> in his <hi>whole Life and Converſation:</hi> But now it appears plainly, that <hi>thy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> is ſtill <hi>Old,</hi> the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103245:9"/>ſame <hi>Ignorance, Blindneſs, Darkneſs</hi> remains upon it, as is in all <hi>Natural Men;</hi> and this is ſeen, and manifeſt by thy <hi>falſe Interpretations of Scriptures;</hi> and Secondly, by thy <hi>falſe applications of them,</hi> in Applying thoſe Scriptures to the <hi>Saints, true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, Members of Chriſt,</hi> as do belong only to the <hi>unregenerate World;</hi> ſuch as are yet in the <hi>ſtate of Nature;</hi> neither art thou changed in <hi>thy Will and Affections,</hi> they are not yet <hi>New,</hi> but according to the <hi>Old Nature</hi> in all <hi>unregenerate Perſons,</hi> as plainly appears in that thou ſheweſt forth no <hi>true Love</hi> to the <hi>Lords precious People, Members of the Body of Chriſt;</hi> but contrariwiſe, <hi>diſowneſt them, and ſeparateſt from them;</hi> nay more, thou doſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile them, and falſly ſpeak evil of them,</hi> as is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen in many paſſages of thy Book: And as for thy <hi>Love and affections towards Chriſt,</hi> it is <hi>Love</hi> but onely <hi>in Tongue, in Word, and Profeſſion onely,</hi> not in <hi>Truth.</hi> Thou profeſſeſt that thou <hi>Knoweſt, and Loveſt him,</hi> but indeed <hi>thou denyeſt him,</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of his People, and diſowning of them, for he hath ſaid, <hi>He that Deſpiſeth you, Deſpiſeth me;</hi> nay more, Thou, and thoſe of thy way, <hi>Deny and diſhonour Chriſt,</hi> in that ye ſet up <hi>his Creature,</hi> and Adore it, and Worſhip it, <hi>for Chriſt,</hi> and call it <hi>Chriſt in you;</hi> and ſo make the <hi>Creator</hi> and the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> all one.</p>
            <p>Now, ſeeing thou art <hi>an Old Creature</hi> ſtill, both in thy inner Man and outward Man in thy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: How canſt thou think thou art <hi>changed,</hi> or that <hi>the Strong Man Armed is caſt out,</hi> but rather that he is Removed to <hi>a ſtronger hold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paul</hi>'s Example a Looking-Glaſs.</note> further; Let us try by another <hi>Touch-ſtone,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art true Gold or no:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103245:9"/>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> we know, was once in a <hi>Carnal ſtate,</hi> in a <hi>ſtate of Nature, in Darkneſs;</hi> but was <hi>Called, and Converted:</hi> And we ſee, he ſhews forth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts to all, that <hi>his ſtate was changed;</hi> for he ſoon after, <hi>prayed earneſtly to God,</hi> and he <hi>Preached the Goſpel,</hi> he ſtood up Zealouſly to Preach <hi>that Jeſus,</hi> which lately before <hi>he perſecuted in his Members:</hi> He Baniſhed them, and Impriſoned them, and did many miſchiefs to them; yea, and thought verily he did well, and that he ought to do many things againſt <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth;</hi> and this was from the <hi>Light within,</hi> which thou and thy Friends ſay, <hi>is in every Man and Woman,</hi> and which <hi>ye adore for God and Chriſt:</hi> But when he was <hi>Converted, this Light</hi> was known to be but <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> by the <hi>true Light, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when he ſhined into his ſoul; when <hi>this Sun of Righteouſneſs aroſe, it ſcattered his Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Compare <hi>thy Change and Converſion</hi> (as thou calleſt it) with <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Converſion,</hi> for his was true, and ſee how like thine looks to his, or how unlike it; and thereby thou and others may gain In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Thou and others may plainly ſee how much thou art Deceived, in that thou thinkeſt, and ſay'ſt, <hi>The ſtrong Man armed is caſt out of thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do but look thy ſelf <hi>in this glaſs of the Example of Paul,</hi> and thou wilt ſee thy ſelf like him, as he was <hi>before his Converſion,</hi> as like him <hi>as one Man can be like another:</hi> But if thou lookeſt thy ſelf in the <hi>Example of</hi> Paul after his <hi>Converſion,</hi> then thou art no more like him, than an <hi>Ape is like a Man;</hi> perhaps, ſome dark ſhadows, and ſimple Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances, ſome ſeeming likeneſs, but nothing of Truth or Reality, in any Spiritual Reſpects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> before his <hi>Converſion</hi> Raged againſt the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103245:10"/>Saints, and was very bitter againſt them; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards when he was <hi>enlightned and Converted,</hi> he joyns himſelf to them, is one with them, and counts it a great and precious Priviledge ſo to be: He Preached to them that Jeſus whom before he knew not; but Perſecuted him, yea, he is tender of them, and Nouriſheth them, and Cheriſheth them, as a Nurſe Cheriſheth her Children.</p>
            <p>Now, conſider with thy ſelf, <hi>James Jackſon;</hi> doſt thou do ſo? doſt thou ſhew forth theſe clear Evidences of <hi>Converſion</hi> and a <hi>New ſtate,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> did? if ſo, then thou haſt good grounds to believe that the <hi>ſtrong Man</hi> is indeed caſt out; if thou ſay it is ſo, then tell me, what meaneth this Bleating of the Sheep, and Lowing of the Oxen which I hear? What meaneth <hi>thy loud out-crys, and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours againſt the Lords People;</hi> thy <hi>Railing Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations</hi> againſt all the <hi>Churches and Congregations</hi> that are not juſt of thy Mind? Is this <hi>Cheriſhing them as a Nurſe cheriſheth her Children, as</hi> Paul <hi>did?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> Fed the Young ones, and the Weak with Milk, and tenderly dealt with them, untill they were able to Digeſt ſtronger Meat. Thou regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not the Weak, nor the Young, no, nor the Strong, but Cryeſt them down all, as Deceived Perſons, in Darkneſs, in <hi>Babylon,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Converſion: So this proves thee to be like him before hís Change; and conſequently, that <hi>the ſtrong Man armed is not yet caſt out of thee, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to a ſtronger hold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thou ſay, Nay, but I Own, and Love, and Cheriſh the Holy People of the Lord, unto whom I am now joyned, which is a good Evidence of my Converſion and Change.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103245:10"/>
            <p>It is Anſwered; That if it were ſuppoſed, and granted, that thoſe People with whom thou walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, were indeed the People of the Lord, (as I hope many of them are, who know not their falſe Doctrines, for I will not be ſevere, as the manner of ſome is, to Condemn all, for the Errors of ſome amongſt them) yet art thou far ſhort of <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> who owned <hi>all the Saints,</hi> though under <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Forms:</hi> To the <hi>Jews,</hi> he became <hi>as a Jew;</hi> to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> as they; to thoſe <hi>under the Law,</hi> as <hi>under the Law;</hi> to thoſe <hi>without Law, as without Law;</hi> he became <hi>all things to all,</hi> in ſuch Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, Un-commanded things as <hi>Forms</hi> are, that ſo he might gain them to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But thou cleaveſt <hi>to a few,</hi> and many of them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>ſtrong Deluſions,</hi> and there thou helpeſt to ſtrengthen their Deceived Minds in Errors; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eiving, and being Deceived: Why art thou not <hi>a Follower of</hi> Paul <hi>herein,</hi> as he beſeeches all to be; as <hi>he is a Follower of Chriſt?</hi> Now, Chriſt Owns, Loves, and Accepts <hi>all his People, under all Forms,</hi> being United to him, as Members of his Body; Worſhipping of him in Spirit and in Truth: So the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>In every Nation</hi> (though they are not one in their Forms, there being ſeveral in this Nation) <hi>he that feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accepted with him.</hi> Now, how are we <hi>Followers of Chriſt,</hi> or of <hi>Paul,</hi> herein, if they are not Accepted of us alſo?</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed with ſuch <hi>proud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proud Profeſſors in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Time Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> 
               <hi>ſelf-conceited, troubleſome perſons</hi> in his time, as are now in ours; and he deals with them, and Reproves them, even for this very thing that I am now ſpeaking of, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103245:11"/>is, <hi>Highly eſteeming of themſelves, and Deſpiſing others;</hi> as we ſee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7. ſome High, Proud Perſons, that Commended themſelves, and valued themſelves above <hi>Paul,</hi> and thoſe that were of his Aſſemblies, they thought that they themſelves were the <hi>onely people of the Lord;</hi> but as for <hi>Paul and his Followers,</hi> they had no ſuch perſwaſion of them; But the Apoſtle Reproves them, and tells them they have as good grounds and Reaſon to think as well of him, and thoſe with him, as of themſelves, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any Man think that he is Chriſts, let him think this again, that as he is Chriſt's, even ſo are we Chriſt's;</hi> let them have as good an Opinion of us, as they have of themſelves, for they have as good grounds for it.</p>
            <p>But (ſaith he) they are a People that look upon ſome things in Themſelves, but take no Notice of any good in Us; and ſo they <hi>Meaſure themſelves by themſelves, and compare themſelves among themſelves,</hi> and in ſo doing they are not wiſe, <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Howſoever we know our <hi>Meaſure,</hi> and our <hi>Time,</hi> our <hi>Gifts and Graces</hi> that God hath gìven us; and although they think <hi>highly of themſelves,</hi> and but <hi>Meanly of us;</hi> yet we know, that <hi>not he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth himſelf, is approved, but whom the Lord commendeth, as v.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>Is it not ſo in our Days? are there not a People among us, who have <hi>high eſteem of themſelves,</hi> and that think of themſelves more highly than they ought to think, that account themſelves <hi>the onely Holy People of the Lord,</hi> and all others to be <hi>of the World;</hi> and caſt off, and diſown, and <hi>ſeparate</hi> from all other <hi>Societies, Communities, Congregations, and Churches of the Saints, and people of God,</hi> in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103245:11"/>all the World, and <hi>Meaſuring themſelves by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and comparing themſelves among themſelves,</hi> are thereby groſly miſtaken, and miſled; they Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and Applaud themſelves above all other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as being in the right and true way, and all others out of it; but <hi>not he that commendeth himſelf is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, but whom the Lord commendeth,</hi> and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, he ſhall ſtand, and be accepted. v. 18.</p>
            <p>Now, let us conſider the ground and cauſe of all this;
<note place="margin">Apoſtacy from the Faith; what it is.</note> whence is it that many have ſuch high thoughts of themſelves, and Deſpiſe others better than themſelves: The Apoſtle tells us, and the Spirit hath ſpoken it expreſly, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>in the laſt days</hi> (which are theſe we now Live in) <hi>Men ſhall depart from the Faith,</hi> that is, from Faith <hi>in the Doctrine of the Goſpel</hi> (not from <hi>Juſtifying Faith</hi>) and ſhall <hi>give heed to Seducing Spirits, and Doctrines of Devils;</hi> they having once departed from the <hi>Doctrine and Truths of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> they ſhall then <hi>give heed to Seducing Spirits, and Doctrines of Devils;</hi> they ſhall ſlight, and make light <hi>of the Scriptures,</hi> and then ſhall <hi>give heed to ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> a ſpirit within them, yea, many ſpirits are watchful to inſinuate into ſuch a mind, as take no heed to the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> for in ſuch a Frame of Mind what ſhould direct them; what <hi>Touch-ſtone</hi> or <hi>Rule of Tryal</hi> can they have (when the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are laid aſide) of <hi>what ſpirit</hi> ſpeaks in them? In ſuch a caſe Men often think it is <hi>the ſpirit of God,</hi> when it is but a <hi>ſeducing ſpirit,</hi> who hath Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed himſelf into an <hi>Angel of Light;</hi> and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <hi>the ſpirit of God,</hi> under the pretence of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Truth: In ſome things that are like Truth, it Reſembles it, but is not ſo: And hereby their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103245:12"/>Weak and Dark Minds are miſſed and deceived: For the Devil does often in many things, ſpeak the very Truth, but it is with an intent to deceive in other things that are of greater Moment and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; like cunning, deceitful Tradeſmen, who bring forth, and ſhew ſome <hi>good and right Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities,</hi> that ſo amongſt theſe they may put off their <hi>counterfeit Wares</hi> the better, and with leſs ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now,
<note place="margin">The Spirit within known by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> know this; That men ſhall not be able to know the <hi>falſe ſeducing ſpirit</hi> from the <hi>true,</hi> but <hi>by the Fruits and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it,</hi> and by trying it <hi>by the ſpirit of God ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Scriptures;</hi> and by theſe it may be known, and not otherwiſe. And hence it is, That many in our Days finding and feeling <hi>ſtrong impreſſions and impulſes in their minds,</hi> and not Examining of them, and trying of them <hi>by the ſpirit ſpeaking in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> do erre groſly, and are miſ-led by them, both in Doctrine and Practice: They give heed to, and are carried away with the <hi>preſent Impreſſion, moving in their minds,</hi> looking upon it immediately, by, and in it ſelf, <hi>as Chriſt the true Light,</hi> ſpeaking in them, when oft-times it is <hi>a ſeducing ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But if it be asked, How then ſhall we certainly know the Impreſſions of the <hi>ſeducing ſpirit</hi> in our minds, and the Impreſſions of the Spirit of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>ſpirit of God,</hi> which is given to them that Believe, Inſtructeth them how to know <hi>its own Operations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, by Comparing <hi>theſe immediate Impreſſions in the Mind, with what is already written in the Scriptures, dictated by the ſame ſpirit,</hi> concerning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103245:12"/>the ſame things now in the Mind or Judgment; therefore we ought to compare them together, and Examine whether they agree, and are one and the ſame: if the Impreſſions of the Spirit in the mind be contrary to the Spirit ſpeaking in the Scriptures, we may then be ſure <hi>it is a falſe and a ſeducing ſpirit;</hi> but if it be the ſame with the Spirit in the Scriptures, and confirmed thereby, then it is <hi>the true ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit of God gives (more eſpecially to ſome of his People) the Gift of <hi>diſcerning of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits:</hi> As we ſee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>To another</hi> he gives the <hi>Diſcerning of Spirits:</hi> And it is by this means afore-mentioned.</p>
            <p>And Secondly,
<note place="margin">Cauſes known by Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</note> we may know <hi>the true ſpirit</hi> from <hi>the ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſpirit, by the Fruits and Effects of it;</hi> we may know <hi>Cauſes by the Effects,</hi> as in Nature, ſo alſo in Grace.</p>
            <p>And therefore when we are doubtful what Spirit it is that ſpeaketh in us or others, let us try it <hi>by the Effects, the Fruits that it produceth;</hi> for <hi>every Tree is known by its own Fruits:</hi> The <hi>Effects</hi> and <hi>Fruits</hi> of the Spirit of God are ſuch as the Scripture tells us of in many places, as in the 5th. <hi>Gal. The Fruits of the Spirit are Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Patience, Humility, Temperance,</hi> &amp;c. Our Lord Chriſt, the Head, who was filled and Annointed with this Spirit above his Fellows, what Effects did it work <hi>in his Humane Nature,</hi> as our Mediator, he tells us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>he is Meek and Lowly in heart;</hi> and again, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1. <hi>I beſeech you by the meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and gentleneſs of Chriſt:</hi> What wonderful <hi>Humility</hi> did he ſhew forth in all his Life amongſt us; and in that aſtoniſhing Example of Waſhing his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103245:13"/>Diſciples Feet: And though he were a King, yea, the King of Kings, yet behold he came Meek and Lowly, Riding upon an Aſſe, and ſo tender of his Young Lambs, his Weak ones, that he carries them in his Boſom, and gently leads ſuch as are Young and tender; he will not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax: Though Faith be but as a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, it ſhall be watered to grow up and increaſe to more ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Now, the like <hi>Effects the ſame ſpirit works in his Members,</hi> (in every one in their Meaſures;) <hi>Paul</hi> fed his New-born Babes <hi>with Milk, and not with Meat,</hi> becauſe they were not able to bear it; <hi>and cheriſhed them, as a Nurſe cheriſheth her Children,</hi> often weeping over them, Travelling from place to place to ſtrengthen the New gathered Churches, Teaching, and Inſtructing them in thoſe two great, and chief Doctrines, <hi>Faith in Chriſt, and Love to all the Saints.</hi> So the <hi>Apoſtle John,</hi> the <hi>ſame ſpirit</hi> brought forth <hi>the ſame Fruits and Effects</hi> in him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. <hi>I have no greater Joy, than to ſee my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Walk in Truth.</hi> And Teacheth <hi>Love, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace, Fellowſhip, and Communion with all the Saints;</hi> And ſo are all the Children of God <hi>thus inclined by the ſame ſpirit,</hi> they ſhew forth the ſame <hi>Fruits and Effects,</hi> in their Degrees and Meaſures.</p>
            <p>But now on the contrary, conſider, <hi>The falſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing ſpirit</hi> brings forth in its Followers the quite contrary <hi>Fruits and Effects,</hi> as we plainly ſee amongſt Men: And hence are thoſe high and proud Conceits and Apprehenſions of themſelves, their Ways, their Doctrines, as <hi>better, above, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all others; being free from ſin, and become per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;</hi> ſaying in Effect, ſtand further from me, I am Holier than thou: Deſpiſing that Low, Childiſh
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103245:13"/>Doctrine of ſin abiding in us, in the remainders of it, whilſt we Live, though the Power and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of it be Deſtroy'd. I ſay, theſe <hi>Fruits and Effects</hi> ſpring from a <hi>Cauſe</hi> like unto them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may ſafely conclude what the <hi>Cauſe</hi> is; ſo again, when we ſee Men <hi>Separating from others bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than themſelves,</hi> leaving, and forſaking other Aſſemblies and Congregations ſound in Doctrine, and Holy in Life, and Converſation (excepting common, un-avoidable Infirmities) we may be ſure hereby, that <hi>this is from a ſeducing ſpirit;</hi> not from the <hi>ſpirit of God</hi> (whoſe contrary <hi>Fruits and Effects</hi> we heard before.)</p>
            <p>As <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The true Spirit is for Unity, the ſalfe Spirit for Diviſion.</note> by his Wiſdom given him of God, plainly Diſcerned, and knew the true Mother from the falſe, by this very thing, by this clear Evidence: She that was for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and for <hi>preſerving together,</hi> and Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing the parts and Members of the Child, was the <hi>true Mother:</hi> But ſhe that was for the <hi>Dividing of the Child, and ſeparating the Members of it,</hi> he knew by that, ſhe was the <hi>Harlot,</hi> and not the <hi>true Mother:</hi> Juſt ſo it is in this Caſe; The <hi>true ſpirit is for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Love, Fellowſhip, and Communion with all the Members of Chriſt,</hi> as Occaſion and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity is, but <hi>the falſe ſeducing ſpirit is for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> and Dividing the Members of Chriſt's Body, upon one pretence or another.</p>
            <p>And herein it is too manifeſt, that not onely ſome in our Days are more groſſely guilty; but alſo many of the <hi>true Members of Chriſt</hi> have been deceived, and carried away very far by <hi>this deluding and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing ſpirit</hi> (through the remainders of Pride, and ſelf-love in them) and have thought it their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103245:14"/>Duty to <hi>ſeparate from others of their Brethren,</hi> upon ſlight, weak, and inſufficient grounds and Cauſes; by which they have greatly Diſpleaſed, and Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>their Head, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and wronged <hi>their fellow-Members:</hi> And as an Evidence of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and a juſt Correction upon them, he hath permitted a People in theſe days to <hi>ſeparate from them all, and to diſown them all;</hi> which I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded is <hi>one End</hi> God hath in ſuffering theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to appear in this day; which as <hi>from God is a juſt Retaliation, to do to them, as they have done to others; the ſame Meaſure they have meeted to others of their Brethren, is now Meaſured to them again:</hi> Seeing no Rules in Scripture, nor Councels, nor Intreaties of their Brethren would perſwade, or win them to be of one mind, and to keep in Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip together; this now comes at laſt as the greateſt and ſharpeſt Reproof and Correction of all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; I hope, and deſire they will conſider it, and Learn from it; to hear the voice of God's Rod, as well as of his Word, and be Inſtructed thereby.</p>
            <p>And now having Tryed the <hi>Author of the ſtrong Man armed caſt out,</hi> and proved that <hi>the ſtrong man is not caſt out, but removed to a ſtronger Hold;</hi> let us proceed further, and make it appear alſo by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Proofs and Evidences, taken out of <hi>his own Book,</hi> (which alſo are ſufficient to convince all others of his Mind and Way) that they may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee (if the God of this World hath not blinded their Minds, and hid plain and clear Truths from them) the <hi>falſe and unſound Foundations which they Build upon,</hi> as well as <hi>the Wood, Hay, and Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> which they Build withal, both as to their <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Practices,</hi> in eſteeming themſelves the onely Holy People of the Lord in this Day, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103245:14"/>Deſpiſing, and Condemning thoſe that are <hi>indeed the People of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then;
<note place="margin">1. The Quakers Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments above others.</note> This Author tells us, what he, and the People with whom he now Walks, have attained unto above all others from whom they ſeparate. The People <hi>(the Quakers)</hi> he ſaith, Build upon <hi>a true and right Foundation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. In the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>the Rock of Ages; Chriſt in us the hope of Glory;</hi> but all other Profeſſing People in the World Build upon <hi>the Writings of Men,</hi> and all of them are ſtrangers to that one Spirit, which gave forth the Scriptures. <hi>See ſtrong Man Armed, &amp;c.</hi> p. 12.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to which, I ſay plainly; That if this were Truth which He hath ſpoken, I would <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> alſo, and Build upon <hi>the ſame Foundation</hi> which he ſays they Build upon: But he hath here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpoken falſely, and that in a double Reſpect. 1. <hi>In Reſpect of themſelves.</hi> 2. <hi>In Reſpect of other Profeſſors, the Churches of Chriſt.</hi> As for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſuch of them as Build upon <hi>the Foundation, the Light within every Man and Woman,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in it, and Obey it, and look for Salvation from it, as they Profeſs to do, ſuch <hi>Build upon a falſe and unſound Foundation, and not upon Chriſt, the onely true Foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, As for the other <hi>Profeſſing People,</hi> from whom they Separate, he hath belyed them alſo groſſely, in ſaying, they Build not upon <hi>Chriſt, the true Foundation;</hi> for it is the <hi>chief and Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Doctrine</hi> which they Preach, and Teach in all their Aſſemblies and Congregations, according to the Word and Goſpel of Chriſt: And upon which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103245:15"/>we are ſure many thouſands have <hi>Built, by the Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and Teaching, and Operations of the ſpirit of the Lord, and are by the ſame ſpirit joyned, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited in a firm and everlaſting bond and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion to Chriſt;</hi> whereby we have <hi>Light, Life, Vertue, Strength, Wiſdom, and all Grace from this Root and Fountain, our precious Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Author proceeds fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">2. Strong Man Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>p.</hi> 13.</note> and tells us, That <hi>the Faith of the People called Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers is the Faith of the Son of God, Jeſus Chriſt is the Author and Finiſher of it;</hi> it renews the whole Man.
<note place="margin">2. The Quakers Faith.</note> By <hi>this Faith ſin is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, ſlain, and Mortified per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly; the heart purified, the World conquered, the Soul Sanctified, Juſtified, and Saved perfectly:</hi> But the <hi>Faith</hi> of all others is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholy, Dead, Imperfect Faith;</hi> it Sanctifies but <hi>in part</hi> (as they ſay) and ſo will never ſave to the <hi>uttermoſt.</hi> Thus far he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is another double groſs untruth, both as to themſelves and others: If their <hi>Faith</hi> be the true Juſtifying, Saving Faith of God's Elect, then it would Evidence it ſelf by the <hi>Fruits and Effects of Faith,</hi> which the Scriptures ſpeak of, and all the Saints Experience in their Meaſure; as might be made evident in particulars: It would (as it does in all true Believers) <hi>purifie the Heart, and work by Love; to God, to his People, to his Word and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, to all the things that are of God.</hi> But fine Words and Profeſſions will not prove, or evidence true Faith.</p>
            <p>This Author does plainly manifeſt to a Spiritual Eye that that which he calls <hi>Faith</hi> in himſelf, (and in ſuch as are like him) is but <hi>preſumption,</hi> wrought by the great Deceiver, the <hi>ſeducing ſpirit,</hi> in weak,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103245:15"/>Ignorant, Proud Hearts and Minds; for it hath not <hi>purified their Hearts,</hi> neither doth it <hi>work by Love,</hi> but on the contrary; their Hearts are yet <hi>Dark, Blind, Ignorant of God, of themſelves, of the Truths of God, of the People of God;</hi> they know not the Difference between <hi>Nature and Grace:</hi> They call <hi>Natural Conſcience and Reaſon</hi> (which is in every Man and Woman by Nature) <hi>God, Chriſt, his Spirit, the true Light;</hi> which will Save and Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie whoſoever hearkens to it, and believes in it. I ſay, Faith hath not Purified their Hearts from <hi>this Blindneſs and Ignorance,</hi> nor from <hi>Pride, Self-love,</hi> and many other Corruptions, Manifeſt, and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in, and amongſt them; as any groſs ſins or Abominations are in the Profaneſt Perſons in the World.</p>
            <p>Neither does <hi>this Faith of theirs</hi> (which they boaſt of) work by <hi>Love; Love to God, Love to all his People, to the Law, and Word of God,</hi> as it did in <hi>David; O how I love thy Law! it is my Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion continually,</hi> Pſal. 119. but they Love not the Scriptures, neither are they led <hi>by the ſpirit</hi> ſpeaking in them, but <hi>by a falſe spirit</hi> ſpeaking in themſelves, contrary to the ſpirit in the Scriptures. And as for their <hi>Love,</hi> it is but <hi>a ſelf-love;</hi> it confines it ſelf to <hi>their own party,</hi> that ſay as they ſay, and do even as they do, that are one with them in the ſame things; and in the Pride of their Hearts reject all others, though the moſt eminent Saints upon the Earth.</p>
            <p>How far then is <hi>this Faith of theirs</hi> (which they boaſt of, accounting it far better than all others) from <hi>purifying their Heart perfectly,</hi> as he there ſays; that hath not yet purified it from theſe gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and apparent Corruptions and ſins; as <hi>Ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103245:16"/>Pride</hi> in a high Degree, <hi>Self-love, Hatred, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing, Diſowning, Scandalizing, and Separating from the Lords People of all perſwaſions,</hi> though Select Congregations, and Precious in the ſight of the Lord, and dear as the Apple of his Eye: O the ſubtil, ſtrong, ſeducing ſpirit is got into <hi>a ſtrong Hold indeed, and Fortified himſelf therein,</hi> that can make them Speak, and Declare theſe <hi>Lyes in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and theſe Doctrines of Devils,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calls them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This Author of the Strong Man Armed caſt out goes on,
<note place="margin">3. <hi>The Quakers Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi>
               </note> and tells us, what <hi>Knowledge</hi> the People (the Quakers) have attained unto above all others; and ſaith, <hi>it is Spiritual and Experimental, from the immediate <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and proceeds not from <hi>hear-ſay, but Divine Revelation;</hi> this is Life Eternal to know God, which is <hi>Light, yea, the Father of Lights,</hi> and that the <hi>Light within is the Son of God.</hi> This is that Myſtery that is hid from the Wiſe and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and Revealed unto Babes: They know him not, but ſay, it is the <hi>Devil;</hi> or at beſt, but the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> and ſo they know not whence it is, and yet he hath enlightned Thouſands; and it was never known that the Devil, or the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Converted any to the Lord.</p>
            <p>For Anſwer hereunto,
<note place="margin">Quakers put Light for Darkneſs, and Darkneſs for Light.</note> I ſay, it is a very dreadful thing for any Man to put <hi>Darkneſs for Light, and Light for Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> (as this Man does) a Dreadful Woe is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt ſuch, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Woe to them that call Evil Good, and Good Evil; that put Darkneſs for Light, and Light for Darkneſs.</hi> If therefore the <hi>Light</hi> in thee be <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> how great is that <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Mat. 6.23?</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:103245:16"/>
            <p>But the Light in Thee, <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> is Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: That is to ſay, Thy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding is Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Blinded,</hi> not onely by <hi>Corrupt Nature,</hi> (as all Unregenerate Men and Women are) but Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo <hi>by the Prince of Darkneſs,</hi> as is Manifeſt by all thy Writings, that thou put'ſt <hi>Darkneſs</hi> for <hi>Light:</hi> For the Minds of all natural Men are <hi>dark,</hi> yea, <hi>darkneſs it ſelf;</hi> they cannot ſee <hi>Spiritual things</hi> no more than a Blind Man can Diſtinguiſh Colours; or than a Man that hath his ſight, in a dark Dungeon, can Diſcern, or Diſtinguiſh of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. <hi>The Natural Man perceiveth not the things of God, neither can he know them, becauſe they are Spiritually Diſcerned,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. Such an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and knowledge haſt thou, and others of thy Principles and Ways. Thou and they (it ſeems) have attained to <hi>this Knowledge,</hi> which others (though the moſt Wiſe of other Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) have not attained to: That <hi>the Light within is the Son of God, whom he hath ſent, and that this is in every Man and Woman, and to know, and abide in this Light is Life Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am grieved for this thine and their <hi>Ignorance,</hi> though thou calleſt it <hi>Knowledge.</hi> Now, if ye will Hearken to the true Light indeed, he will drive away, and diſpell <hi>this Darkneſs,</hi> and ſhine into the Heart, and give <hi>the Light of the Knowledge of God, in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Thou deſpiſeſt the Knowledge of all others, that comes by <hi>hear-ſay meaning the Scriptures,</hi> as it plainly appears; thine (thou ſayeſt) is <hi>by Immediate Revelation:</hi> But let me ask thee and them, how comes any one to <hi>know Chriſt,</hi> and to <hi>Believe in him,</hi> but <hi>by the Scriptures?</hi> How ſhall they <hi>Believe in him of whom they have not heard but by the Word of the Goſpel,</hi> Rom. 10? As for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103245:17"/>
               <hi>Immediate Revelations</hi> we are not to Believe any of them, further than as they are Conſonant, and Agreeable to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which the Holy Spirit of God hath already ſpoken; elſe we may believe a Lye, from a falſe Spirit; Witneſs <hi>thy own Caſe,</hi> with many others alſo, who have liſtned to <hi>Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Revelations,</hi> and prefer them before the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the Spirit of God in the Scriptures;</hi> which (undoubtedly) will be your undoing, except ye Repent, and ſee your Error, for in thus doing ye prefer <hi>the Devils Doctrine</hi> before <hi>the Doctrine of Chriſt:</hi> Yea, ye ſhut out the <hi>ſayings of Chriſt,</hi> and take in the <hi>ſayings of Satan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we have no way to <hi>try the Spirits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Three Spirits ſpeak in Men.</note> how ſhall we know what Spirit it is that ſpeaketh in us; for there are <hi>three diſtinct Spirits</hi> that ſpeak in Men at certain times: Sometimes the Spirit of God moves and works in Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>he dwells and abides in his People,</hi> but not in his Enemies; he ſometimes <hi>Reproves wicked Men, the World, of ſin, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, There is <hi>the ſeducing ſpirit,</hi> he alſo moves in the Minds of Men, both in the <hi>Godly and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly:</hi> He moved <hi>David,</hi> and prevailed with him, to his hurt: <hi>This ſpirit</hi> all are to Watch and War againſt daily. He ſometimes moves to that which is Good, as well as to Evil, but with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to deceive thereby: he ſubtilly mixeth ſome <hi>Currant Coyn</hi> with the <hi>Counterfeit,</hi> that it may the better paſs without ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Many things proceed immediately from a <hi>Mans own ſpirit</hi> (his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Reaſon, and Natural Conſcience</hi>) many things are wrought and Forged in this Mint, according to a Mans Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Faculties.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:103245:17"/>
            <p>Now, how ſhall a Man know <hi>from which of theſe ſpirits</hi> things proceed,
<note place="margin">Tryal of Spirits.</note> and whether they be good or not, or what they tend to, but by ſome <hi>known, fixed, perfect Rule;</hi> and what is that, but the <hi>Scriptures?</hi> The <hi>ſpirit of Truth</hi> having given them as a <hi>Light to our Feet,</hi> and a <hi>Lanthorn to our Paths,</hi> even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o our <hi>inward Paths,</hi> (the Movings and workings of our Hearts) as well as to our <hi>outward Paths</hi> in our Converſations: He that ſhall take heed to the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Revelations,</hi> and Motions in his heart, and follow them, and not take heed to the <hi>Revelations of the ſpirit in the Scriptures</hi> to compare them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhall be ſure to erre; in this thou, <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> and many more of the <hi>Quakers;</hi> are ſad Inſtances and prooſs of this Truth at this day; for if the <hi>ſeducing ſpirit</hi> once perceive that any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will take heed to, Obſerve, and follow the <hi>Dictates and Motions within him,</hi> and never try them <hi>by the Scriptures,</hi> he may then ſuggeſt what he will, and never be Diſcovered, but Obeyed as God, eſpecially in all thoſe things that have a ſhew, and Reſemblance of good in them, and which weak and Ignorant Minds are not able to Diſcern or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh; partly, by Reaſon of the Lowneſs and Weakneſs of their Natural Parts and Faculties; and partly, by Reaſon of the Weakneſs of Grace, and ſmall Meaſures of Light, if any at all be here.</p>
            <p>And Obſerve this alſo for a certain Truth,
<note place="margin">Light of Nature ſees ſome Sins, and ſome Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> That <hi>Natural Conſcience</hi> in all Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men does <hi>Rebuke, and Reprove them for many groſs Evils,</hi> which they at any time are guilty of: If they Commit <hi>Murder or Theft,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103245:18"/>or Cheat and Deceive their Neighbour,</hi> or ſuch like; this <hi>Light within every one</hi> is ſufficient to ſee theſe to be Evil, and that they ought not to be: And <hi>this Natural Light within</hi> will alſo ſecretly move them to ſome things that are <hi>good and Honeſt,</hi> to do to others, as they would have others to do unto them: It ſhews them that <hi>Meekneſs, Patience, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Chaſtity, Charity,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Moral Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> are good and commendable in the Lives of Men; and when they follow after theſe things (as many Heathens have done) then their <hi>Conſciences (or the Light within)</hi> will Excuſe them, and they have Peace in ſo doing: But if they do thoſe other <hi>groſs Evils,</hi> then this <hi>Light within</hi> will <hi>Accuſe, Diſquiets and Diſturb them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this <hi>Light within</hi> can never Diſcover to them <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Evils and ſins:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Light within ſees not Spiritual ſins.</note> As <hi>Pride, Self-love, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief, Hypocriſie,</hi> and ſuch like; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it lead them to ſee, or Diſcern <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, or the things of Chriſt,</hi> Revealed in the Goſpel; the <hi>things of the Kingdom of God, and the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs thereof,</hi> without the <hi>Light of the ſpirit of God, and the Scriptures.</hi> All this is but <hi>Nature,</hi> it is not <hi>Grace;</hi> neither is it <hi>Chriſt the true Light,</hi> as this <hi>Author of the ſtrong Man Armed caſt out,</hi> and his Followers do call it, and contend earneſtly for it, and account it <hi>true Knowledge,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Degree of Knowledge,</hi> as no other Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors have attained to but themſelves, as he there tells us: Whereas indeed they have not yet reached to the very <hi>firſt Principles of the Oracles of God:</hi> And therefore thou, <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> did'ſt well to leave off to be a <hi>Pariſh Prieſt,</hi> and to be any longer <hi>a Teacher among the Independents:</hi> As thou told'ſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103245:18"/>us, I wiſh thou would'ſt alſo leave off to be a <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> any longer among the Quakers, or rather <hi>a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer.</hi> And firſt go, and Hear, and Learn, and be Inſtructed in the <hi>ſaving Knowledge of Chriſt, as the Scriptures have Revealed him;</hi> leſt thou be one of thoſe who will Cry at the laſt day, <hi>Lord, Lord, have we not Propheſied in thy Name, and in thy Name done many Wonderful Works:</hi> And then thou hear among others, that Dreadful Sentence, <hi>Depart from me, ye Workers of Iniquity, I know you not;</hi> I own not your Teachings, your Prophecyings, or Declarings in my Name; ye have Blaſphemed my Name, and cauſed my Name, my Goſpel, and my People to be deſpiſed amongſt many by your means; ye Diſowned, Reproached, and Separated from my People, and in as much as ye did it unto theſe my Brethren, ye did it unto me.</p>
            <p>You the <hi>Teaching Quakers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Quakers guilty of theſe two great ſins.</note> are guilty of thoſe <hi>two great Evils</hi> that the People were guilty of in the <hi>Prophet Jeremiah</hi>'s Time, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.12. <hi>The Prophets Propheſied Lies unto them,</hi> and Taught the People to forſake the Living and true God, and to look unto Idols; and the Lord pleads with them about it, and tells them ſuch a thing was never heard of amongſt any People or Nations, that they ſhould Change their God; but this ſottiſh People, who had no underſtanding, they changed their Glory for a Vain thing, for that which cannot Profit: And it is ſuch ſtupendious Folly and Madneſs, that he calls to the very Heavens to Behold it, and Admire it; <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Be aſtoniſhed, O ye Heavens, at this, and be horribly afraid: Be ye very Deſolate, ſaith the Lord;</hi> v. 13. <hi>For my People have Committed two Evils, They have forſaken me, the Fountain of Living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103245:19"/>and hewed them out Ciſterns, broken Ciſterns, that can hold no Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Conſider, ye have even done thus; <hi>Ye have forſaken the Living and true God, the Saviour of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> (all that do Believe in him, and reſt upon him and his Righteouſneſs for Juſtification) and ye have ſet upon an <hi>Idol, Natural Conſcience,</hi> and truſt to it, and <hi>your own Perſonal Righteouſneſs and Obedience, for Life, Juſtification, and Salvation;</hi> and what are theſe, but as their <hi>Broken Ciſterns,</hi> that can Afford no Refreſhing in a Time of Need? Take heed then, and be Inſtructed, thou and they, and Teach no longer this <hi>Falſe Doctrine,</hi> that the <hi>Light in every Man and Woman is Chriſt, the true Light;</hi> ſeeing it is but <hi>a Creature,</hi> and in every one by Nature: Will ye Debaſe, and Degrade <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by calling him <hi>a Creature?</hi> Or Deiſie <hi>the Creature,</hi> by calling it <hi>Chriſt the true Light?</hi> It is true, it is <hi>from Chriſt,</hi> he is the <hi>Creator of it,</hi> as of all other Creatures in the World, the World was made by him, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him was nothing made that was made, <hi>John</hi> 1. How then can it be <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Is the <hi>Carpenter the houſe</hi> that he hath Builded? Or is the <hi>houſe the Carpenter?</hi> Are they both one and the ſame? Is not the <hi>Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Man,</hi> and the <hi>houſe his Workman-ſhip?</hi> Is not <hi>God the Creator</hi> of all things, and <hi>his Creatures di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Beings?</hi> Why doſt thou Confound them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and make them all one?</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Chriſt</hi> be the <hi>true Light,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience his Created Light,</hi> as the <hi>Sun</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament are alſo his Created Lights: Let theſe and other Lights be diſtinct, and known one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not confounded together any more.</p>
            <p>For this <hi>Light of Natural Conſcience</hi> (which is in <hi>every Man and Woman</hi>) as it does now in this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103245:19"/>World Reprove for many <hi>groſs</hi> ſins, and move unto many <hi>Moral Vertues and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; Excuſing for the one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Light within ſhall be in Hell for ever.</note> &amp; <hi>Accuſing for the other;</hi> (as we ſee it is plainly Aſſerted by the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> Rom. 1.) <hi>This Light,</hi> I ſay, will Remain, and Abide in <hi>Reprobates and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers for ever,</hi> in the next World, as well as in this; and will be there a Tormentor to them, World without end. Wilt thou and thy Followers then call it <hi>Christ, and the true Light:</hi> Take heed then, <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> and all thoſe of thy Mind, and Repent of your Errors, leſt <hi>this Light ſhine clearly, and in the midſt of that outer Darkneſs,</hi> and be as the <hi>Worm that never dyes, and a Light and Fire that ſhall never go out,</hi> or be Extinguiſhed to all Eternity.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine of the <hi>Light within takes Men off from Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Quakers draw Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to Idolatry.</note> and Directs them to look after, and follow <hi>an Idol;</hi> and this is <hi>ſo great an evil and ſin,</hi> as that it is not to be endured, nor ſpoken of, without great Indignation againſt it, and in Zeal for our precious Lord Jeſus Chriſt; who is certainly greatly provoked by it; which will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear when he begins to Execute his Wrath and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt his Enemies: We may ſee how he ſtands affected towards ſuch Perſons as ſeek to draw away the Hearts of the People from him after other gods: See <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. <hi>the whole Chapter. If there ariſe a Prophet, or any other Perſons, and ſeek to draw away the hearts of the People from the Lord, unto Idols,</hi> they were not to be ſpared, but ſhould certainly be put to Death; no, not the neareſt Friend or Relation whatſoever. <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. <hi>If thy Brother, the Son of thy Mother, or thy Son, or thy Daughter,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:103245:20"/>or the Wife of thy Boſom, or thy Friend which is as thine own ſoul, ſhall entice thee ſecretly, ſaying, let us go and ſerve other gods: Thou ſhalt not conſent unto him, nor hearken unto him, neither ſhall thine Eye pity him, neither ſhalt thou ſpare, neither ſhalt thou conceal him:</hi> Ver. 9. <hi>But thou ſhalt ſurely kill him, thine hand ſhall be firſt upon him, to put him to Death, and afterwards the hand of all the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if any <hi>City</hi> ſhould be known to <hi>Depart from God,</hi> and go after <hi>Idols,</hi> it was to be Burnt with Fire, and all that was in it.</p>
            <p>We ſee how Jealous God is of his Glory, <hi>His Glory he will not give to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Quakers under Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Judgments.</note> 
               <hi>nor his praiſe to Graven Images;</hi> ſurely he is God, and Changeth not; as he hath Diſcovered his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt his Enemies, ſo he doth, and will do ſtill: Therefore take Notice of theſe things, <hi>ye Seducers among the Quakers;</hi> for although God doth not deal with Men now, in theſe Goſpel-days, to puniſh them with <hi>Corporal or Temporal puniſhments,</hi> as in former times under the <hi>Old Adminiſtration;</hi> yet as ſure as God is true, he will deal with his Enemies ſeverely at laſt; and his Judgments <hi>in theſe Days of the Goſpel are more ſpiritual than formerly: Spiritual Judgments are greater than Corporal Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments; Hardneſs of Heart, Blindneſs of mind, a Reprobate Senſe, a Seared Conſcience;</hi> theſe are Dreadful Judgments: And ſurely theſe Judgments and tokens of Gods Anger are upon the very Men that we are ſpeaking of, <hi>the falſe Prophets and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers among the Quakers,</hi> as is plainly to be ſeen; and their <hi>Sin is ſeen in their Puniſhments.</hi> They ſeek to draw away the Hearts of People from the Lord, from our <hi>Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> from his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:103245:20"/>
               <hi>Word and Goſpel,</hi> unto <hi>an Idol</hi> of their own ſetting up, and would have all People to bow unto it, and Worſhip it, and truſt in it, and Obey it; and therefore God hath juſtly with-drawn himſelf from them: He denies them <hi>his Grace, his Spirit,</hi> yea, in a great Meaſure <hi>the very Light of Nature,</hi> which is common to other Men, as is ſeen by their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Tenets, and Principles,</hi> and by their Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, Irrational Arguing, in maintaining their <hi>Idle Fancies,</hi> which have neither <hi>Scripture,</hi> nor any <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Reaſon</hi> to uphold them. And as is ſeen alſo by their Rage and Anger againſt any that do oppoſe their Errors, ſeeking to turn them to the Truth; they find <hi>hard and bitter ſpeeches, and Railing Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations</hi> againſt them for ſo doing. And as the <hi>heart of God</hi> is againſt them, ſo alſo are the <hi>hearts of his People;</hi> for Their heart goes where the heart of God goes: And this alſo Declares their ſin, as it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a puniſhment due to them. So that <hi>theſe Judgments</hi> are not ſmall that are upon them, <hi>even in this Life,</hi> though they may yet eſcape other <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal puniſhments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> What does it avail them to ſay, They do not ſeek to <hi>draw away Peoples Hearts from Christ,</hi> but rather to <hi>Direct their Minds to Chriſt;</hi> they teach them to <hi>take heed to the Light within every Man and Woman, which is Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is Anſwered, This is falſe, ye do not ſeek to Direct Peoples Minds <hi>to Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>to an Idol, Natural Conſcience,</hi> as hath been proved here, and by many others formerly: <hi>Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, Chriſt is not Mocked;</hi> it is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye give it the <hi>Name of Chriſt:</hi> He is the more provoked by your making uſe of <hi>his Name,</hi> and denying him <hi>his Worſhip,</hi> that <hi>Love and Obedience</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:103245:21"/>that is due unto him; <hi>that truſt and confidence</hi> that ought to be put in him, <hi>that Glory and Praiſe</hi> that ought to be given unto him; all is taken away <hi>from Chriſt,</hi> and given <hi>to this Idol:</hi> Ye do alſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly <hi>Diſhonour him,</hi> and <hi>Blaſpheme him,</hi> by En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituling him to <hi>falſe Doctrines,</hi> and <hi>Erroneous Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions;</hi> ſaying, it is from, or by the <hi>Light within;</hi> and in the <hi>External Light</hi> ye ſee, and ſpeak theſe and theſe things; yea, many times when ye utter <hi>Railing ſpeeches, Lies, and falſe Accuſations againſt his People,</hi> in ſeeking to do you good. O dreadful <hi>Blindneſs and Hardneſs of Heart!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Does <hi>Christ within</hi> deny <hi>Chriſt without?</hi> Does the <hi>Light within</hi> deny the <hi>Perſon of Chriſt</hi> (as ye do in your Pamphlets) his being in Heaven, and his Coming from thence in Glory to Judge the World in Righteouſneſs, even by <hi>that Man whom God the Father hath appointed:</hi> Had you not <hi>a double or treble vail of Darkneſs</hi> upon your Minds you would never ſpeak after this ſort.</p>
            <p>Ye ſay,
<note place="margin">The Quakers Perfection: In Sin.</note> ye Witneſs <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection:</hi> Indeed ſo ye do: Ye prove it to all againſt your ſelves: And we Witneſs your <hi>Perfection</hi> alſo; all that know your Principles and Ways, do Witneſs that ye are come to <hi>Perfection, to Perfection in Sin,</hi> to the <hi>higheſt Degrees of ſinning,</hi> your Iniquities are even <hi>full,</hi> or very near it; for how can ye riſe <hi>Higher?</hi> what ſteps are there for you yet <hi>to aſcend up unto,</hi> above what ye have <hi>already attained?</hi> Ye have already denied the <hi>Holy one, and the Juſt, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> that bought us; ye have <hi>Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame;</hi> yea, ye have <hi>trodden him under foot, and counted the blood of the Covenant as a common thing,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:103245:21"/>and done deſpight to the Spirit of Grace,</hi> denying <hi>his true Operations in his People,</hi> and alſo Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly Attributing the <hi>Inſpirations of the Devil</hi> unto the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> in your ſelves; ye have deſpiſed the <hi>Word of God, the Scriptures, the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus;</hi> and therein the tenders of <hi>Rich and free Grace in the Covenant of Life and Peace,</hi> and preferred <hi>your own vain Fancies;</hi> yea, <hi>the ſubtil inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations and inſpirations of ſeducing ſpirits</hi> before the clear <hi>truths of the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> and reſting in <hi>your own Righteouſneſs for Juſtification;</hi> and what can ye do more, or worſe?</p>
            <p>Ye have alſo <hi>Deſpiſed, Rejected, Diſowned, and Separated from the people of the Lord,</hi> all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Churches, Congregations, and Aſſemblies of the Saints,</hi> yea, and <hi>Reproached</hi> them alſo, and uttered <hi>many hard and bitter ſpeeches</hi> againſt them, and that for ſeeking to do you good, in turning you from the <hi>ways of ſin and Death:</hi> And being lifted up in your ſelves in the height of your <hi>Pride and vain Minds;</hi> ye have thought and ſaid of your ſelves, that <hi>ye are the moſt holy people upon Earth; yea, the onely people of God upon the Earth.</hi> And what can ye ſay, or do more, or worſe than theſe things? Have ye not attained the <hi>higheſt degrees of ſinning,</hi> even to ſuch <hi>a Perfection</hi> as the Nature of Man is capable of, or that Satan can bring it unto? and therefore we witneſs <hi>your perfection</hi> in theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
            <p>But as to <hi>Perfection in Grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Quakers Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Grace.</note> as ye vainly think of your ſelves, (and would have others to eſteem of you alſo,) ye are at the remoteſt diſtance that may be,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>In Knowledge.</hi>
               </note> ſeeing that ye have not as yet laid <hi>the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:103245:22"/>of the Knowledge of Chriſt:</hi> Yea, are Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (even your Teachers) of the very <hi>firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Oracles of God;</hi> ye know not the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between <hi>Nature and Grace,</hi> ye are not yet able to diſtinguiſh between <hi>Natural Light</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience of every Man and Woman,</hi> and the <hi>true Light, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but miſtake the one for the other: Ye are not able to diſcern the workings of <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> and <hi>the ſeducing ſpirit,</hi> but mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake the one for the other: Ye are ſo Ignorant and Blind, that ye think and ſay, Men muſt be Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>by the works of the Law, a Mans own perſonal Obedience,</hi> and not by the <hi>Imputed Righteouſneſs of Chriſt by Faith,</hi> quite contrary to the <hi>Goſpel of Chriſt;</hi> a deadly, damning Doctrine. Herein lies your <hi>Perfection in Knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for your <hi>Perfection in Faith and Hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>In Faith and Hope.</hi>
               </note> how can ye <hi>believe,</hi> or in <hi>what,</hi> or in <hi>whom</hi> do <hi>ye Believe;</hi> ſeeing ye have <hi>denyed Chriſt, the Object of Faith to all true believers;</hi> denyed him in his <hi>Death, Righteouſneſs, Merits,</hi> and in all that he hath <hi>done and Suffered</hi> for his People: theſe things are herein, (and by others) made manifeſt againſt you by your own Writings, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>And as for your <hi>Perfection in Love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>In Love.</hi>
               </note> the chiefeſt of all Graces, ye are far from <hi>Perfection</hi> in that alſo: All the <hi>Love</hi> ye ſhew forth, is but <hi>ſelf-love to your ſelves, and among your ſelves:</hi> Every particular Perſon thinking, and eſteeming of himſelf more Highly than he ought to think, and would that all others ſhould eſteem highly of him alſo. And as for any <hi>Love to others,</hi> it is but to <hi>your own party,</hi> ſuch as ſay as ye ſay, and do as ye do: And becauſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:103245:22"/>they (poor, ignorant, ſilly people) are willing to hang upon your Lips (the <hi>Teachers</hi>) and to take all for granted that ye ſay, as if your ſayings were the Oracles of God, for that ye Love them. They eſteem more of <hi>the ſayings of their Teachers,</hi> than of <hi>the ſayings of God;</hi> as one of them (not long ſince) expreſſing her deſires to have ſome of her <hi>Friends Books;</hi> one ſaid to her, ſhe had the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſhe might employ her ſelf there: She Anſwered, That the <hi>Bible</hi> (indeed) is a good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thing, but ſhe had rather Read ſome of her <hi>Friends Books.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So we ſee, That in all theſe things ye have <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed perfection,</hi> as ye call it, which indeed is at the <hi>furtheſt diſtance from perfection;</hi> ſo far, as not yet <hi>Witneſſing the firſt beginnings of Grace in you:</hi> But as for the other kind of <hi>Perfection,</hi> that is, <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in ſin,</hi> in the <hi>higheſt degrees of ſinning,</hi> ye do Witneſs it, and have given many clear and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold <hi>Proofs and Evidences of your perfection</hi> in that Reſpect; and we (all that fear God, who know your deadly Principles) do joyn with you <hi>in this Teſtimony, and do Witneſs alſo</hi> that ye have <hi>Witneſſed Perfection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O how have ye Deſpiſed the <hi>Free Grace of God,</hi> and Neglected <hi>great Salvation,</hi> tendred in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which all the Saints ſo highly prize and value, ſeeing God in Chriſt doth vouchſafe to condeſcend ſo low to poor ſinful Duſt and Aſhes, in the <hi>ſweet terms of the Goſpel,</hi> Offering <hi>Peace and Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Happineſs and Glory</hi> to all thoſe who will Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thereof; yea, even Intreating and Beſeeching of Miſerable ſinners to come in, and be Reconciled to him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>We as Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as if Chriſt did beſeech you by us, be ye Reconciled
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103245:23"/>to God.</hi> How then ſhall they eſcape who Neglect ſo great Salvation? Surely ſuch as are <hi>deeply wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and under the <hi>ſight and ſenſe of ſin, death and hell,</hi> the <hi>Wrath of God, the Curſe of the Law,</hi> they highly prize the <hi>Terms of the Goſpel, the Covenant of Grace, the ſweet and precious promiſes of Life, Reſt, and Peace:</hi> But thoſe that are <hi>whole</hi> ſee no need of the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> as it appears ye do not, that can make ſo light of the terms of <hi>Free-Grace and Love through Christ;</hi> as we find ye do by many paſſages in your Books.</p>
            <p>Where ſhall we find in all your <hi>Books and Pamphlets</hi> ſuch Doctrine as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> Preached,
<note place="margin">Paul Preacheth Chriſt, and not the Light in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man and Woman.</note> and wrote in all his Epiſtles, by the Inſpiration of God; he ſet forth <hi>Chriſt crucified</hi> in all places where he came, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed the people in that <hi>Fundamental Doctrine.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.2. <hi>I determined not to know any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, ſave Jeſus Chriſt and him Crucified: Paul</hi> lays aſide, and ſlights all things for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.8. <hi>Yea, doubtleſs, and I count all things but loſs, for the Excellency of the Knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſs of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win Chriſt.</hi> Ver. 9. <hi>And he found in him, not having mine own Righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but that which is through the Faith of Chriſt, the Righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We can hear <hi>no ſuch Doctrine as this amongſt the Quakers;</hi> nay, <hi>the very contrary:</hi> ſlighting the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, and the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to Believers; who of God is made <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> to them: And ſetting up <hi>their own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> and the Perfection of it, which may be made appear by their Books.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:103245:23"/>
            <p>And yet they tell (and ſo deceive) their ſimple, ſilly Hearers, that <hi>they do Declare Chriſt unto them, the Light within every Man and Woman,</hi> that <hi>is God, and Chriſt, the Saviour of the World:</hi> But will this ſerve their turn, to put <hi>the Name Chriſt</hi> upon one of his Creatures? Will <hi>Chriſt</hi> allow any to take away <hi>his Name, and his Glory, and cloath an Idol with it;</hi> and then ſay, they Declare, and ſet forth Chriſt? This is the way to divert and draw off the minds of poor Ignorant People <hi>from Chriſt,</hi> as he is Revealed in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This is <hi>the great Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Doctrine of the Devil;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Devil's Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Doctrine.</note> The <hi>chief point of Doctrine</hi> that he Teacheth his Diſciples; That is to ſay, <hi>To Deny Chriſt:</hi> Eo diſown him according as the <hi>Goſpel</hi> hath Revealed him; and then to ſet up ſomething elſe in his ſtead: Let them call it <hi>Christ</hi> if they will, that's no Matter to give it <hi>the Name,</hi> ſo it be not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he knows it will deceive Ignorant Minds the ſooner, the more eaſily: For thereby he knows they do but <hi>Mock Chriſt,</hi> and diſown him the more; and alſo the more provoke him, that Men ſhould give <hi>his Name and Title</hi> to any thing, and <hi>diſown himſelf,</hi> as theſe Men do: They call the <hi>Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt,</hi> but deny <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> as the Goſpel ſets him forth. Now, this the Devil knows is enough to ſerve his turn, and deſtroy them, and therefore he ſtill keeps the Eye of their Mind upon this, and makes them look upon it through a Multiplying Glaſs, and ſhuts the Eyes of their Mind <hi>againſt Chriſt, as he is Revealed in the Scriptures:</hi> The God of <hi>this wicked World hath Blinded the Minds of them that believe not, leſt the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould ſhine unto them:</hi> And if the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:103245:24"/>Goſpel be hid from them, it is hid to them that are loſt. We ſee in all their <hi>Declarings,</hi> in all their <hi>Books and Pamphlets,</hi> this is <hi>the Main and Chief point;</hi> to Teach their Hearers to take heed to the <hi>Light within,</hi> to the <hi>Witneſs of God within,</hi> with variety of Expreſſions to that purpoſe: But what do we hear in all their Books, and Teachings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Chriſt that was Promiſed long before he came into the World; of Chriſt that was born when the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time was come; of Chriſt that Lived amongſt us, and Preached, and Taught amongſt us the way of Salvation; of Chriſt that Dyed for us, and roſe again, and Aſcended into Heaven; that is now at the right Hand of God, making Interceſſion for us; of Chriſt that ſhall ſhortly come again in glory (and yet in his Humane Nature,) to Judge the World in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs?</hi> This is <hi>the Chriſt</hi> that the Goſpel Declares, and that all true Believers know, and own, and Teach plainly and clearly (without Equivocations and ſubtil Evaſions as theſe <hi>falſe Teachers among the Quakers</hi> uſe to ſpeak of him,) and whom all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers have Received by Faith, who dwells <hi>in them, and they in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what do we hear of all this in the Teachings of theſe Men among the <hi>Quakers?</hi> Nay, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, their Doctrines in their <hi>Books and Pamphlets</hi> that they frequently ſend forth, do <hi>Directly Oppoſe theſe things:</hi> And therefore we may ſafely conclude their Doctrine is the <hi>Doctrine of Devils;</hi> for if all the Devils in Hell ſhould combine together, and joyn their Curſed Craft and Malice <hi>againſt Chriſt and the Souls of Men,</hi> they could not bring forth a more <hi>Damning Doctrine</hi> than this is: For, to <hi>Deny Christ is to deny all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:103245:24"/>
            <p>What then ſhall we ſay to theſe Men, or of them? Surely,
<note place="margin">Obſtinate Quakers to be Rejected.</note> ſeeing theſe things are ſo, That they have thus <hi>deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord that bought us,</hi> and Preach up <hi>another Chriſt,</hi> and maintain and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>this their Idol,</hi> in Oppoſition <hi>to Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Goſpel</hi> hath Declared him; and ſlight, and Deſpiſe the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> we have grounds to conclude they are Men of <hi>Corrupt Minds, of Seared Conſciences, Idolaters, and Hereticks.</hi> Now, the Apoſtle by the Inſpiration of God, gives us a Rule, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>Reject an Heretick after once or twice Admoniſhed,</hi> but theſe Men have been often Admoniſhed, Pleaded, and Diſputed with; and they regard not Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they reſiſt the Truth, and the Spirit of Grace and Truth ſpeaking in the Scriptures, and in, and by his People, they will not hear, they will not regard the Counſel of God: But in <hi>their Ignorance and Pride</hi> they deſpiſe both <hi>God and Men;</hi> and do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their <hi>own Idle and vain Fancies, and Satans ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile falſe Inſinuations,</hi> before the <hi>Teachings of the Spirit of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If God ſhould work a Miracle, and raiſe up <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> Paul from the Dead, to Declare againſt them and their Doctrines, they would no more regard him, nor his Teachings, than they regard <hi>Tho. Hicks,</hi> in his three Dialogues Between a Chriſtian and a Quaker; or than they regard any other <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Chriſt,</hi> who pleads with them, and lays <hi>the very truths of God</hi> before them, as it is Revealed by the <hi>Spirit in the Goſpel.</hi> We are aſſured of this, from <hi>Luke</hi> 16.31. If they will not Hear <hi>Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> neither will they hear, though <hi>one ſhould riſe from the Dead:</hi> So if they will not hear <hi>Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the Goſpel,</hi> if they will not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:103245:25"/>hear <hi>the Scriptures;</hi> neither will they be perſwaded to imbrace the Truth, though one ſhould be ſent to them from the Dead. Nay, if <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> ſhould come, and ſpeak to them in that mean ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that he was when he converſed among us here below, theſe People would regard him no more than the hardned Jews did in their Day: For <hi>they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and Deny him now, his Doctrine, and his Perſon, in his Merits, Righteouſneſs, Satisfaction,</hi> &amp;c, And ſo would do, if he were <hi>Perſonally preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that my Judgment is, Let them alone, <hi>they be blind Leaders of the blind;</hi> they talk of <hi>a Light within,</hi> but <hi>the Light in them is Darkneſs;</hi> and it is <hi>a great darkneſs, a double darkneſs;</hi> more than a <hi>ſingle Natural darkneſs</hi> (as is the ſtate of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind by Nature) but alſo <hi>a darkneſs added</hi> to that; even <hi>a darkneſs as a puniſhment or a Judgment, a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial darkneſs. Natural darkneſs</hi> is the <hi>ſin</hi> of man, but <hi>this darkneſs is the Judgment of God:</hi> That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they regard not the Truth, they will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it in the Love thereof, therefore hath God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them up to <hi>ſtrong deluſions to believe lies:</hi> That ſeeing they will not <hi>believe the Truth, they ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Lyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Difference ſhall we think is there between theſe Men,
<note place="margin">The Quakers ſin is like the great ſin of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened Jews.</note> 
               <hi>the Teachers among the Quakers,</hi> who have delivered theſe <hi>Damnable Doctrines</hi> afore-mentioned, (being the <hi>Doctrines of Devils;</hi>) and ſtill maintain them? What difference, I ſay between them and <hi>thoſe Jews who Blaſpemed the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and ran into that <hi>ſin unto death?</hi> Thoſe Jews Rejected Chriſt, his ſayings and Doctrine, which he Taught among them, and they told him that he had a Devil: Chriſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:103245:25"/>tells them then, after that he had often ſpoken unto them, and Taught them, and they would not hear him, nor regard his ſayings, he then Declares un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them their <hi>dreadful ſtate:</hi> And ſurely the ſin of theſe Men looks ſo like unto the ſin of thoſe <hi>Jews,</hi> that I think it's hard for any Man to diſtinguiſh them otherwiſe than by ſaying, That the <hi>ſin of theſe Teachers</hi> does Exceed the ſin of <hi>thoſe Jews:</hi> The ſin of theſe Men ſeems to be much <hi>Aggravated,</hi> in that they have not onely heard all thoſe <hi>Sayings, and Doctrines of Christ,</hi> which he Preached among the Jews, but they have had the <hi>Truths of God Offered and tendred to them by others alſo;</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, and Diſciples of Chriſt</hi> have ſpoken to them <hi>in the Scriptures</hi> (which thoſe Jews never had.) And alſo, many of the <hi>Miniſters, Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt</hi> have ſpoken to them, and tendred <hi>the very Truths of the Goſpel to them;</hi> yea, many others of <hi>his Faithful Saints and Servants,</hi> have from time to time ſpoken to them, and Adviſed, Counſelled, and Admoniſhed them, and yet all in vain; they have Rejected all, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed all; and have <hi>(as Swine)</hi> Trampled <hi>Pearls under their Feet, and turned again, and Rent thoſe that brought them;</hi> they have <hi>Reviled them, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached them</hi> for ſo doing; ſo that to what purpoſe ſhould any Man go about to <hi>Teach theſe Teachers,</hi> who are not <hi>capable to Learn,</hi> as being <hi>Blinded, and Hardned, and Sealed up</hi> (as is fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed) <hi>even to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> having their <hi>Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron? Men of Corrupt Minds, Reprobate to every good work,</hi> without <hi>Judgment,</hi> unfit either to <hi>Teach or Learn:</hi> For we know there have been many ſuch in former days, who were guilty of <hi>this great ſin;</hi> ſome ſuch were contemporaries with the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103245:26"/>
               <hi>Prophet Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 6.10. <hi>Make the Heart of this People fat, and make their Ears heavy, and ſhut their Eyes,</hi> &amp;c, So alſo many ſuch were in the Time of our <hi>Lord and Saviour,</hi> Mat. 13.15. <hi>This Peoples Heart is waxed groſs, and their Ears are dull of Hearing, and their Eyes they have cloſed, leſt at any time they ſhould See with their Eyes, and Hear with their Ears, and ſhould <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand with their Heart, and ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Converted, and I ſhould heal them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Generation there are juſt ſuch a People (even thoſe of whom we ſpeak;) they ſhut their <hi>Ears</hi> and their <hi>Eyes,</hi> and their <hi>Hearts againſt Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Truths of the Goſpel:</hi> All the Advice and Councels of Men, which are according to the <hi>Truth,</hi> all are Rejected and Deſpiſed. The <hi>Inſpirations of the ſpirit of God</hi> are refuſed, but the <hi>Inſpirations of the ſpirit of Deluſion</hi> are readily Received and Embraced. My Judgment is therefore, let them be <hi>Rejected as Hereticks,</hi> having been ſo often <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed;</hi> as Men that are hardned to Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Hearers among the Quakers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Advice to the Hearers among the Quakers.</note> my Councel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you is, <hi>Separate your ſelves from the Congregations, and Meetings of theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Men,</hi> leſt ye be Conſumed in all their ſin: Be as much afraid of them, and of their <hi>Poyſonous Doctrines,</hi> as ye would be afraid to eat of <hi>a diſh of Meat before you on the Table, that had rank Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in it,</hi> of which ye were told, and fully aſſured of it: Would ye eat of ſuch a Diſh? I know ye would not; Remember and conſider <hi>Eternity,</hi> it will be well or ill with you for ever, according as ye Receive, or Refuſe the <hi>Truths of the Goſpel
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103245:26"/>now.</hi> Beware of <hi>Falſe Prophets, which come to you in Sheeps clothing, but inwardly they are Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wolves;</hi> if ye be the <hi>Sheep of Christ, follow him,</hi> and know his Voice <hi>in the Scriptures, in your hearts, and amongſt his own People,</hi> and follow not <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> that bring <hi>ſtrange falſe Doctrines</hi> about the <hi>Light within;</hi> and in many other things which have been mentioned, contrary to the Mind of Chriſt Revealed in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Theſe People, the Quakers,
<note place="margin">The Quakers great Idol near falling.</note> have forſaken <hi>the Fountain of Living Waters,</hi> and have run to <hi>broken Cisterns:</hi> And ſeeing they have forſaken the <hi>Living and true God,</hi> the Glory of his People, and ſet up <hi>an Idol, a falſe Chriſt, the Light in every Man and Woman that cometh into the World:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore bring againſt this their <hi>falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> ſeveral <hi>Arguments from Scripture,</hi> to prove the Vanity and falſhood of it, as ſo many <hi>Pieces of Ordnance</hi> Planted againſt <hi>this great Idol,</hi> which the Quakers have ſet up and Worſhip, that ſo it may fall, as <hi>Dagon,</hi> before the <hi>Ark of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas they ſay, That <hi>Christ the true Light is in every Man and Woman that cometh into the World:</hi> This is not a Truth; becauſe in whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Christ is and dwells,</hi> he does <hi>enlighten</hi> that Soul with <hi>true Light, ſaving Light, ſupernatural Light,</hi> even by <hi>himſelf,</hi> by <hi>his Spirit,</hi> and by <hi>the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's true, all wicked Men that come into the World have <hi>Lights</hi> of Chriſt's making, he Created them, which <hi>Enlighten all Mankind,</hi> and that both <hi>Outwardly and Inwardly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They are Enlightned <hi>Outwardly,</hi> by Lights that God hath Created, and ſet in the Heavens, the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103245:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:103245:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:103245:28"/>
               <hi>Sun and the Moon,</hi> by which all are Enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And then Secondly, All Men and Women that come into the World, are Enlightned with <hi>Inward Light</hi> alſo; <hi>Reaſon and Natural Conſcience:</hi> So Chriſt the true Light, Enlightneth all that come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, which is all that is Intended and meant by that place, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. But <hi>Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is the true Light, the Light of Lights;</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth <hi>his own People immediately by himſelf,</hi> and by <hi>his Spirit,</hi> which the wicked of the World are not Partakers of; they have onely thoſe <hi>common Lights</hi> afore-mentioned. As is fully and plainly Proved by theſe <hi>Scripture Arguments.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="propositions">
               <head>Ten Propoſitions Proved by Scripture.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thoſe in whom Chriſt is, and and dwells,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Firſt Argument.</hi> Prop. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>he Inlightens them with ſpiritual Light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But wicked Men and women are not Inlightned with ſpiritual Light; therefore Chriſt is not in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men and women.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Proof of theſe <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> both <hi>Major and Minor</hi> (then the <hi>Concluſion</hi> drawn from them muſt needs be granted by all Rational Men,) See <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Ye ſometimes were Darkneſs, but now are ye Light in the Lord: walk as Children of Light.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to turn Men <hi>from Darkneſs to Light,</hi> Acts 26.18. And we ſee the <hi>Corinthians</hi> who <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were Darkneſs,</hi> and afterwards Converted, <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. <hi>God who commanded the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined in our Hearts, to give the Light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> But as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:103245:28"/>for others who were Carnal and Unregenerate, he tells us, they were <hi>in Darkneſs, and Darkneſs in them,</hi> v. 4. <hi>And the God of this World had blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the minds of thoſe that believe not, leſt the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>In whomſoever Chriſt is,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Second Argument.</hi> Prop. 2.</note> and dwells, he quickens them, and makes them ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually Alive.</p>
                  <p>But unregenerate Men and Women are not Spiritually Alive, but Dead; Therefore Chriſt is not in unregenerate Men and Women.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proof.</hi> Eph. 2.1. <hi>You hath he quickned, who were Dead in Treſpaſſes and ſins.</hi> And Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of the Jews, That they would not come unto him, <hi>that they might have Life,</hi> John 5.40. plainly implying, that <hi>they were Dead, and that they might have Life,</hi> if they had come unto him.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt is not in thoſe who are not in him.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Third Argument.</hi> Prop. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the Unregenerate World are not in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Chriſt is not in the Unregenerate World.</p>
               </q>
               <p>For Proof hereof ſee <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>You that were ſometimes alienated, and Enemies in your mind by wicked works, yet now hath he Reconciled,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. <hi>If any Man be in Chriſt, he is a New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate Perſons</hi> are <hi>New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> therefore not in Chriſt. And Chriſt ſays plainly that he is <hi>In his People,</hi> which implies (as we may perceive, if we Obſerve the context) that he is not <hi>in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate World,</hi> John 17.23. <hi>I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:103245:29"/>in them, and thou in me.</hi> And again, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>I in them:</hi> Thoſe that Chriſt means <hi>by Them,</hi> are in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition <hi>to the World;</hi> for he hath choſen <hi>them out of the world, v.</hi> 16. the words <hi>[I in them]</hi> are very Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical, and full with this ſence, clearly implying that he is not <hi>in the world of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate perſons,</hi> even as the words before, <hi>v.</hi> 9. do plainly expreſs that he <hi>prays not for the world,</hi> but <hi>for them, his people;</hi> ſo theſe words do as plainly imply that he <hi>is in them, and not in the world,</hi> John 15.4, 5. we ſee there at large, That ſuch as <hi>abide in Chriſt, he alſo is in them,</hi> and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt is not in thoſe for whom he Prays not.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Fourth Propoſition.</hi> Prop. 4.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But,</hi> Chriſt Prays not for the unbelieving World.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi> Chriſt is not in the unbelieving World.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour tells us ſeveral times, that <hi>he is not of the world,</hi> v. 14. <hi>they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.</hi> And again, <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world;</hi> as if he had ſaid, I am none of their Company, I am not <hi>of them,</hi> nor <hi>in them;</hi> I have no ſuch Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, or Familiarity with them, as to <hi>Live in them:</hi> I am not <hi>of the world,</hi> nor <hi>in the world;</hi> I am <hi>in my People,</hi> even <hi>in thoſe</hi> which thou Father haſt given me: <hi>I in them,</hi> and thou in me.</p>
               <p>And <hi>ver.</hi> 9. He poſitively and plainly tells us, That he <hi>Prays not for the world,</hi> the <hi>wicked, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, unregenerate world;</hi> he neither <hi>Prays for them, nor is in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Fifthly, Another <hi>Propoſition, or Syllogiſm,</hi> proving that <hi>Chriſt is not in all Men and women,</hi> as the Quakers aſſert, is this.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:103245:29"/>
               <q>
                  <p>They to whom Chriſt doth not Manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by Teaching them his Mind and Will,
<note place="margin">Prop. 5.</note> Chriſt is not in them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But</hi> Chriſt doth not manifeſt himſelf to wicked and ungodly Men and Women: Therefore Chriſt is not in wicked and ungodly Men and Women.</p>
               </q>
               <p>For Proof of this <hi>Propoſition</hi> in both parts, conſider,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wicked and ungodly Men and Women</hi> are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of true <hi>ſaving Knowledge and Wiſdom;</hi> they know not the things that belong to their Peace; and are deſtroy'd for lack of <hi>Knowledge:</hi> 2 Cor. 4.4. <hi>The Devil, the god of this unbelieving World, hath blinded their Minds, leſt the Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould ſhine unto them,</hi> Chriſt Diſcovers himſelf, his Mind, and Will, in and by <hi>the Goſpel,</hi> his <hi>Spirit</hi> opening Mens Minds and Underſtandings to receive it, but Chriſt ſuffers <hi>this blindneſs of Mind</hi> to reſt upon ſome Perſons, and does not Manifeſt himſelf unto them; therefore <hi>he is not in them:</hi> One asketh Chriſt a Queſtion, <hi>John</hi> 14.22. about this very thing; <hi>Lord, how is it that thou wilt Manifeſt thy ſelf unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, and not unto the World?</hi> He had heard Chriſt make ſuch a diſtinction between <hi>them and the World,</hi> in being <hi>in them,</hi> and not <hi>in the World,</hi> and in <hi>Praying for them,</hi> and <hi>not for the World;</hi> that now he asketh Chriſt a Reaſon of this Difference and Diſtinction between <hi>them and the World,</hi> which is ſufficient for the Proof of the <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And elſe-where, telling his Diſciples, That God had hid thoſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent of the World, and Revealed them unto Babes.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Sixthly, Another Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prop.</hi> 6.</note> Chriſt is in none but thoſe who dwell in Love.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:103245:30"/>
                  <p>But wicked Men and Women do not dwell in Love.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Chriſt is not in Wicked Men and Women.</p>
               </q>
               <p>For Proof of this <hi>Propoſition,</hi> ſee 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.12. <hi>If we Love one another, God dwelleth in us, and his Love is perfected in us:</hi> And ver. 16. <hi>God is Love, and he that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, we know all <hi>wicked Men and women in the world</hi> they <hi>dwell not in Love, but in Enmity and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; and Enmity and Hatred dwells in them.</hi> They <hi>Love not God, but Hate God,</hi> Pſal. 27. <hi>They Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me without a Cauſe:</hi> They have <hi>Enmity in their minds againſt God, his word, his ways, Ordinances, and People;</hi> Therefore <hi>Chriſt is not in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The ſeventh <hi>Propoſition,</hi> Proving that <hi>Chriſt is not in all Men and women that come into the world,</hi> as the Quakers aſſert, is this.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt is not in thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons where the Devil is,
<note place="margin">Prop. 7.</note> and dwells, Rules, and Reigns.</p>
                  <p>But the Devil is, Rules, and Reigns in the Wicked, unregenerate World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore</hi> Chriſt is not in the wicked, unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate world.</p>
               </q>
               <p>For Proof hereof, See <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. <hi>In time paſt ye walked according to the courſe of this world, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Prince of the power of the Air, the Spirit that now worketh in the Children of Diſobedience.</hi> And 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. <hi>And that they may recover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of the Snare of the Devil, who are taken Captive by him at his will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is alſo Manifeſt by that Compariſon that our Lord Chriſt makes to Anſwer the <hi>Blaſphemous Jews,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:103245:30"/>who charged him, that he caſt out Devils by the power of the Devil, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.21. <hi>when the ſtrong Man Armed keeps the Houſe, all is in quiet, he Rules;</hi> but when a ſtronger than he cometh, he caſts him out, and Divides the Spoyls, <hi>v,</hi> 24. The <hi>unclean Spirit keeps Houſe,</hi> and after a time goes out, for a Seaſon, and then Returns again into his Houſe, and takes <hi>ſeven other ſpirits as bad, or worſe than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and they enter in, and dwell there; and the laſt ſtate of that Man is worſe than the firſt.</hi> This is for thee, <hi>James Jackſon, Author of the ſtrong Man Armed caſt out.</hi> Thou ſayeſt in this thy Book, that <hi>the ſtrong Man Armed</hi> (meaning the Devil) is caſt out of thee; and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> a ſtronger than he, is come in, and dwells in his ſtead: this (by the way) plainly contradicts <hi>this Principle</hi> and <hi>great Doctrine</hi> of thy Friends, the Quakers; That <hi>Chriſt is in every Man and woman.</hi> Thou confeſſeſt the <hi>Devil was in thee,</hi> whilſt thou Lived'ſt ſo wickedly as thou haſt told us; but now, if Chriſt, a ſtronger than he, be come, and entred into thee, how was he there before, according to this Scripture, which ſays, <hi>when a ſtronger than he cometh:</hi> which plainly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies he was not there before; but <hi>the Devil was there before, and kept the Houſe.</hi> But now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this well, ſuppoſe it be ſo indeed, That the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, this ſtrong Man Armed, was caſt out,</hi> or in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy went out for a time, intending to come into <hi>his Houſe again,</hi> and Fortifie himſelf <hi>in thee, his Houſe, in a ſtronger hold;</hi> and with greater ſtrength, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>ſeven other Spirits worſe than himſelf, more Subtile and Politick,</hi> Fortifying themſelves <hi>in a way of Hypocriſie and Religion;</hi> the other <hi>hold of Profaneneſs</hi> not being ſo ſure as this; for now thou art perſwaded (as thou telleſt us) all is well with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:103245:31"/>thee, thou art <hi>a New Man, a Converted Man,</hi> as we ſee, and Read thy long ſtory to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>I Adviſe thee, as thou loveſt thy Soul, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeſt thy Eternal Welfare, take heed leſt <hi>this Scripture be not fulfilled in thee, and upon thee,</hi> for thou lookeſt as like one of thoſe ſpoken of, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in this Scripture, as can be: beware leſt thy laſt ſtate be not worſe than thy firſt.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Another <hi>Argument</hi> proving that <hi>Chriſt is not in all Men and women,</hi> is this.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt is not in any Man or Woman who have not Faith:
<note place="margin">Prop. 8.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the Wicked and ungodly have no Faith.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Chriſt is not in the wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The Apoſtle Prays to be delivered <hi>from unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and wicked Men, for all Men have not Faith,</hi> 2 Theſ. 3.2.</p>
               <p>Now, <hi>Chriſt is, and dwells in thoſe in whom he works Faith,</hi> for <hi>he is the Author and Finiſher of Faith in all his People, and he dwells in them by Faith,</hi> Eph. 3.17. He Prays, <hi>That they may be ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with might by his Spirit, in the inner Man, That Chriſt may dwell in your Hearts by Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Another <hi>Argument</hi> Denying the Quakers Aſſertion, and Proving the Truth, is this:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt is not in any Man or Woman,
<note place="margin">Prop. 9.</note> but in thoſe to whom he doth communicate his Nature and Image.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But</hi> Chriſt doth not Communicate his Nature and Image to Impenitent and ungodly Men and Women.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore</hi> Chriſt is not in ungodly Men and Women.</p>
               </q>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:103245:31"/>
               <p>It is impoſſible that Chriſt ſhould dwell in any Soul, and not Manifeſt his Preſence there, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Impreſſions of his own Nature, Image, and Likeneſs:</hi> And therefore <hi>where he comes, he doth Communicate his Image, more or leſs.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.48. <hi>As is the Heavenly, ſuch are they alſo that are Heavenly:</hi> v. 49. <hi>And as we have born the Image of the Earthly, we ſhall alſo bear the Image of the Heavenly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>There are given unto us exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great and precious Promiſes, That by theſe you might be partakers of the Divine Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Another <hi>Propoſition</hi> confirming the ſame, is this:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt is in none but in thoſe onely who are joyned to him, as Members of his Body.
<note place="margin">Prop. 10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But wicked Men and Women are not joyned to him as Members of his Body.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Chriſt is not in wicked Men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               </q>
               <p>This Truth may be Illuſtrated, and ſhadowed out unto us by a plain <hi>Similitude</hi> between <hi>Natural and Myſtical Fruit-trees: Similitudes</hi> of things with which we daily Converſe, obvious to our <hi>Natural Senſes,</hi> are very helpful unto us <hi>to ſhadow out, and Illuſtrate Spiritural things,</hi> which are <hi>Dark, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruce, and Difficult,</hi> as they lye in intricate Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Notions; which without ſome <hi>plain Similitude</hi> would be diſcerned but dimly, as in this particular. As VVindows are to a Houſe, ſo are Similitudes to a Diſcourſe: They both let in Light. VVe know the <hi>Root, Body, Boughs, Branches, and Twiggs of a Fruit-tree</hi> are <hi>all joyned together,</hi> and do make but <hi>one Body or Subſtance:</hi> And that the <hi>Root</hi> gives no
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:103245:32"/>
                  <hi>Sap, Life, or Nouriſhment</hi> but onely to thoſe parts of the Tree that are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited to it;</hi> all thoſe <hi>Boughs and Branches</hi> are Nouriſhed from the <hi>Root;</hi> they Receive <hi>Sap, Spirit, and Life;</hi> the <hi>Innate, Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal Form and Virtue of the Tree is in all the parts:</hi> But the <hi>Virtue and Influence of the Root</hi> is not <hi>in any other Branches or Boughs,</hi> which do not grow upon the <hi>Root,</hi> though they are never ſo near this Tree, though they are contiguous, and mixed among, or hang among the Living Branches, yet they have <hi>no Life in them, no Sap, no Virtue from the Root,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>no parts of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Even ſo it is here, in this <hi>Myſtical Fruit-tree, Chriſt and his Members; his People,</hi> who are <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his Body,</hi> they Receive <hi>Life, Nouriſhment, and Virtue from him;</hi> he is <hi>in them</hi> by his <hi>Effectual Operations:</hi> But as for others, who are <hi>not of his Body.</hi> who are <hi>not joyned to him by Faith wrought by the Spirit,</hi> he is not <hi>in them,</hi> they receive <hi>no Virtue, Life, or Nouriſhment from him;</hi> he doth not <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate himſelf to them,</hi> as he does to <hi>his own People, his Members;</hi> for he is <hi>in them, and they in him,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.27. <hi>Ye are the Body of Chriſt, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in particular,</hi> Col. 1.18. <hi>He is the Head of the Body the Church.</hi> And <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19. <hi>From the Head, all the Body by Joynts and Bands, having Nouriſhment Miniſtred and knit together, increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with the Increaſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is plain from Chriſt's own words, <hi>John</hi> 15.1, 2, &amp;c. <hi>I am the Vine, and my Father is the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman: Every Branch in me that beareth not Fruit be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>keth away, and every Branch that beareth Fruit he p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgeth it, that it may bring forth more Fruit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ver. 4. <hi>Abide in me, and I in you:</hi> Ver. 5. <hi>I am the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne, ye are the Branches; he that abideth in me,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:103245:32"/>and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much Fruit, for without me ye can do nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I drawn theſe <hi>Ten Pieces of Ordnance</hi> out of Gods own <hi>Magazine,</hi> and levelled them againſt <hi>this Idol, this falſe Chriſt, the Light in every Man and Woman;</hi> and it is ſallen and broken, and <hi>Chriſt the true Light ſet up,</hi> and Worſhipped in its ſtead, by all that Worſhip God in Spirit, and in Truth.</p>
               <p>How dreadful is the Caſe of theſe People <hi>(the Deceived ones among the Quakers,)</hi> who ſet up <hi>an Idol inſtead of Chriſt,</hi> and Worſhip it, and Teach others ſo to do; thereby forſaking <hi>the Fountain of Living waters, and digging to themſelves broken Ciſterns that can hold no water.</hi> Well might the <hi>Apoſtle Peter,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle Jude</hi> alſo, call them <hi>Wells without water, and Clouds without water,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.17. Jude 12.</p>
               <p>Seeing they have forſaken <hi>the Fountain of Living waters, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and truſt to <hi>a broken Ciſtern,</hi> they ſhall return from it with their <hi>Pitchers empty,</hi> and be aſhamed; they ſhall find <hi>no water of Life to refreſh them:</hi> They are now <hi>empty Veſſels,</hi> as all (who have the <hi>true Light</hi> in them) may perceive; They have <hi>no Light, Wiſdom, Knowledge, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> as Chriſt gives to his People: No <hi>Sanctification,</hi> no <hi>Juſtification,</hi> no <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> no <hi>Salvation.</hi> But it is not ſo with <hi>true Believers,</hi> for they have choſen the <hi>Fountain of Living waters, the Fountain of Gardens,</hi> the Well <hi>of Living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> Cant. 4.15. The <hi>Spring-head of the River of water of Life, clear as Cryſtal, proceeding out of the Throne of God, and of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 22.1. Who alſo gives unto every one of them, to have in themſelves <hi>a Well of water ſpringing up unto Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:103245:33"/>John 4.14. ſo that <hi>out of their Bellies ſhall flow Rivers of Living water,</hi> John 7.38. In ſo much that they do therewith <hi>water others,</hi> and ſo obtain yet <hi>more waterings themſelves,</hi> Prov. 11.25. So that <hi>their Souls are like watered Gardens, and as Springs of water, whoſe waters fail not,</hi> Iſa. 58.11.</p>
               <p>We ſee then what a vaſt difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>theſe Wells without water, theſe Clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water</hi> afore-mentioned; who have ſet up their <hi>Idol,</hi> and truſt in it; and thoſe that have choſen the <hi>Fountain of Living waters:</hi> The one ſort are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually <hi>dry,</hi> without any <hi>true Refreſhings;</hi> as the <hi>dry and barren wilderneſs without Fruit:</hi> But the other continually <hi>watred and refreſhed,</hi> and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth <hi>much good Fruit:</hi> As the <hi>Tree Planted by the Rivers of waters, which bringeth forth his Fruit in due Seaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. I ſhall now proceed, and ſhew ſome <hi>other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars</hi> wherein the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſay they do Excell all other Profeſſors in the World, having already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>three particulars,</hi> (which <hi>James Jackſon</hi> tells us of in his Book, <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>Strong Man Armed caſt out,</hi> viz. In the <hi>true Foundation, in Faith, and in Knowledge:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Quakers Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> So Fourthly, in <hi>Humility,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſubjection to the Power and Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt; whereas other Profeſſors are blown, ſwell'd, and puff'd up with Airy Notions, vain boastings, and ſelf-conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as he there ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Anſwer to which, I ſay, I ſhould be glad to ſee theſe <hi>good words and Profeſſions</hi> to have any thing of Reality in them, that they may not be, as the Apoſtle ſays of <hi>the Love of ſome,</hi> which is <hi>in word, and in Tongue onely, not in deed, nor in Truth:</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:103245:33"/>For wherein does this <hi>Humility</hi> appear? I ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that looks like <hi>Humility</hi> amongſt them, except it be <hi>in an Outward Garb of Comely and decent Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel;</hi> and for that, they are (in good earneſt) to be commended; I wiſh others would take Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by them herein, and avoid all Fooliſh Garbs and Faſhions, unbecoming for Profeſſors of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Yet this alone is but <hi>a ſhew of Humility;</hi> it is not <hi>the Grace it ſelf:</hi> But it is plain and manifeſt by their <hi>Principles, Behaviour, and Practice,</hi> they Diſcover that which is <hi>Directly contrary and Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to Humility,</hi> i. e. much <hi>Pride of Heart,</hi> and are lifted up in themſelves, as the <hi>Proud Phariſee</hi> was; and are perſwaded, and profeſs, that they are not as other Men are; all are <hi>Publicans and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, in Ignorance, Blindneſs, and Darkneſs</hi> but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Yea, <hi>all Profeſſors of all perſwaſions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,</hi> that are not one with them in <hi>Judgment and Practice,</hi> they are all Deceived, and out of the way; out of the <hi>Light, the Truth, and the Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, what greater <hi>Evidence of Pride</hi> can Men Diſcover than this? Little cauſe therefore has this Author to boaſt of <hi>his and their Humility,</hi> and to accuſe <hi>other Profeſſors as blown, ſwelled, and puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up with Airy Notions, vain boaſtings, and ſelf-conceitedneſs;</hi> when they themſelves are plainly ſeen and known to be the Men, <hi>void of Humility, and ſwelled with Pride.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Fifthly, This <hi>Author of the ſtrong Man Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med caſt out,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 14. <hi>The Quakers <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
                  </note> Commends the People with whom he now walks, for their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> not onely in <hi>Opinion and Judgment, but in Spirit:</hi> And <hi>their Love is as the ſoul, that hath its Influence into
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:103245:34"/>all the parts and Members of the Natural Body;</hi> ſo it is among them, <hi>which</hi> (as he ſays) <hi>makes them in all their ways, Doctrine, and Practice, to be but as one Man,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is Anſwered; The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Love, and Concord</hi> amongſt the Quakers, is far from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> that Chriſt Commandeth &amp; requireth to be amongſt <hi>his People, the Members of his Body, the Church:</hi> He commandeth <hi>Love, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace, Communion, and Fellowſhip</hi> to be between, and amongſt <hi>all his People, his Members:</hi> And there is ſo, in their Degrees and Meaſures, which is diſcovered as Occaſions and Opportunities are Offered.</p>
               <p>But though there were (as there is not) that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Judgment, Opinion, and Practice amongſt themſelves,</hi> as he ſaith there is; yet I ſay, it is far from that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Love</hi> that is in the <hi>true Church of Chriſt,</hi> for theſe People have cut off, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated themſelves from the <hi>true Church,</hi> and from all the <hi>particular Aſſemblies, Societies, and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of the Church of Chriſt;</hi> and do fanſy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be <hi>the onely People of God upon Earth;</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all others, for ſo he hath ſaid. O Wonderful <hi>ſtrong deluſion! A Darkneſs, and Blindneſs,</hi> not <hi>Natural</hi> onely (as all Carnal Men are Blind) but ſurely, <hi>a Judicial blindneſs</hi> is upon them, <hi>Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as a juſt Judgment from the Lord,</hi> who hath given leave to the <hi>god of this World to blind the Minds of them that believe not.</hi> This <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity among themſelves</hi> Dividing and Separating from all the Saints better than themſelves (if we ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that they are of the Body) is <hi>the greateſt Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Enmity, ſtrife, Schiſm, and Diſſention</hi> that can be; for out of his own Mouth he is Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: He Alludes to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion between the Members
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:103245:34"/>of the Natural body,</hi> their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Love</hi> (he ſays) is <hi>ſuch a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion:</hi> Now conſider, Were it not a ſtrange and Monſtrous thing in Nature, for <hi>ſome of the Members of the Natural body</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine together <hi>againſt all the reſt,</hi> to Neglect, or diſown the <hi>reſt of the Members?</hi> Nay, the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Natural body</hi> we know, have mutual, and tender <hi>care of, and Love one to another,</hi> even ſo it is in the <hi>Myſtical body the Church:</hi> The <hi>true Members Love one another;</hi> and as they have <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with the Head,</hi> ſo they have alſo <hi>one with another:</hi> And where there is at any time any <hi>Diſſention and External Separation, Corruption and Satan</hi> are the Cauſe of it, which ſhould Occaſion <hi>Repentance and Humiliation,</hi> and not <hi>boaſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> ſhews us plainly wherein the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the true members of the Church of Chriſt</hi> conſiſts; which is another kind of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the true Church.</note> than that among theſe People: He Diſcovers it briefly in this <hi>ſeven-fold Bond or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> See <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4. <hi>There is one body, and one ſpirit, one hope of your Calling; one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>one Body.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>One Body.</hi>
                  </note> All Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in all Ages of the world paſt, preſent, and to come, in <hi>all Nations, Kindreds, and People,</hi> Worſhipping God in Spirit, and in Truth, under <hi>all Forms,</hi> do make this <hi>one body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this <hi>one body</hi> hath but <hi>one Spirit;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>One Spirit.</hi>
                  </note> as the Members of the Natural Body have but <hi>one Soul</hi> to Actuate and Enliven them, ſo alſo in the <hi>Myſtical body;</hi> they all are <hi>quickned, taught, moved, and led by that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:103245:35"/>one Spirit,</hi> which is the Promiſe of the Father, and of the Son.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Members of this one body</hi> having <hi>one ſpirit,</hi> have alſo <hi>one hope;</hi> even the hope and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the good things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the Goſpel;
<note place="margin">3. <hi>One Hope.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eternal Life, the enjoyment of God for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Another <hi>Bond of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> in the <hi>true Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4. <hi>One Lord.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>is One Lord,</hi> even <hi>our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> unto whoſe Laws and Commands all his People are Subject.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>One Faith.</hi> That is,
<note place="margin">5. <hi>One Faith.</hi>
                  </note> the true Juſtifying Faith of Gods Elect, wrought by that <hi>one Spirit,</hi> apprehending that <hi>one Lord,</hi> for Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by him alone: <hi>Paul</hi> calls it the <hi>Common Faith,</hi> Titus 1.4. <hi>Titus mine own Son, after the Common Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, Another <hi>Bond of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in the true Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">6. <hi>One Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </note> is <hi>one Baptiſm,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. <hi>By one ſpirit we are all Baptized into one body; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we be Jews, or Greeks, whether we be bond or free, and have been all made to drink into one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> This <hi>one Baptiſm makes all Believers truly one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, The laſt <hi>bond of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the true Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">7. <hi>One God.</hi>
                  </note> is, <hi>One God, and Father of all who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> All Believers are <hi>born of God,</hi> and are all Partakers of the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> among the Lords People, none of them have a better Nature than another, as to the <hi>Truth,</hi> but as it differs <hi>in the Degrees or
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:103245:35"/>Meaſures;</hi> to ſome God is pleaſed to Communicate <hi>a greater meaſure,</hi> to ſome <hi>a leſſer Meaſure of Gifts and Graces,</hi> that <hi>one and the ſelf-ſame Spirit</hi> Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to every Man ſeverally as he will, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11.</p>
               <p>We ſee here theſe <hi>ſeven Bonds</hi> are the <hi>true Bonds</hi> of the <hi>true Members of Chriſt, his Body, the Church;</hi> and are here mentioned and laid down by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle as ſtrong Reaſons and Grounds why <hi>all the Members</hi> ſhould endeavour to keep the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace,</hi> and not <hi>Divide</hi> and <hi>Separate</hi> one from another, ſeeing they are all <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one Body,</hi> and have but <hi>one Spirit</hi> among them all, and have all <hi>one hope,</hi> all of them but <hi>one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm,</hi> all but <hi>one God and Father;</hi> here is good Reaſon then they ſhould be <hi>one</hi> among themſelves, in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace, Love, Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and Communion one with another,</hi> as Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſerves.</p>
               <p>So that the Author above mentioned hath little Reaſon to boaſt of that kind of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> that is among the Quakers, if he conſider theſe things.</p>
               <p>Sixthly,
<note place="margin">6. <hi>The Quakers Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>Author of the ſtrong man Armed caſt out,</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tells us, That the <hi>Patience and Faithfulneſs of theſe People in doing and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the Will of God,</hi> is Remarkable; for the World is againſt them, though (as he ſays) they are the onely Innocent and harmleſs People upon the Earth; and becauſe there is more of God amongſt theſe People (the Quakers) than others, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they hated of all Men, and every where amongſt all Religions evil ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Anſwer whereunto, I ſay, That <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſuffering for Well-doing</hi> is very Acceptable with God, and ſhall certainly have a great Reward
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:103245:36"/>from God; the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.14. <hi>If ye Suffer for Righteouſneſs ſake, happy are ye;</hi> But there is a Suffering ſometimes for <hi>Evil doings, and Evil ſayings:</hi> And it is better if the Will of God be ſo, that we Suffer for <hi>well doing, than for evil doing,</hi> v. 17.</p>
               <p>Now, it is true, Theſe People (the Quakers) have been <hi>Sufferers</hi> as well as others; but for what have they <hi>Suffered?</hi> Has it been for <hi>well doing,</hi> for doing the Will and Work of Chriſt? They will ſay Yea, for doing the Will of God; but it follows not therefore that it is ſo: Chriſt will rather ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, who Required theſe things at your Hands? Nay, he hath forbidden them, your <hi>Falſe Doctrines and Opinions, your Diſownings, Deſpiſings, and Separations from the Precious People of the Lord,</hi> in all the <hi>Societies, Aſſemblies, and Congregations in the Land,</hi> your <hi>Diſturbing of them, and Railing againſt them,</hi> whilſt they are about the work of the Lord, ye your ſelves being <hi>drawn, or driven by the Seducing Spirit,</hi> have done <hi>his work,</hi> (and not <hi>the Lords work</hi>) and have ſometimes Suffered for it: And herein ye boaſt, and think your <hi>Patience</hi> is great, and that ye <hi>ſuffer according to the Will of God:</hi> But know, That it is not the <hi>Suffering, but the Cauſe</hi> that makes <hi>a Martyr:</hi> It is poſſible a Man may give <hi>his body to be burned</hi> (and that is more than to be <hi>Impriſoned</hi>) and yet not <hi>ſuffer for Righteouſneſs-ſake.</hi> 1 Cor. 13. <hi>Though I give my Body to be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and have not Love, it profiteth me nothing. Jeſuites and Papiſts</hi> have ſometimes <hi>ſuffered</hi> for their <hi>falſe Principles and Practices;</hi> and ſo may others, and ſo have you. Therefore ſpeak no more of your <hi>Patient ſufferings,</hi> untill ye know that ye Suffer for <hi>a good Cauſe,</hi> for <hi>well doing;</hi> untill ye
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:103245:36"/>Suffer <hi>for Chriſt,</hi> and for <hi>Righteouſneſs-ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I have gone through the ſeveral particulars, wherein the <hi>Author of the ſtrong man Armed caſt out,</hi> ſays, He and the People called Quakers, do Excell all other Profeſſing People in the World; wherein it appears to all Men that have in them <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> how groſſely theſe People are <hi>Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and blinded by ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> that they give heed unto; which making ſtrong Impreſſions in their Minds, they are Seduced, and carried away with them, never Examining of them, and Trying of them <hi>by the Scriptures,</hi> and ſo are eaſily Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And it is a moſt dreadful Condition that they are in, and an Evidence of the <hi>greateſt, and ſoreſt Judgment of God, that the Nature of Man is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of, on this ſide Hell; a Judicial blindneſs and hardneſs of heart,</hi> upon any Man, or Men, is the <hi>greateſt of all Judgments.</hi> And this is <hi>the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> that God often lays upon Men that <hi>will not hearken unto him, that Deſpiſe his Word and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, his Worſhip, and his People:</hi> That <hi>will not Receive the Truth in Love, that they might be ſaved.</hi> Therefore God doth ſend them <hi>ſtrong Deluſions that they ſhould believe a Lye; that they all might be Damned who believe not the Truth, but have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which doth confirm <hi>this man,</hi> James Jackſon,
<note place="margin">A falſe Perſwaſion of Converſion.</note> 
                  <hi>(Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the ſtrong man Armed caſt out)</hi> that he is <hi>truly Converted by the Light within,</hi> which he ſays, <hi>is Chriſt,</hi> is this; for that he finds ſuch wonderful <hi>Effects</hi> in himſelf, (as he Accounts them) he is now become <hi>a New Man,</hi> he is <hi>turned from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of Satan unto God;</hi> he is turned from all his former
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:103245:37"/>
                  <hi>Profane, Wicked, Debauched courſe of Life,</hi> as he tells us, and alſo from being <hi>a Pariſh Prieſt,</hi> and not onely ſo, but he is alſo turned from being <hi>a Teacher among the Independents,</hi> and ſince come to <hi>joyn with the Quakers:</hi> And now he tells us, he is where he would, and ſhould be; and concludes he is <hi>turned to the Lord:</hi> And counts it a Marvellous thing that any ſhould Deny <hi>the Light in every man to be Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Strong Man Armed, p.</hi> 14.</note> but ſay, it is the <hi>Devil,</hi> or at beſt but the <hi>Light of Nature:</hi> But (ſaith he) it was never known, that the Devil, or Nature did ever turn any to the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Anſwer hereunto, I ſay it is true, it was never known, that the <hi>Devil, or the Light of Nature did ever turn any to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here now is another Tryal of thy ſtate, (and all others that are of thy <hi>Principles and Practices:</hi>) Ye take it for granted, that ye are <hi>turned to the Lord by Hearkning to, Obeying, and Believing in the Light within;</hi> for thy part, <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> thou haſt given <hi>no Proof, nor Evidence</hi> at all according to <hi>Scripture,</hi> or the <hi>Experience of the People of God,</hi> that thou art yet <hi>Converted to the Lord:</hi> whereby any Man that is Taught of God, ſhould be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that thou art <hi>truly Converted to the Lord:</hi> That which thou doſt Manifeſt to all, and which thou thinkeſt is a ground ſufficient to perſwade them to believe that thou art a New Man, (and which it ſeems is enough to ſatisfie thy ſelf) is this, becauſe thou art turned from <hi>Profaneneſs to a more Civil Life;</hi> and haſt alſo left <hi>ſeveral ſorts of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,</hi> and now cloſed with <hi>the moſt Holy, Innocent People upon Earth; yea, the onely People of God,</hi> for ſo thou haſt ſaid of them. But let us further Try
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:103245:37"/>theſe two things by <hi>a true Touch-ſtone,</hi> and Weigh them in the <hi>Ballance of the Sanctuary:</hi> The one, <hi>The Light within, of what ſort it is:</hi> The other, the <hi>Effects of this Light,</hi> what it produceth in men. And for that <hi>Cauſes</hi> are often Difficult to be known and diſcerned, <hi>immediately, in and by themſelves,</hi> it is beſt to Try them by their <hi>Effects,</hi> that which they <hi>produce and bring forth;</hi> by which we may come to know of what Nature the <hi>Cauſe</hi> is.</p>
               <p>So then; This <hi>Light within,</hi> thou ſayeſt,
<note place="margin">The Light within Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts none to the Lord.</note> (and wouldeſt have all Men to Believe) hath <hi>Converted Thee and many Thouſands to the Lord, of the People called Quakers;</hi> but we are wholly left without any Proof, Sign, or Evidence, that you are <hi>Converted to the Lord:</hi> Nay, on the contrary, we ſee many <hi>Proofs and Evidences,</hi> that thou and they are not yet <hi>Converted to the Lord,</hi> as have been already (and more yet ſhall be) Diſcovered, whereby it will be made plain and manifeſt, that thou and they that are of thy mind, are utterly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken and deceived concerning both the <hi>Cauſe and the Effect:</hi> That is, ye are miſtaken utterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Light within, and the Fruits and Effects of it,</hi> in, and amongſt you. As for Thee, <hi>James Jackſon (Author of the ſtrong Man Armed caſt out)</hi> it is plain and manifeſt to a Spiritual Eye, That thou art yet <hi>in the Gall of bitterneſs, and in the Bond of Iniquity;</hi> for certainly, <hi>The Tree is known by its Fruits; a good Tree cannot bring forth bad Fruits:</hi> By the Fruits of Trees we know of what Kind or Nature the Tree is that brings them forth; doſt thou doubt of this? thou need'ſt not, if thou doſt but remember who it was that ſaid it; and all Agree, and know it is a Truth. So then, Thy <hi>Fruits</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:103245:38"/>Diſcover thee to be <hi>a very Corrupt Tree,</hi> bringing forth <hi>ſower, bitter, poyſonous, deadly Fruits;</hi> Thy <hi>Grapes are Grapes of Gall, thy Cluſters are bitter:</hi> And the like are the Fruits of the <hi>Leading Quakers amongst you:</hi> Thou and they bring forth <hi>Falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Errors, Hereſies, and Blaſphemies againſt God, his People, and his Truths;</hi> ye <hi>give heed to Seducing Spirits and Doctrines of Devils, ſpeaking Lies in Hypocriſie,</hi> which I ſhall plainly Diſcover in ſeveral particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Thou ſayeſt of many thouſands of the <hi>Lords peculiar People,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Strong Man Armed,</hi> p. 12.</note> That <q>they Build not upon the true Foundation, Jeſus Chriſt, but that the Teachers of all other Sects, and ſorts of Profeſſors amongſt the Presbiterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Baptiſts, and others, they ever Rejected, Diſallowed, and ſet at nought this ſtone, this true Foundation, which is Chriſt in us the hope of Glory, and Build upon ſome other falſe Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now, let me tell thee, thou <hi>falſe Tongue, ſet on fire of Hell,</hi> hadſt thou the <hi>true Light</hi> in thee indeed (as thou ſayeſt of thy ſelf) thou wouldſt ſooner have choſen to have had <hi>thy Tongue cut out,</hi> than to have ſpoken <hi>this Lie in Hypocriſie:</hi> Or to have had <hi>thy Hand cut off,</hi> than to have <hi>wrote it:</hi> For if it be better for a Man to have <hi>a Milſtone hanged about his Neck, and to be caſt into the Sea, than to Offend one of thoſe Little ones that believe in Chriſt;</hi> what thinkeſt thou will be the puniſhment of him that Offends <hi>many thouſands of thoſe Little ones?</hi> Yea, when the <hi>Offence</hi> is ſo high, that he <hi>Reproacheth, Slandreth, and Blaſphemeth them,</hi> and their <hi>Lord and Saviour in them;</hi> for he hath ſaid, <hi>He that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:103245:38"/>you, Deſpiſeth me: Inaſmuch as ye did it to one of theſe my Brethren, ye did it unto me:</hi> Thou Reproacheſt the <hi>true Light in many others</hi> by the <hi>Real Darkneſs within thy ſelf:</hi> And if the <hi>Light that is in thee be Darkneſs, how great is that Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> O it is <hi>very great and groſs Darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider theſe words,
<note place="margin">Natural Light is Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Darkneſs.</note> and who ſpake them, it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from theſe words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Chriſt's own Mouth, that <hi>the Light in Men, all unregenerate Men, is but Darkneſs:</hi> It is Real <hi>Natural Light, the Light of Reaſon, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and Conſcience,</hi> which yet as to the <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending of Spiritual things, is but Darkneſs:</hi> for the <hi>Natural Man</hi> (though never ſo Wiſe and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional) <hi>cannot ſee, nor Diſcern the things of God,</hi> in a Spiritual manner; and <hi>ſuch a Light within</hi> thou haſt, and miſtakeſt it, for the <hi>true Light Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as is manifeſt by the <hi>Effects,</hi> as was ſaid; for <hi>Chriſt the true Light</hi> cannot Reproach <hi>his own People, nor the work he hath wrought in them,</hi> as thou doſt; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>thy Light is Darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay further, have we not good grounds to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that <hi>the Darkneſs</hi> in thee, and many others of your Leaders, is more than that <hi>Common, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Darkneſs,</hi> that is, upon the Minds of <hi>all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate Men.</hi> There is cauſe to believe that it is <hi>a Judicial Darkneſs and Blindneſs,</hi> as was upon the Minds of many of the <hi>unbelieving Jews</hi> who Rejected Chriſt and his Goſpel, after all his Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Miracles among them: Such a Darkneſs as the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks of; <hi>Make the Heart of this People fat, and blind their Eyes, that ſeeing they may ſee, and not perceive:</hi> Not that God put in any more <hi>blindneſs</hi> into Mens minds, but <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:103245:39"/>his Grace, and denies his Spirit;</hi> but permits the <hi>Evil Spirit, the god of this unregenerate World, to blind the Minds of them that believe not, leſt the Light of the Glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould ſhine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</hi> And ſeeing that the Light of the Goſpel does ſhine ſo Gloriouſly in this Day, and ye Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it, and Deſpiſe it, we have cauſe to be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you have in you <hi>this double Darkneſs and Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> notwithſtanding all your Pleading for the <hi>Light within:</hi> Ye know not what ye ſay, nor whereof ye Affirm.</p>
               <p>Thou and thy Friends (as thou calleſt them) do quite miſtake that Scripture,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>This Scripture,</hi> John 1.9. <hi>groſſely Miſtaken.</hi>
                  </note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ye ground your Opinion and Perſwaſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Light within,</hi> John 1.9. <hi>This is the true Light, that Lighteth every Man that cometh into the World.</hi> Thou and they put a <hi>meaning and ſence</hi> upon it, though in other Scriptures brought againſt you, ye diſown all <hi>meanings;</hi> yet here ye make uſe <hi>of a meaning,</hi> but it is a falſe one: For it is not ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt the true Light,</hi> is in every one that cometh into the World, but that he <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every one that cometh into the World.</hi> Take then the very words, and the <hi>genuine ſence</hi> is plainly this: That <hi>Chriſt the true Light,</hi> doth Light every one that cometh into the World, and That in <hi>two Reſpects:</hi> Firſt, by an <hi>Outward Light;</hi> and Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by an <hi>Inward Light.</hi> The <hi>Outward Light</hi> is by the <hi>Sun in the Firmament, with the Moon and the Stars,</hi> this <hi>Outward Light all Men and Women have that come into the World, in all Nations, Tongues, and People:</hi> Secondly, <hi>Chriſt enlightneth them by an Inward light alſo;</hi> by the <hi>Light of Reaſon, Humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and Natural Conſcience;</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:103245:39"/>by theſe <hi>Lights</hi> alſo <hi>he Lighteth every one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the World,</hi> according to that Scripture afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned: And ſo much (and no more) is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by it, as it concerns <hi>every one that cometh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World:</hi> He is called the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> having Created <hi>divers Lights of ſeveral kinds.</hi> But now, as it concerns <hi>Believers, the peculiar People of God,</hi> the <hi>true Light Jeſus Chriſt, enlightneth them with another Light,</hi> beſides the former, which none but they onely are partakers of: The <hi>other Lights</hi> are but <hi>Darkneſs</hi> to <hi>this Light;</hi> yea, the Scripture calls them <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> in Compariſon of <hi>this true Light, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, the Son of Righteouſneſs,</hi> when he ariſes upon the Soul he makes things <hi>manifeſt and clear,</hi> which before were hid <hi>in Darkneſs,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. <hi>God, who Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined in our Hearts, to give the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> But as for the <hi>Wicked and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> (which are the greateſt part of the World) they have not <hi>this Light in them</hi> (as thou, <hi>James Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and the Teachers among the Quakers do affirm, and contend earneſtly for:) But they are of the Number of thoſe which the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, by the Mouth of his Servant <hi>Paul,</hi> in 2 Cor. 4.4. <hi>The god of this World hath blinded the Minds of them that believe not, leſt the Light of the Glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt (who is the Image of God) ſhould ſhine unto them:</hi> Look well unto it, that ye be not of the Number of <hi>theſe blind ones, blinded by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Spirit,</hi> which is got into your own <hi>blind Minds,</hi> and which ye call, and Blaſphemouſly ſay, <hi>is Chriſt the true Light in every Man.</hi> And verily, this is one ſad Sign, that ye are indeed <hi>of that very
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:103245:40"/>Number,</hi> even becauſe ye diſown the <hi>Goſpel of Chriſt, the Scriptures of Truth ſpoken by Chriſt himſelf, and by the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> Saying and Affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are not the <hi>Rule to Chriſtians in Faith and Obedience;</hi> neither do ye ſubmit to have your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits Tryed by them, but truſt to the <hi>Light within,</hi> which is but <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> as to <hi>Seeing and Diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Spiritual things:</hi> For <hi>Spiritual things are Spiritually Diſcerned.</hi> And know, and conſider this, That if the Goſpel of Chriſt be not Received, and ſubmitted unto, but Neglected, or Rejected, then it is hid from ſuch: And in ſuch a Caſe, the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. <hi>If our Goſpel be hid, it is hid from them that are loſt, whom Satan hath blinded, leſt it ſhould ſhine unto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou,
<note place="margin">The Quakers Doctrine is directly contrary to the Scriptures.</note> 
                  <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> and other <hi>Teaching Quakers,</hi> teach that <hi>Chriſt, the true Light, is in every Man and Woman in the World;</hi> But this is directly contrary to <hi>plain and poſitive Scripture:</hi> For before <hi>Converſion and Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, all Men and Women are in Darkneſs, and Darkneſs in them;</hi> yea, <hi>are Darkneſs it ſelf,</hi> in the Abſtract, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Ye ſometimes were Darkneſs, but now are ye Light in the Lord; Walk as Children of Light.</hi> And 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.8. <hi>Darkneſs is paſt, and the true Light now ſhineth:</hi> Heb. 10.32. <hi>After ye were Illuminated, ye endured a great Fight of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. Paul</hi> knew that <hi>all Men were in Darkneſs, and Darkneſs in them:</hi> And therefore his Preaching was to turn them <hi>from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of Satan (the Prince of Darkneſs) to the Living God:</hi> Yea, <hi>our Lord Chriſt himſelf, the true Light,</hi> ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 1.46. <hi>I am come a Light into the World, that whoſoever believeth in me, ſhould
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:103245:40"/>not abide in Darkneſs;</hi> plainly implying, that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Men <hi>Believe</hi> they abide <hi>in Darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And again, he ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 12.35. <hi>Yet a little while is the Light with you, Walk while ye have the Light.</hi> Now, if Chriſt had been the Light ſtill remaining in them, in every one, (as the Quakers Teach) Chriſt would not have uſed theſe words, <hi>Yet a little while is the Light with you; walk while they have the Light:</hi> It's like theſe Quakers would have Anſwered him boldly, (and Ignorantly enough) We have the <hi>Light within us;</hi> it is always <hi>in us, and with us, and abides in us,</hi> and <hi>in all Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the World:</hi> Go whither thou wilt, for we have <hi>the Light within us ſtill continually:</hi> For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly theſe Men would no more have owned him, nor his Doctrine had they been contemporaries with him, than they own him now in theſe Days: And we know they have <hi>Denyed him,</hi> both <hi>in his Perſon, and in his Doctrlne;</hi> as appears Manifeſtly in their Books and Writings, beſides Denying of him, in Denying his Members.</p>
               <p>It is Evident then, That the <hi>Teaching Quakers</hi> do Deceive the Poor, Ignorant, Simple People, <hi>their Hearers,</hi> with this Doctrine about the <hi>light within,</hi> and ſpeak concerning it directly contrary to the <hi>Doctrine of the Scriptures:</hi> And theſe poor ſimple People (ſilly Women, as the Apoſtle calls them) 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. finding, and perceiving there is ſome <hi>Light within</hi> that Diſcerns ſome things to be good, and moves unto it, and on the contrary, denies ſome evil things, and will not conſent to known Evils; They do hereupon conclude, that <hi>this is Chriſt the true Light,</hi> according as they are Taught, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the <hi>Difference between Natural Light and Spiritual Light,</hi> no more than their Teachers,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:103245:41"/>and ſo it paſſeth for a currant Doctrine amongſt them, though it be moſt Abſurd and falſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly contrary to the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Do ye not know that there is <hi>a Conſcience in every Man and Woman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conſcience is a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Light.</note> and that it is <hi>a Light according to its Nature?</hi> it hath ſo much <hi>Light,</hi> as not onely to ſee and know Earthly things, according to <hi>Reaſon and Humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> but alſo ſome things according to the <hi>Law of God,</hi> Rom. 1. to ſee, and to reprove for <hi>ſome groſs evils and ſins; As Murder, Theft, Drunkenneſs, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiality, Deceitful dealings,</hi> and ſuch like things againſt the <hi>Light of Nature;</hi> which alſo the <hi>Law of God</hi> forbids: And <hi>this Light within every one</hi> does move unto <hi>ſome things that are Morally good and Honeſt,</hi> Reproving, and Troubling for the one, and Excuſing for the other: But <hi>this Light</hi> can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>lead to Chriſt</hi> without the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> and the <hi>Word of the Goſpel,</hi> which Reveals Chriſt fully: Therefore give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and unto <hi>God</hi> the things that are <hi>Gods.</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe unto <hi>Conſcience</hi> the things that belong to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> that which is his own: Set not a Creature in the Throne of the Creator; and by Worſhipping an <hi>Idol,</hi> forſake the <hi>Living and true God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true,
<note place="margin">Chriſt the true Light, is really in Believers, and in none elſe.</note> and a glorious Truth indeed (a precious Priviledge of the Saints, and peculiar People of God,) that <hi>Chriſt dwells in them;</hi> and this is <hi>a great and Glorious Myſtery made known unto the Saints: (onely Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers)</hi> as we ſee, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>Even the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery which hath been hid from Ages, and from Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:103245:41"/>but now is made manifeſt to his Saints,</hi> ver. 17. <hi>To whom God would make known what is the Riches of the Glory of this Myſtery, among the Gentiles, which is: Chriſt in you the Hope of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is a glorious <hi>Myſtery</hi> revealed to the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> that they ſhould now come in, and be of the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>poor Gentiles</hi> that never were call'd before that time: <hi>the Gentiles,</hi> who were formerly Excluded (in all the Generations before thoſe dayes) they are now made fellow-heirs with the <hi>Believing Jews:</hi> And this Rich and Glorious Priviledge is alſo revealed to them: <hi>Chriſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in them by Faith, by his Spirit, and all his graces, and operations, communicating his Nature to them,</hi> that they are as really partakers of the <hi>Image of the ſecond Adam, in righteouſneſs and true holineſs,</hi> as they were of the <hi>Image of the firſt Adam in ſin and darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what is <hi>this Priviledge</hi> to the <hi>wicked, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate world,</hi> that lye <hi>in ſin, and darkneſs?</hi> what <hi>Communion hath light with darkneſs? what fellowſhip hath Chriſt with</hi> Belial? Will Chriſt Dwell in the Soul where the Devil Dwells, and Reigns? Nay verily: If Chriſt come to dwell and abide in any Soul, and be a light unto it, he will ſurely caſt out <hi>Sathan, that Strong man Armed,</hi> that keeps the houſe (as Sathan does in all wicked men) and Sathan ſhall Reign, nor keep houſe no longer but Chriſt will remove him, and come in his place, and Reign, and Rule, and Dwell there; and by his Preſence, and Dwelling in the Soul, will give to ſuch a believing Soul, ſure grounds of hope of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory: according to this word; <hi>Chriſt in you the hope of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:103245:42"/>
               <p>And ſeeing the Teachers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Quakers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Scriptures are the Word of God.</note> do ſlight and undervalue <hi>the Scriptures</hi> and deny them to be the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and to be <hi>a Rule for Chriſtians in Faith and Practice;</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their own <hi>Fanſies, and vain imaginations</hi> (moved often by <hi>ſeducing Spirits</hi>) before the <hi>written Word of God,</hi> let us conſider the tendency of this ſtrong deluſion.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writes to the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 15.4. <hi>Whatſoever things were written aforehand, were written for our Learning, that we through pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope.</hi> The Church of God was for a long time without the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> God teaching his People <hi>immediately by his Spirit,</hi> or by <hi>Angels,</hi> mixed with ſome <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential diſpenſations,</hi> but when he had gathered his Church and People out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he was graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed to inſtruct them by a plain <hi>written Word, to be a perfect, ſtanding Rule,</hi> both for <hi>Faith and Practice;</hi> And required (upon divers ſore <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>Rewards and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> on the other) that they ſhould obſerve them.</p>
               <p>And thoſe that were Godly amongſt them, took diligent heed thereunto, and great delight therein: How did the holy Prophet <hi>David</hi> (a man after Gods own heart) prize and value the <hi>written Word of God;</hi> (though he had but a ſmall part of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> to what we now have) as we ſee in all his <hi>Pſalms,</hi> more eſpecially in the 119. <hi>Pſal.</hi> almoſt in every verſe of that long Pſalme, he makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Law of God,</hi> his <hi>Statutes, Ordinances, Judgments, Precepts, and Commandments,</hi> how he loved them, delighted in them, meditated in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:103245:42"/>them; <hi>O how I love thy Law; it is my meditation continually;</hi> he aimed at the keeping, and practice of them, as at a mark; and tells us it is the nature, and property of all good men ſo to do, Pſal. 1. <hi>The godly man meditates in the Law of God Day and night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now theſe <hi>Teachers and Leaders of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> they expreſs no love to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> but the quite contrary; they Slight, and Undervalue them, and teach others to do ſo too; and deny them to be a Chriſtians <hi>Rule of Faith and Practice,</hi> though ſpoken by <hi>Christ himſelf in his own Perſon,</hi> (a great part of them) who is truly <hi>God,</hi> as well as <hi>Man;</hi> and the reſt <hi>inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt, who alſo is God.</hi> Yet theſe Unreaſonable and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful men, deny them to be <hi>the Word of God,</hi> though ſpoken <hi>by God himſelf:</hi> We have much of the Scripture ſpoken, <hi>by Chriſts own mouth, and all was given by inſpiration of God, Holy men of God, ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and is not the <hi>Holy Ghoſt God?</hi> How then are not the <hi>Scriptures the Word of God?</hi> Are not theſe men infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated that will not own theſe things.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>believing Theſſalonians</hi> had heard <hi>the Word of God,</hi> ſpoken by <hi>Paul,</hi> and received it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, he thankes God for it; <hi>for this cauſe thank we God without ceaſing, becauſe when ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Word of God, which ye heard of us, ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it not as the word of men, but as it is in Truth the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when any one would draw us to hearken to any <hi>Private Spirit,</hi> as of old they did (and ſo now) we are commanded by God, <hi>not to hearken to them,</hi> Iſaiah 8.20. but we are directed <hi>to the Scriptures: To the Law, and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeake not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:103245:43"/>according to this Word, it is becauſe there is no light in them:</hi> And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Lo they have rejected the word of the Lord, and what wiſdome is in them?</hi> So then; here we ſee plainly they that ſpeak not, and write not according to <hi>the Scriptures,</hi> they have neither <hi>wiſdome, nor Light in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider this, ye deluded People among the Quakers, that give more heed to a <hi>dim, natural light within (darkned alſo by deluding ſpirits)</hi> than to the <hi>Light of the Scriptures,</hi> though the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs ſhine Bright, and Gloriouſly in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> hath marked out <hi>ſuch men,</hi> for <hi>wicked men</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6. <hi>We are of God; he that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, heareth us, he that is not of God heareth not us; hereby know we the Spirit of truth and the Spirit of Error.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What can be more plain? hereby then it is Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, what ſort of men <hi>theſe are in this Generation,</hi> who will not <hi>hear the Prophets, and Apoſtles ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Spirit in the Scriptures: he that will not hear <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s is not of God:</hi> but on the contrary, he that <hi>heareth us,</hi> that is, <hi>obeyeth us, and is ruled and guided by that which we have ſpoken and written, he is of God, and is guided and taught by the Spirit of God,</hi> which God hath alſo given to them that believe.</p>
               <p>And farther, This truth is alſo ſpoken by our bleſſed Lord and Savionr Chriſt himſelf, even from <hi>his own mouth:</hi> Joh. 8.47. when the Proud unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Jewes (ſuch another proud, ſelf-conceited People as are now in our dayes) would not receive his doctrine, he tells them plainly what they are, <hi>ver.</hi> 47. <hi>he that is of God, heareth Gods words, ye therefore heard them not, becauſe ye are not of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:103245:43"/>
               <p>Tremble, and Quake at this Dreadful word, ye ſeduced People of the Quakers, who will not hear, nor be guided <hi>by the Scriptures, the written, and declared word of God:</hi> Ye are here <hi>pronounced by Chriſts own mouth, his Prophets, and Apoſtles;</hi> that <hi>ye are not of God:</hi> That is, ye are <hi>not born of God, ye are not born of the Spirit:</hi> for that which is <hi>born of the Spirit, is Spirit:</hi> ye are <hi>not regenerate,</hi> ye are <hi>not believers;</hi> ye are <hi>no members of Chriſt:</hi> ye are <hi>not taught of God, nor led by his Spirit,</hi> but by <hi>a falſe Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to <hi>Timothy</hi> he commended him for that he had known the <hi>Scriptures from a child, which were able to make him wiſe unto ſalvation;</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15. And ſayes, that <hi>all Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtruction in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> ver. 17. <hi>That the man of God may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, throughly furniſhed unto all good workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe men are ſo farr from being <hi>furniſhed to all good workes,</hi> that they are <hi>reprobate to every good work:</hi> they having caſt-aſide the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> they can never be <hi>furniſhed</hi> any other way, to any <hi>good Work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us conſider how great a favour it is from God that we have <hi>the Scriptures;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Scriptures are Gods Love-letters to Mankind.</note> which are Gods <hi>Love-letters to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; indited by his own Spirit, and written by his own ſervants, to woo them, and win them to accept of his own, and only beloved Son in marriage:</hi> that there may be <hi>a Contract, and an everlaſting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion between them:</hi> and ſo they may become <hi>the Spouſe of Chriſt, the Lambs Wife;</hi> And that although they have no <hi>Beauty, nor Comelineſs</hi> upon them, yet
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:103245:44"/>that he will accept of them, notwithſtanding their <hi>Deformity,</hi> if they will but <hi>but conſent to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Oh who would not conſent, to ſuch a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull condiſcenſion in the Great, and Holy God, to ſuch poor miſerable creatures, as we are, <hi>blind and deaf, deformed, foul, and filthy, poor, and needy, wanting all things that might make us accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his eyes!</hi> But though it be ſo, yet he hath promiſed that he will make us <hi>Comely, and Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and Rich, with Ornaments, and a Crown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and no good thing ſhall be wanting to them that love him.</hi> Therefore (all theſe things conſidered) let us have the <hi>Scriptures</hi> in high eſteem; and walk by them, for we ſhall be judged by them at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>But what a ſad caſe are they in then who deny them as <hi>a Rule to walk by,</hi> and diſown them? And if <hi>ſo great a curſe</hi> ſhall be the portion of thoſe <hi>who take away any part of the Scriptures,</hi> as that God will <hi>take away their part out of the Book of Life, and out of the holy City, and from the things that are written therein,</hi> Rev. 22. what ſhall we think will be the <hi>Portion and Puniſhment of thoſe, who take away all the Scripture at once, and make it as a void thing; and deny them to be a perfect Rule to Chriſtians of Faith, and Obedience;</hi> and do inſtead thereof direct men to <hi>a blind guide, that had need of a guide it ſelf;</hi> for that it ſees nothing of <hi>the true way, the truth, and the life, without the Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now becauſe the ſpirit of God who indited the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<note place="margin">Characters of falſe Prophets whereby they are known.</note> and ſpake by the mouth of his <hi>holy Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Chriſt himſelf alſo in his own perſon,</hi> hath told
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:103245:44"/>us, That <hi>falſe Prophets and Teachers</hi> ſhould be in the <hi>later dayes,</hi> and ſhould ſeduce, and deceive many; And ſo ſubtle ſhall their <hi>carriage and their Doctrine be (like their Teacher)</hi> that they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive (if it were poſſible) <hi>the very Elect;</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe alſo we know that <hi>theſe are the laſt times, the laſt daies, even theſe dayes wherein we live,</hi> in which dayes <hi>theſe falſe Teachers</hi> (foretold) ſhould come; it is our duty therefore, and it highly concerns eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian to <hi>try the Spirits,</hi> becauſe even Now <hi>many falſe Prophets</hi> are in the world among us.</p>
               <p>Let us conſider and examine than, who theſe <hi>falſe Prophets and Teachers are;</hi> how they may be known; What <hi>Marks and Characters</hi> there are ſet down <hi>in the Scriptures</hi> whereby theſe men may be known: for the <hi>Spirit of God hath marked them out, whereby they may be diſcerned from other men;</hi> even whereby they may be known to be <hi>the very men foretold,</hi> that ſhould come <hi>in theſe laſt dayes.</hi> Our Lord Chriſt hath bid us <hi>take heed of them,</hi> Luk. 13.23. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have foretold you of theſe things.</hi> Let us therefore conſider ſome particulars, as marks of theſe men.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, that in the Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Tim.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Now the ſpirit ſpeaketh expreſly, that in the later times ſome ſhall depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing Spirits, and Doctrines of Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Some ſhall <hi>depart from the Faith;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Departing from the Faith.</hi>
                  </note> Now what kind of <hi>Faith</hi> is here meant; it is not <hi>a true and juſtifying faith,</hi> for that none can depart from; but it is a <hi>Temporary Faith,</hi> ſome ſhaddows and fancies reſembling faith; ſuch a faith as our Lord Chriſt ſpeakes of, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>They believed for a while, but in time of Temptation fell away.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:103245:45"/>
               <p n="2">2. They alſo caſt off, and departed from <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Faith;</hi> for they regard not what is <hi>written in the Scriptures,</hi> either concerning <hi>Faith or Practice.</hi> And it is not ſo with theſe Men of whom we ſpeak; conſider, and Judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They give heed to Seducing Spirits,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Character: they give heed to Seducing Spirits, and Doctrines of Devils.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and Doctrines of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</hi> This <hi>Mark and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> is alſo ſeen conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and plainly upon the <hi>Teachers among the Quakers;</hi> yea, ſo Evident is it, as if written with a Beam of the Sun.</p>
               <p>Now, what <hi>Doctrines do the Devils Teach,</hi> when they are permitted of God, (for his Secret ends) to uſe the Tongues of Wicked Men? we may be ſure his Aim and drift will be to Preach <hi>againſt Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Againſt Chriſt.</hi>
                  </note> to darken his Glory as much as he can; <hi>both in his Humane and Divine Natures;</hi> and <hi>in his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, Works, Sufferings, Righteouſneſs, Satisfaction, Reconciliation, Benefits, and Priviledges</hi> that he hath wrought, and brought unto his People. Theſe things are manifeſt in ſeveral particulars, in their Books and Pamphlets.</p>
               <p>And Secondly,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Againſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
                  </note> Another par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular of the <hi>Doctrine of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> which he will be ſure to Teach his Diſciples, it is to weaken, or Deſtroy the Authority of <hi>his Word, the Scriptures, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Salvation;</hi> by which, Truth and Error may be known and proved: For if he once Deſtroy <hi>the Rule and Meaſure of Doctrines,</hi> (ſo that Men do not try them by <hi>a known, plain, fixed Rule</hi>) then he knows Men may Preach, and pretend their <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and vain Imaginations,</hi> and obtrude them upon
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:103245:45"/>others, as moſt certain Truths. And hath he not Taught the Men of this Generation <hi>this point of his Deviliſh Doctrine?</hi> Do they not <hi>ſlight and Deſpiſe the Scriptures, the Word of God;</hi> and Offer, and prefer their own <hi>vain, Idle Fancies,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> even the Men of whom we are ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Teachers among the Quakers? This is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and clear to the Eyes of all who are <hi>enlightned by Chriſt, and by the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Thirdly, Against the Church.</note> As the <hi>Doctrines of Devils are againſt Chriſt, his word, and Goſpel,</hi> ſo alſo againſt <hi>his People, his Church, all his Members;</hi> they ſhall be ſure to be <hi>Cryed down, Slandered, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, Reproached, and Condemned, as Hypocrites,</hi> in all that they ſay, and do, in, and about the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, in his Ordinances which he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, for as the Devil hath great ſpight and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt the Head, ſo alſo againſt the Members.</p>
               <p>Now, do not the <hi>Quakers</hi> deal thus with the <hi>Lords People</hi> at this day? This is another <hi>particular point of the Doctrine of Devils,</hi> which the <hi>Seducing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> have Taught thoſe who give heed unto them; how have they cryed down (with a <hi>Blaſphemous Noiſe</hi> every where) all the <hi>Congregations, Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and particular Churches of the Saints, of all perſwaſions, without exception of any;</hi> as being all in Darkneſs, in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſet up <hi>themſelves as the most Holy, Innocent People; yea, the onely People of God upon Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Another of the <hi>Doctrines of Devils,</hi> is this:
<note place="margin">4. <hi>Reſting upon their own Righteouſneſs.</hi>
                  </note> When he hath done all he can to darken, and hide from his Diſciples the <hi>true and onely way of Salvation by Chriſt, Revealed in the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:103245:46"/>Goſpel,</hi> and weakned the <hi>Authority of the Scriptures,</hi> and the <hi>Credit, and Eſteem of his People:</hi> Then he introduceth and brings in <hi>ſomething of a Mans own,</hi> inſtead thereof, (that he knows is <hi>inſufficient,</hi> and will fail) in Order to Salvation: That is to ſay, <hi>Man's own Righteouſneſs, Obedience, and works,</hi> and puts them upon truſting to theſe, and ſo Return again to the <hi>Old Covenant of works,</hi> and to neglect the <hi>New Covenant of Grace;</hi> which courſe he knows is the ready way to <hi>Deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And he doth this with the more Efficacy in the minds of Wicked Men, becauſe it is <hi>a Remnant of Corruption,</hi> even in the Minds of Good Men, of all by Nature; there is ſomething of this remaining in the beſt, <hi>a Secret eſteeming; and over-valuing of ſomething of their own;</hi> which is ſeen in the <hi>clear Light of the Spirit,</hi> and confeſſed by all but the Quakers, although they have it in them moſt of any People, yet through the <hi>Darkneſs of their minds</hi> they ſee it not, neither will own any ſuch thing, but tell us, <hi>they own, and witneſs Perfection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having mentioned theſe four particulars, which are the <hi>Chief Points of Doctrine which the Seducing Spirits do Teach thoſe that give heed unto them:</hi> I ſhall now proceed to he reſt of the <hi>Characters,</hi> which the Apoſtle plainly ſets down by the Directions of the holy ghoſt, whereby <hi>falſe Teachers may be known;</hi> as we ſee, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>Speaking lyes in Hypocriſie; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now,
<note place="margin">The Third Character of falſe Teachers: Lies in Hypocriſie.</note> it is eaſie to mention many <hi>lyes in Hypocriſie,</hi> which the Quakers are guilty of: Whereby <hi>this Character</hi> is deeply ſtampt upon them, and made manifeſt to all.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:103245:46"/>
               <p>This is <hi>one Lye in Hypocriſie;</hi> That <hi>Chriſt the true Light is in every Man and Woman that cometh into the World,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Firſt Lye in Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</note> and that if they give heed unto, and Obey the Light that is in them, it is a ſufficient Guide unto Salvation without the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>I ſay, This is <hi>falſe Doctrine, and a Lye in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie:</hi> Chriſt doth not dwell in Wicked, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, Impenitent ſinners; the Devil dwells in them, and Rules, and Reigns in them; he Ruleth in the Children of Diſobedience, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. What Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord hath Chriſt with <hi>Belial, Eph.</hi> 2.2?</p>
               <p>Chriſt often ſtands at the Door, and Knocks, if any Man hear his Voice, and open the Door, he will come in, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. but not otherwiſe: See the Arguments againſt this falſhood.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Strong Man Armed cast out,</hi> p. 12.</note> This alſo is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lye in Hypocriſie;</hi> That <hi>the Quakers build upon the true Foundation, Jeſus Chriſt, and all other Profeſſing People Build upon ſome other falſe Foundation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is <hi>a double Lye in Hypocriſie,</hi> both as to themſelves and other Profeſſing People; many of them (I will not ſay all) do profeſſedly Build upon <hi>a falſe and Sandy Foundation,</hi> which certainly will fail, <hi>i. e. the Light within every Man and woman that come into the world;</hi> and that is not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but a <hi>Creature:</hi> There is <hi>a Natural Light</hi> we know in every Man and Woman, <hi>Reaſon and Conſcience,</hi> but it is not <hi>Chriſt;</hi> he Created it, as all things elſe in the World, but what Compariſon between the <hi>Creator</hi> and the <hi>Creature:</hi> This is at large ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to elſe-where.</p>
               <p>And concerning other Profeſſing People, though
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:103245:47"/>many of them (it is to be feared) do Build upon <hi>falſe Foundations;</hi> yet ſure we are, many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them do Build upon <hi>the true and onely Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> This Lye then is againſt thoſe who Build upon the <hi>true Foundation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Third Lye in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Strong Man Armed,</hi> p. 13.</p>
                  </note> This is another <hi>Lye in Hypocriſie,</hi> That they, (the Quakers) have <hi>a true Faith;</hi> that Faith whereof Chriſt is the Author and Fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher: but the Faith of all others is <hi>an unholy, dead, Imperfect Faith,</hi> it Sanctifies but in part, and ſo will never ſave to the utmoſt.</p>
               <p>This is thus proved to be <hi>a Lye:</hi> There is no <hi>true Faith</hi> but it is known by its <hi>Fruits, works, or Effects, it Purifies the Heart, and works by Love; Love to God, Love to all his People, to his word and Goſpel, to all that is of God, and from God.</hi> Now, it is very Manifeſt by the <hi>Fruits</hi> that the Quakers bring forth in their <hi>Doctrines and Converſations,</hi> that they have not <hi>the Faith of Gods Elect;</hi> it is but <hi>preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a ſhadow of Faith,</hi> whereof the <hi>Devil is the Author,</hi> their Inſtructer in other Doctrines alſo. And it is likewiſe (on the other ſide) manifeſt, that Multitudes of other <hi>Profeſſing Chriſtians</hi> (whom they Deſpiſe) have <hi>true, ſaving, Juſtifying Faith;</hi> by the <hi>Fruits and Effects of it,</hi> in their Hearts, and in their Lives and Converſations.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Fourth Lye in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Strong Man Armed,</hi> p. 13.</p>
                  </note> This is another <hi>Lye in Hypocriſie:</hi> They ſay the <hi>Knowledge</hi> that the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers have is a <hi>Spiritual and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental Knowledge, by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation:</hi> But the knowledge of the <hi>Prieſts and Paſtors of all other Religions in the world,</hi> is but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:103245:47"/>
                  <hi>Ignorance,</hi> they know not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but call him <hi>Devil,</hi> or at beſt, the <hi>Light of Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is thus proved to be <hi>a Lye,</hi> and that a double one: Many of the Teaching Quakers are very <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,</hi> even of the very <hi>Principles of the Doctrines of Christ,</hi> they were never Taught of God, we perceive it plainly by their <hi>Diſcourſe and writings:</hi> O the wonderful Darkneſs and Blindneſs that is upon their Minds! A thick vail of Ignorance, as all Natural, Unregenerate Men have: but <hi>their Vail is double; Natural, and Judicial.</hi> The Natural Man hath not the knowledge of Chriſt, nor of the things of God, he cannot know them (in that ſtate) becauſe they are <hi>Spiritually Diſcerned</hi> and known, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Theſe People know not the <hi>true Light Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> they know not the difference between <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Light and Spiritual light,</hi> but give and aſcribe that to the <hi>Creature,</hi> which properly belongs onely to the <hi>Creator:</hi> They know not the way of <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Chriſt,</hi> but Blaſphemouſly ſlight it, as we find in their Books: And Teach that Men are Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by their <hi>own works,</hi> directly contrary to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> whereby at once, they <hi>deny Chriſt,</hi> and the whole Goſpel, and the whole Deſign of God in the Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p>They know not how to Diſtinguiſh or Diſcern between the <hi>Suggeſtions and Inſpirations of a Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Spirit, and the workings of the Spirit of God in Mens Hearts;</hi> neither do they know, nor give to their Hearers <hi>any Directions</hi> how they may <hi>Try the Spirits, whether they are of God or not,</hi> but plainly bid them <hi>Hearken to the Light within,</hi> give heed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and follow it, and it will lead them to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which gives wonderful Advantage to <hi>Satan,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:103245:48"/>the Seducing Spirit,</hi> to work in their minds, even what he will, ſeeing they have no way to Diſcover him, he being Transformed (at ſuch a time) into an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> and in many things reſembles the <hi>Spirit of God:</hi> And thoſe Ignorant Teachers know no way how to diſcern him, having ſlighted and laid aſide <hi>the Scriptures, whereby one Spirit is known from another,</hi> being deſtitute alſo of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God:</hi> So that (upon this very Account) both they, and their <hi>Ignorant, ſimple Hearers,</hi> are under <hi>ſtrong deluſions,</hi> giving heed unto <hi>Seducing Spirits;</hi> and thence it is that their <hi>Teachings, Books, and Pamphlets</hi> are ſo <hi>falſe,</hi> and ſo directly contrary to the <hi>Truth of the Scriptures:</hi> And yet we ſee they boaſt of their <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and eſteem themſelves more Wiſe and Knowing than all others.</p>
               <p>Fifthly,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Fifth Lye in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Strong Man Armed,</hi> p. 14.</p>
                  </note> Another <hi>Lye in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie</hi> is this: The Quakers ſay, their <hi>Humility</hi> does far exceed all others; it is the <hi>emptying themſelves of all their own Righteouſneſs, Wills, Wiſdom, and ſelf-exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and is a Real, Inward, Spiritual abaſement, and ſubjection to the Life, Power, and Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But O how contrary to theſe words, (nothing but words) are all their <hi>Doctrines and Declarings</hi> to the People, and in all their Pamphlets, if we compare one thing with another! For they do but deceive their ſimple, unwary Hearers with a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of ſome <hi>good words and expreſſions,</hi> now and then, that ſo they may the more readily Receive <hi>the deadly Poyſon</hi> that is mixed therewith: They ſometimes Profeſs in words that they <hi>own Chriſt and the Scriptures, but in deed and reality they deny
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:103245:48"/>both;</hi> as is abundantly proved againſt them, and made manifeſt unto all.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>this very particular Lye in Hypocriſie,</hi> this that I ſay appears plainly: For whereas he here ſays, they are the <hi>moſt humble People,</hi> in that they <hi>empty themſelves of all their own Righteouſneſs, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Self-exaltation,</hi> and have in them <hi>a real, ſpiritual Abaſement and Subjection to Chriſt;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the quite contrary appears in the Subſtance of their Doctrines; Witneſs <hi>Edw. Burrough</hi>'s <hi>Works in Folio, p.</hi> 33. where he ſays plainly, <hi>God doth not Accept any, where there is any failing, or who do not fulfill the Law, and Anſwer every Demand of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> So <hi>William Penn,</hi> Sandy Foundation, <hi>p.</hi> 29, 30. <q>Obedience to Juſtification <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> ought to be as Perſonally extenſive as was Mans Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Condemnation: In which Real <hi>(not Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putative)</hi> ſence thoſe various terms of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Righteouſneſs, Reſurrection, Life, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, Juſtification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are moſt Infallibly underſtood; for <hi>(ſaith he further)</hi> Impute, or Imputing ſignifies no more in Scripture, but to expreſs Men Really and Perſonally to be that which is Imputed to them, whether as guilty, or remitted; for <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> any to be Juſtified from the Imputation of anothers Righteouſneſs, is both Ridiculous and Dangerous, whence came that uſual ſaying amongſt many Profeſſors of Religion; That God looks not upon them, as they are in themſelves, but as they are in Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee now here plainly what Doctrines the <hi>Teaching Quakers</hi> bring forth; and how much it ſavours of <hi>Humility and Self-abaſement,</hi> according to <hi>this great Lye in Hypocriſie</hi> afore-mentioned. This their Doctrine ſhews they are <hi>ſwelled with
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:103245:49"/>Pride; to the very higheſt pitch of Pride, that Self-love</hi> (and Satan to blow it up) <hi>can raiſe them:</hi> Here they Account themſelves <hi>perfect, and able to Anſwer every Demand of Juſtice,</hi> and will not be beholding to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the <hi>Imputation of his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs;</hi> this is the <hi>Humility</hi> of the Quakers. But O Miſerable Creatures are they! and more Miſerable are they yet like to be, whoſe <hi>Humility is the height of Pride,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Righteouſneſs is nothing but the groſſeſt ſin and wickedneſs,</hi> and who have not the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt Imputed to them,</hi> which is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God, and perfect,</hi> as well as <hi>Inherent Righteouſneſs, Created of God, but yet imperfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Doctrine of theirs is <hi>a groſs Lye in Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie,</hi> and the <hi>Grand Doctrine of Devils;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>let it be accurſed;</hi> yea, I ſay again, <hi>let it be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed for ever.</hi> And as for the Teachers of it, they ſhall be accurſed alſo, except they Repent.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Grace of Humility</hi> hath the quite contrary <hi>Effects;</hi> it Teacheth Men to have a low eſteem of themſelves, and when they have done all they can in the ways of Obedience, to account that yet they are but unprofitable Servants.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Humble Spirit</hi> was ſeen in <hi>Paul,</hi> who, though he were <hi>a great Apoſtle,</hi> yet he accounted himſelf <hi>leſs than the leaſt of all Saints;</hi> yea, and teacheth all others to be of the ſame Mind: <hi>In lowlineſs of Mind, let each eſteem other better than themſelves,</hi> Phil. 2.3. How far then are theſe Men from <hi>true Humility?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Sixth Lye in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Strong Man Armed,</hi> p. 15.</p>
                  </note> Another <hi>Lye in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> is this: They ſay, their <hi>Patience is Invincible, to them is this Grace given,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:103245:49"/>The World hath been againſt them, not for their own ſakes, but for Chriſt's ſake in them, though they are</hi> (he ſays) <hi>the moſt Innocent and harmleſs People upon Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, whether this papears to be Truth or a <hi>Lye in Hypocriſie,</hi> may appear by their <hi>Speeches and Writings,</hi> wherein they expreſs and manifeſt <hi>much Bitterneſs of Spirit, Wrath, Anger, Malice, and Impatience,</hi> as is in their frequent <hi>foul, harſh Language,</hi> that proceeds from them, both by their <hi>Tongues and Pens,</hi> againſt thoſe who do Converſe with them, or ask them queſtions, Soberly, and Modeſtly, with a real deſire to be Reſolved; or that ask them a Reaſon of the hope that is in them, or of their perſwaſions about ſuch or ſuch things; Their Anſwers ought to be given with <hi>Meekneſs and Love,</hi> That they may ſatisfie thoſe who ask them, according to Truth: But inſtead thereof they commonly pour out <hi>harſh words and ſpeeches,</hi> like thoſe Enemies of <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 64.4. <hi>They whet their Tongues like a Sword, they bend their Bows, and ſhoot their Arrows, even bitter words.</hi> Witneſs <hi>Edward Burrough</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> p. 20, 21, &amp;c. againſt a Servant of Chriſt, asking him ſerious que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, he Anſwered in ſuch Language as this, (which others alſo of their Teachers do likewiſe own, and approve of.)</p>
               <p>To all, or moſt of the queſtions he mixeth this Language,
<note place="margin">The Quakers Railing Accuſations.</note> (and many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to the like purpoſe) in his Anſwers. <q>Thou Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, and Child of Darkneſs; we witneſs thee to be in the Sorcery and Witchcraft, thou Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon; thy queries are Conjured in the Black Art, out of the Bottomleſs Pit; thou Diviner, we
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:103245:50"/>witneſs thee to be the Beaſt; thou Antichriſt, who looks at Chriſt's Death at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> alone; thou Jeſuite, art pleading for Chriſt afar off thee, thou art Accurſed; thou Beaſt, to whom the Plagues of God are due: Thou Blind Hypocrite, thou <hi>Cain,</hi> thou full of Subtilty; with the Light thou art ſeen, and with the Life thou art Judged and Condemned.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words were poured out, with many more ſuch like <hi>Invectives</hi> againſt him the Queriſt, and others from time to time, as Men have conference with them. But are theſe the <hi>Fruits and Evidences of Patience;</hi> which they boaſt of, which they ſay they have attained above <hi>all other Profeſſing People?</hi> Then what is <hi>Impatience, Wrath, Bitterneſs, and Anger?</hi> Are not their <hi>Tongues ſet on fire of Hell, and moved by the Devil,</hi> who brings the Fire from thence, and kindles it, and blows it up to a great Flame?</p>
               <p>Nay doubtleſs, they are not onely <hi>Pinch'd, and vex'd by ſerious Queſtions, and ſound Scripture Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments,</hi> but alſo even <hi>cut to the Heart,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> were againſt <hi>Stephen,</hi> when he dealt truly and plainly with them, as we ſee, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.54. <hi>When they heard theſe things they were cut to the Heart, and they gnaſhed on him with their Teeth:</hi> So theſe Men they are <hi>vex'd and Angry,</hi> when they are Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and cannot Anſwer, they are <hi>Pinch'd, and cut to the very Heart,</hi> which they ſhew and manifeſt by <hi>ſuch ſpeeches as theſe aforementioned;</hi> for out of the abundance of the Heart, the Mouth ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>Theſe I ſay, are <hi>Lyes in Hypocriſie:</hi> This then is another <hi>Character plainly ſeen upon the Quakers;</hi> whereby compared with the reſt of the <hi>Characters,</hi> ſpoken by the Holy Ghoſt, they are manifeſted to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:103245:50"/>be the <hi>falſe Prophets that ſhould come into the World in theſe laſt days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this day is <hi>this Scripture fulfilled:</hi> The <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> who were fore-told expreſly by the Spirit of God, that they ſhould come in theſe laſt days; <hi>even now are they come in this Generation:</hi> They are <hi>Departed from the Faith, they give heed to Seducing Spirits, and Doctrines of Devils; they ſpeak Lyes in Hypocriſie, having their Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron;</hi> which is the next <hi>Character</hi> to be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">The Fourth Character of falſe Teachers: Their Conſciences are ſeared with an hot Iron.</note> Another <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> whereby <hi>falſe Prophets &amp; Teachers</hi> are known, which the Spirit of God tells us of, is this:</p>
               <p>They have their <hi>Conſcience ſeared with an hot Iron,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.2. This Expreſſion, <hi>ſeared with an hot Iron,</hi> taken <hi>properly,</hi> is a <hi>Similitude</hi> of what is done <hi>Spiritually,</hi> in and upon the Conſciences of ſome more than Ordinary notorious ſinners, under a <hi>Judicial,</hi> as well as <hi>Natural hardneſs of heart, Blindneſs, and Reprobate ſenſe;</hi> unto which Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God ſometimes gives them up, for refuſing to Receive and Hearken to the Truth, often tendred, and Diſcovered to them; with ſome other Notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſins. For as <hi>Natural Fleſh ſeared with an hot Iron,</hi> is thereby made <hi>hard, dead, and inſenſible;</hi> ſo as it will not receive any <hi>Impreſſion,</hi> nor is <hi>ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> as <hi>ſoft, tender, lively Fleſh is;</hi> ſo it is with the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of ſome Men, which are <hi>ſeared,</hi> they have no <hi>Spiritual ſenſe,</hi> nor <hi>feeling of ſpiritual things;</hi> but are <hi>dead, and hardned, blind and deaf,</hi> as concerning the things of God, of which thoſe Chriſtians that have <hi>tender Conſciences, and ſoft
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:103245:51"/>hearts,</hi> have a clear <hi>ſight and ſenſe of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Men whoſe <hi>Conſciences are ſeared with an hot Iron,</hi> they do <hi>think, apprehend, and believe,</hi> (and that ſtrongly too) many things that are <hi>quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Truth;</hi> both as to <hi>Reaſon and Faith:</hi> which things they <hi>ſpeak and write</hi> accordingly.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Another <hi>Sign, or Evidence of thoſe whoſe Conſciences are ſeared with an hot Iron,</hi> is this:</p>
               <p>They will Reject and Deſpiſe all <hi>plain Truths in Scripture,</hi> as being contrary to their <hi>Corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Principles, and Intereſts,</hi> though they are never ſo much concerned therein, and though brought, and tendred to them with never ſo much Love, and earneſt deſire for their good and welfare; yet theſe things take <hi>no Impreſſion upon their hearts,</hi> no more than <hi>upon a ſtone;</hi> they remain ſtill the ſame, and no good is done upon them by any means.</p>
               <p>Nay, Thirdly, (as another <hi>Evidence of a ſeared Conſcience)</hi> The <hi>means uſed to Reform them,</hi> does the <hi>more harden them,</hi> and makes them the <hi>more Deſperate in ſinning;</hi> which is ſeen in their many <hi>Imprecations, Revilings, Slanderings, and bitter Reproachful ſpeeches,</hi> which proceed from them, againſt thoſe that would do them good. Now, is it not hereby Evident and plain, That very many of the Quakers are under <hi>this Judgment, of having their Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron:</hi> So that <hi>this Character</hi> is alſo plainly ſeen upon them, as is made manifeſt particularly by their <hi>Speeches, Books, and Practices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, Another <hi>Character of falſe Teachers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Fifth Character of falſe Teachers:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Denying the Lord that bought us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </note> or rather their <hi>Names</hi> ſpelled out at length, with all the <hi>Letters</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:103245:51"/>that make up their <hi>Names</hi> plain and Legible to all who have clear fight, and <hi>walk in the Light:</hi> Theſe are Named, and ſet down largely and plainly, both by the <hi>Apoſtle Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.1, 2, &amp;c. <hi>and the Apostle Jude</hi> joyns with him; ſee his whole Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>2 Pet. 2.1. <hi>But there were falſe Prophets among the People, even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you; who privily ſhall bring in Damnable Hereſies, even Denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ver. 2. <hi>And many ſhall follow their pernicious ways, by reaſon of whom the way of Truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now before I ſpeak to the particular <hi>Characters,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Apoſtles</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Jude <hi>both agree in the ſame Characters of falſe Teachers.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>or Letters,</hi> whereby (being joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together) we may ſpell out their <hi>Names;</hi> let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this thing, which is of great weight and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the Buſineſs in hand, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Peter</hi> ſpends a <hi>whole Chapter</hi> in decyphering, and marking out <hi>theſe falſe Teachers,</hi> which ſhould come <hi>in theſe latter days:</hi> And ſo doth the <hi>Apoſtle Jude</hi> alſo ſpend his <hi>whole Epiſtle</hi> to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, concerning <hi>the very ſame Men,</hi> both of them Agreeing in the <hi>ſelf-ſame particular Characters, Letters, or Marks,</hi> whereby they are known, as we may ſee in the particulars following.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:103245:52"/>
               <p>Firſt then:</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 Pet. 2.1. <hi>There ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in Damnable hereſies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. So <hi>Jude, to the ſame purpoſe,</hi> ver. 4. <hi>There are certain Men crept in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, who were of Old Ordained to this condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly men,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, <hi>Both brand them with this Mark, or Character,</hi> ver. 1. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lord that bought them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. So <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 3. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the onely Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Both note their <hi>Pride and Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in Deſpiſing Government, and ſpeaking evil of Dignities:</hi> The moſt Eminent, and chief Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, both in <hi>Church and State,</hi> Exalting themſelves above them all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 2 Pet. 2.10. <hi>They Deſpiſe Government, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous are they, ſelf-willed; they are not afraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. So <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 8. <hi>They Deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Both the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> note their height of <hi>Pride and Preſumption,</hi> in Deſpiſing Perſons of greateſt Worth and Eminency, <hi>both in Church and State,</hi> i. e. <hi>Dignities.</hi> They both ſet out their <hi>Pride and exceſſive Ambition</hi> by way of <hi>Aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> telling us, That even the Angels of God, which are far more Excellent Creatures in Wiſdom and Power than Men; yet even they do not bring <hi>Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſation</hi> againſt men, in any caſe; no, nor againſt the <hi>Devil:</hi> But <hi>theſe</hi> (with an Emphaſis) <hi>as Natural Brute Beaſts,</hi> ſpeak evil of the things
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:103245:52"/>they Underſtand not; ſo that hereby is the ſin of theſe Men Aggravated and heightned, who do fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>in their Pride and Diſpleaſure bring Railing accuſations</hi> againſt good Men, that Oppoſe their falſe Doctrines, as is already particularly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. 2 Pet. 2.11. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels which are greater in Power and Might, bring not Railing accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them before the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. So <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 9. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael, the Arch-Angel, when contending with the Devil about the Body of</hi> Moſes, <hi>durſt not bring againſt him a Railing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation; but ſaid, The Lord Rebuke thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Both the Apoſtles Mark them out by <hi>this Character,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.17. <hi>Theſe are Wells without Water; Clouds carried about with a Tempeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. So <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 12. <hi>Clouds they are without Water, carried about with Winds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are <hi>Wells and Clouds without water,</hi> ſhews and ſhadows without Subſtance, Husks and Shells without Kernels, having ſome Form or ſhew of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Godlineſs, and Chriſtianity,</hi> but not the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Life;</hi> no Real, or true <hi>Grace or holineſs;</hi> no <hi>water of Life from the pure Fountain of Life;</hi> they have not the <hi>Spirit of Life,</hi> which in Believers is a <hi>Well of water ſpringing up to Eternal Life;</hi> but theſe are as <hi>Clouds without water, carried about with the winds of Temptations,</hi> i.e. <hi>Secret impulſes of ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> that hurry them to and fro, of their Errands and Buſineſs; and then they Cry, it is from <hi>the Light within.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:103245:53"/>
               <p n="6">6. A Sixth Character. Both the Apoſtles ſay, They are <hi>in the way of</hi> Balaam: 2 Pet. 2.15. <hi>They have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray, following the way of</hi> Balaam.</p>
               <p n="6">6. So <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 11. <hi>Wo unto them, for they have gone in the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and ran greedily after the Error of</hi> Balaam <hi>for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and periſhed in the gain-ſaying of</hi> Core.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſays, <hi>They have gone in the way of</hi> Cain; it's true, <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew his Brother: Now, theſe Men, though they riſe not againſt any with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Weapons,</hi> yet their <hi>hearts riſe againſt their Oppoſers,</hi> as appears in that they <hi>whet their Tongues like a Sword, and ſhoot out their Arrows, even bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter words,</hi> like <hi>David</hi>'s Enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.4. In that ſence they have gone in <hi>the way of</hi> Cain, and <hi>ran greedily after the Error of</hi> Balaam: And as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>they are gone aſtray, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owing the way of</hi> Balaam.</p>
               <p>Now, what was the <hi>way of</hi> Balaam, the <hi>Error of</hi> Balaam? Was it not chiefly, in that he went <hi>ſo contrary to the known Will and Word of God; the Will and Mind of God was plainly, and often made known unto him;</hi> that he ſhould not go to Curſe the <hi>People of Iſrael, the Lords People:</hi> It was <hi>plainly and manifeſtly made known and Revealed unto him,</hi> and yet he would go, contrary to the <hi>plain revealed Will of God;</hi> which was the moſt Deſperate Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Folly that could poſſibly be: The Apoſtle calls it <hi>Madneſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.16. <hi>The dumb Aſſe ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Mans Voice forbad the Madneſs of the Prophet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, theſe Men, the Teachers among the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, have <hi>gone in the way of</hi> Balaam, and do ſtill
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:103245:53"/>go and run <hi>greedily, earneſtly after the Error of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam: In that the <hi>Mind and will of God is plainly and fully Revealed, and made known unto them in the Scriptures;</hi> and which hath been often, very often Declared, and proved by the <hi>clear Light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> by many of his true and Faithful <hi>Meſſengers and Ambaſſadors,</hi> ſent of God, and Taught of God, and have the mind of Chriſt, and have made it known unto them, and yet <hi>ſo Blind, ſo Ignorant, ſo Deſperately mad</hi> are they, as that they go on ſtill <hi>in the way of</hi> Balaam, <hi>after the Error of</hi> Balaam in this Deſperate <hi>Madneſs and wickedneſs,</hi> as <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am did in his,</hi> Directly againſt the <hi>plain and clear word of God Revealed in the Scriptures;</hi> as hath been fully proved in many particulars, by many that have pleaded againſt them, and manifeſted their Errors: And it may well be ſuppoſed alſo, that many of them run greedily <hi>after the Error of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam <hi>for Reward, or Advantage,</hi> being <hi>Tradeſmen, and great dealers in worldly affairs,</hi> they may have Reſpect to the Recompence of Reward or Profit (in a quite contrary ſence to <hi>Moſes</hi>'s choice) <hi>in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one with another,</hi> and making Advantages that way; for I am ſure they have <hi>no true Spiritual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements</hi> to go on in that way; but all are to turn them out of <hi>this way of</hi> Balaam: But they blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go on, or are drawn, or driven, or carried as <hi>Clouds in a Storm or Tempest,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle goes on further, and ſays, <hi>They ſhall periſh in the gain-ſaying of</hi> Core; for as <hi>Core,</hi> and his Company with him periſhed for Oppoſing, and <hi>Deſpiſing</hi> Moſes <hi>and the People of the Lord with him,</hi> and ſetting up themſelves againſt them (and in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them, they di <hi>Oppoſe and Deſpiſe the Lord, in and among them</hi>) even ſo do theſe People now,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:103245:54"/>
                  <hi>they ſet up themſelves proudly, in Oppoſition to all the Lords precious People in every place,</hi> and call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>onely holy people of the Lord upon the Earth;</hi> and herein they go beyond, and above <hi>Core and his Company;</hi> for they did not deny but that <hi>Moſes</hi> and others were <hi>holy,</hi> but they took too much upon them: <hi>Core and his Company</hi> would be Reſpected alſo, ſeeing <hi>all the Lords people were ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every one of them,</hi> and ſo they Murmured, and chid with <hi>Moſes and Aaron,</hi> and ſaid <hi>Proudly and Stubbornly, they would not come up,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> called them; they were very Obſtinate, but yet gave no ſuch <hi>Language,</hi> neither fell upon them with <hi>Railing Accuſations,</hi> as theſe Men do againſt the <hi>Societies and Congregations of the Lords People:</hi> But Obſerve the Iſſue of all this; the Text ſaith, <hi>they Periſhed:</hi> Core <hi>and his Company</hi> Periſhed for their Pride, Gain-ſayings, and Reſiſtance; and what can theſe Men expect, but ſooner or later, though not ſuddenly, or in that manner as they? Yet hath not our Lord ſaid, That <hi>it were better for any that a Mill-ſtone were hanged about their neck, and they caſt with it into the Sea, than that they ſhould Offend one of his Little Ones that believe in him,</hi> Mat. 18.6. What Puniſhment then muſt be for him, or thoſe who Offend <hi>ſo many thouſands of the Lords little Ones, and Peculiar ones,</hi> dear unto him as the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Eye? Who can tell how <hi>ſore a Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſuch ſhall be thought worthy of, when the Lord cometh with <hi>Vengeance againſt his implacable hardned Enemies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Seventhly, Both the Apoſtles Mark them out for <hi>Puniſhments</hi> when their ſin is come to its <hi>full meaſure and height;</hi> and do aſſure us, That as God hath Puniſhed and Deſtroyed other great ſinners in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:103245:54"/>former Days, ſo he will do to theſe alſo.</p>
               <p n="7">7. 2 Pet. 2.4. <hi>If God ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ver. 5. <hi>Spared not the old world, but deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ver. 6. <hi>And turned the Cities of</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrah <hi>into aſhes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them Examples unto thoſe that after ſhould live ungodly.</hi> So theſe falſe Teachers.</p>
               <p>2 Pet. 2.1. <hi>They ſhall bring upon themſelves, ſwift deſtruction. Their Judgment lingreth not, and their damnation ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth not,</hi> ver. 3.</p>
               <p>So alſo <hi>Jude</hi> notes their Puniſhment as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have been.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Ver. 5. <hi>He deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the people of</hi> Iſrael <hi>that believed not,</hi> and Verſ. 6. <hi>The Angels that kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their own habitation, he hath reſerved in everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chains, under dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, unto the Judgment of the great day.</hi> Ver. 7. <hi>Even as</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah, <hi>and the Cities about them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are ſet forth for an Example ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the vengeance of eternal fire. Woe unto them,</hi> &amp;c. ver. 11.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles both having inſtanced in theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>great examples</hi> of God's wrath upon <hi>great ſinners,</hi> would have us to know and be aſſured, that as theſe mentioned were puniſhed, ſo alſo ſhall <hi>theſe falſe Prophets and Teachers,</hi> that are marked out with <hi>theſe Characters,</hi> as they have both of them mentioned; for they both intend, and ſet out the <hi>ſame men,</hi> as we ſee both agree, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the <hi>ſame Characters or Letters,</hi> which being ſet together, a diſcerning eye will read, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand who they are when they appear in the world <hi>in theſe latter dayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:103245:55"/>
               <p>And as a further Aſſurance of their <hi>downfall and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Enochs <hi>Propheſie of theſe ungodly ſinners.</hi>
                  </note> beſides what theſe two Apoſtles have told us; Enoch <hi>alſo the ſeventh from</hi> Adam Propheſied of theſe, ſaying, <hi>Jude</hi> ver. 14. <hi>Behold the Lord cometh with thouſands of his Saints, to execute Judgment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly among them, of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodlily committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee here <hi>theſe ungodly men</hi> ſhall be called to an Account for all their <hi>ungodly deeds whatſoever:</hi> And in particular, for all their <hi>Erroneous and Falſe Doctrines, Books, Pamphlets, and Writings,</hi> which have proceeded from them, wherein are ſo many hard ſpeeches againſt Him, <hi>this great Him,</hi> even <hi>Jeſus Chriſt Himſelf;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Quakers have ſpoken Hard ſpeeches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Chriſt.</note> who will ſhortly come to judge the world in righteouſneſs. Theſe men the <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> among the Quakers, have ſpoken many hard ſpeeches <hi>againſt him immediately, and directly;</hi> and alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>him mediately;</hi> that is, againſt <hi>his Members, his People,</hi> for inaſmuch as they did ſo againſt any of his <hi>Brethren,</hi> they did it <hi>unto Him;</hi> But O how many <hi>hard ſpeeches, blaſphemous ſpeeches</hi> have theſe ungodly ſinners ſpoken <hi>againſt him immediately, and directly, in denying, and diſ-owning of him, in his Perſon, in his Natures, in his Offices, in his Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Death, Blood, and Sufferings, in his All-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Righteouſneſs, Satisfaction, and Juſtification, wrought for all believers;</hi> ſpeaking ſlightly of him, as <hi>a Chriſt afar off,</hi> and <hi>at a diſtance,</hi> deſpiſing thoſe that ſpeak of <hi>a Perſonall Chriſt in Heaven;</hi> Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:103245:55"/>
                  <hi>no Chriſt but what they have within;</hi> and that's nothing but <hi>a blind, naturall, defiled Conſcience;</hi> which it ſeemes can ſuffer them to <hi>blaſpheme Chriſt now in Heaven,</hi> in glory, making interceſſion for all believers.</p>
               <p>Of many of theſe <hi>horrid, unheard of Blaſphemies againſt Chriſt,</hi> ſee <hi>Edw. Burrough's Workes in Folio pag.</hi> 33. 34. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alſo Will. Penn, Sandy Foundation, pag.</hi> 29, 30. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe many <hi>hard, and blaſphemous ſpeeches ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken directly againſt our precious Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> he will ſhortly come to call them to an account for, and <hi>puniſh them accordingly:</hi> Yea, and for all the <hi>hard ſpeeches</hi> ſpoken alſo againſt <hi>his people,</hi> who are dear unto him; it had been better for theſe men that a Milſtone had been tyed about their necks, and that they had been caſt into the Sea, than to have offended them, and ſpoken ſo hardly and falſly of them, as they have done. They make no difference among Profeſſors; they ſeparate not the precious from the vile.</p>
               <p>Theſe things are fully and at large ſet forth in three Dialogues between a Chriſtian and a Quaker. By <hi>Tho. Hicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And further yet, he brands them with another <hi>plain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Quakers ſeparation from Chriſt and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple proves they are no Chriſtians.</note> 
                  <hi>and notorious Mark, or Character,</hi> which is conſpicuous to every eye, that by this <hi>Plain Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> joyned to all the reſt, ſo viſible alſo, theſe being joyned and ſet altogether, we may ſpell their <hi>Names and their Natures</hi> ſo plainly, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not miſtake the men: for although there are other <hi>falſe Prophets and Teachers</hi> in the world beſides
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:103245:56"/>yet they are of another ſort; we muſt ſpell their Names, and know them by other <hi>Marks, Letters, and Characters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, <hi>this Character</hi> which yet follows in <hi>this Epiſtle of</hi> Jude, is in the 19. verſe: <hi>Theſe are they who ſeparate themſelves; ſenſual, having not the Spirit:</hi> Now, let it be well conſidered who they are that <hi>ſeparate,</hi> and from whom they <hi>ſeparate:</hi> There is a <hi>Separation</hi> indeed, that is not onely good and Lawful, but alſo a Duty: There is a Command for it; but what is that <hi>Separation?</hi> We ſee it plainly, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>Believers</hi> that were Converted by the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, were Commanded to come out from among the <hi>Heatheniſh Idolaters,</hi> and not to be partakers with them any longer in their <hi>Heatheniſh, Idolatrous Worſhip, in Worſhipping Idols, Wood and Stone, the works of Mens Hands:</hi> But what is that <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this Separation?</hi> This <hi>ſeparation</hi> the Apoſtle takes Notice of, as a very <hi>groſs ſin;</hi> and we ſee it is one of the <hi>Letters, or Characters of theſe Men</hi> of whom they ſpeak, the <hi>falſe Teachers;</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty of all thoſe great and groſs ſins, which theſe two Apoſtles (<hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi>) had newly mentioned; he now adds to them all another <hi>plain, broad, conſpicuous brand,</hi> and ſets it on with an <hi>Emphaſis, Theſe are they that Separate themſelves; ſenſual, having not the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As if the Apoſtle had ſaid in more words, The <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> that I have been now ſpeaking of, and the many that follow their pernicious ways, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſe are they, theſe are the People who ſeparate themſelves;</hi> and from whom ſhall they <hi>ſeparate?</hi> Even from the <hi>People of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Churches, Congregations, and Aſſemblies of the Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:103245:56"/>
               <p>Now, do not <hi>theſe Men ſo?</hi> Do not the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſeparate themſelves from all the Saints, from all the particular Churches and Aſſemblies of the Lords People, in all the Land,</hi> as if they were <hi>Heathens and Idolaters;</hi> and ſpeak evil of them, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them with many <hi>bitter words and ſlanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Witneſs <hi>James Jackſon, (Author of the ſtrong Man Armed caſt out) in his Separation from the Churches of the Independents,</hi> who Reproaches the <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and brings <hi>Railing Accuſations againſt them,</hi> and many other of the precious Saints, even as the <hi>Apoſtles, Peter and Jude,</hi> do Declare as one of the <hi>Characters</hi> of theſe People, as hath been ſhewed: And yet he glories in this <hi>his Separation,</hi> and Accounts it (as we ſee) as one ſpecial <hi>mark of his Converſion,</hi> that he is turned from <hi>Darkneſs to Light,</hi> and from the Power of Satan (that <hi>ſtrong Man Armed</hi> being now caſt out) he is come <hi>to God, and to his People,</hi> who (as he tells us,) are the <hi>moſt Holy, Innocent People upon the Earth:</hi> And this his <hi>Converſion he aſcribes to the Light within, which Light</hi> (as he alſo ſaith) <hi>hath Converted Thouſands</hi> in like manner unto God; (yea, as he himſelf is <hi>Converted;</hi>) And counts it a Marvellous thing that thoſe who think themſelves Chriſtians, ſhould not Acknowledge <hi>this Light within to be Chriſt, the true Light,</hi> that hath done ſuch mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous things for him, and many others: But that they ſhould call it <hi>Natural Light, or the Devil;</hi> he accounts this <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, if we do but Examine this his and others <hi>Separation</hi> according to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and look upon it in the <hi>true Light indeed,</hi> we ſhall ſee and find, that it is ſo far from being <hi>a Mark, or Sign of their true Converſion</hi> (as he and they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:103245:57"/>it) that it <hi>is indeed a Mark and Evidence of their Carnal, Dark, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate ſtate:</hi> And ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> Accounts it to be; and a <hi>Note or Character</hi> of the Ungodly Men, the <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> which he had been ſpeaking of, throughout his <hi>whole Epiſtle;</hi> And ſets it on as <hi>a plain Mark</hi> for all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſee and take Notice of; <hi>Theſe are they that Separate themſelves,</hi> Jude 19. Yea, and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> John <hi>joyns his Teſtimony with him,</hi> to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18, 19. The Apoſtle here ſpeaks of ſome <hi>in his time,</hi> that were like theſe very Men <hi>in our time;</hi> As we ſee, <hi>Little Children, it is the laſt time: And as ye have heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, even now are there many Antichriſts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we know that it is the laſt time.</hi> And he makes their <hi>Separation</hi> (as we ſee) <hi>a Character of their wickedneſs,</hi> ver. 19. <hi>They went out from us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us; but they went out that they might be made manifeſt that they were not all of us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee here what <hi>ſeparation from the People of the Lord,</hi> and their Aſſemblies is Accounted, by this Apoſtle alſo, he tells us plainly, it is <hi>a Mark or Character of wicked Men;</hi> That ſuch as <hi>ſo ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> are <hi>none of the Number of Gods People,</hi> they went out, or <hi>ſeparated from us, becauſe they were not of us;</hi> they were <hi>none of Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Members, no Believers,</hi> as we are; they were not <hi>of us:</hi> For (ſaith he) if they had been <hi>of us,</hi> if they had been <hi>of the ſame Body with us,</hi> whereof Chriſt is the Head, then no doubt they would have continued <hi>with us,</hi> and not have <hi>ſeparated from us;</hi> but it is ſo, <hi>they went out from us, they forſook us, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from us,</hi> that it might be made manifeſt,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:103245:57"/>that <hi>ſuch were not of us, that ſuch were not joyned to Chriſt, as we are.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then, what grounds of boaſting this <hi>James Jackſon,</hi> or any other of his Principles and Practice, have in their <hi>ſeparations</hi> from the true Churches of Chriſt, (and joyn with a deluded, Ignorant Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that Fanſy themſelves the onely People of the Lord, as being Converted by the Light within) we leave to thoſe who are Taught of God to Conſider and Judge.</p>
               <p>Alas, Poor, Ignorant,
<note place="margin">A Lying Spirit is gone forth amongſt the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, which Seduceth them.</note> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Men! They Underſtand not, That a falſe, and Lying Spirit (or many) is gone forth among them, and hath Deceived them. If there were but <hi>this one Mark or Character,</hi> (though there are many more men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) yet it were enough of it ſelf to Diſcover them, that they are led by <hi>a Lying, Seducing ſpirit,</hi> which hath perſwaded them: That is, Their <q>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning, and Reproaching ſo many Thouſands of the Lord's People; Miniſters and Ambaſſadors ſent of God, Paſtors of particular Churches and Congregations; all Profeſſing People in the Land, yea, in the World, without exception of any.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And although many that are called <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the Land, and many <hi>Profeſſors</hi> are groſſely guilty of ſin, and deny Chriſt in their Works and Doings, which is to be Lamented; Muſt therefore all the <hi>Saints and true Members of Chriſt</hi> be Diſowned, and Denyed alſo, whereof there are many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands? If theſe Men had the Spirit of God, and were enlightned, and led by him, they would make a <hi>Difference,</hi> and ſeparate the <hi>precious</hi> from the <hi>vile;</hi> but they do not <hi>Diſtinguiſh</hi> between the <hi>Righteous</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:103245:58"/>and the <hi>Wicked,</hi> but Condemn them together, and ſo are Abomination to the Lord: So that thereby it is plainly ſeen, that <hi>they are not of God;</hi> that they are not as his Mouth to the People (as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. It is the <hi>Seducing Spirit,</hi> we may be ſure, that doth bely, and Reproach the Lord's People, and his Works and Operations in them. By this, and other <hi>Characters</hi> afore-mentioned, we may be as ſure who the Men are, as if their Proper Names (whereby the World knows them from other Men) were Recorded in Scripture. For as the Lords People may certainly know that their <hi>Names</hi> are in the Scriptures, and are Written in Heaven, in the Book of Life (Gods Eternal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and Secret Counſell) by Seeing and Reading their <hi>Natures, Properties and Qualifications</hi> in the Scriptures, to which Eternal Life is promiſed: I ſay, they may know thereby that they themſelves are the Perſons, as certainly as if their <hi>Proper Names</hi> were there Recorded, whereby they are known amongſt Men: So on the contrary, of Wicked and Ungodly Men, they are alſo known, in like manner, by their <hi>Natures, Properties, and Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We know who hath ſaid,
<note place="margin">Births of the Spirit, and of the Fleſh.</note> 
                  <hi>That which is Born of the fleſh, is fleſh; and that which is Born of the ſpirit, is ſpirit:</hi> We may know of what it is Born by the <hi>Birth</hi> that is brought forth: <hi>Satan</hi> he broods upon the Carnal Spirits of wicked Men, and begets <hi>falſe Notions, Opinions, and Principles,</hi> we may know they are of his begetting by their <hi>Form and ſhape,</hi> when they are brought forth: <hi>Principles of Pride, ſelf-love, falſe Notions,</hi> and other Deformed ſhapes, when they are Conceived,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:103245:58"/>then after a while they are <hi>brought forth,</hi> they are <hi>born,</hi> they are <hi>Publiſhed and Declared;</hi> in <hi>Diſcourſe, Preaching, Writing, or Printing;</hi> the <hi>Births</hi> of Mens minds, their Fleſhly, Carnal Minds are brought forth into the World; and they are ſo like their Father the Devil, that thereby they may be known who was the Father of them.</p>
               <p>So on the contrary, <hi>That which is Born of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is ſpirit;</hi> the <hi>ſpirit of God dwells</hi> in his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and he daily works, and moves in them, he Inſpires them with <hi>Truths,</hi> according to the Mind of God, which the Spiritual Mind <hi>Conceives,</hi> and brings forth in <hi>Prayer, Preaching, Diſcourſe, and Writings;</hi> and theſe <hi>Conceptions</hi> are <hi>Born and brought forth into the World;</hi> to the View and Knowledge of all: And that which is thus <hi>born of the ſpirit, is ſpirit,</hi> or <hi>ſpiritual;</hi> it is <hi>Truth:</hi> According to the <hi>Mind of the ſpirit;</hi> for he that is joyned to the Lord, is <hi>one ſpirit;</hi> one with him, of his Mind: The Saints are Unanimous, of the ſame Mind with God, as Wicked and Unregenerate Men are unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous with the Devil; they are of his Mind, and he of theirs; for he Ruleth in the Children of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Devil</hi> ſpeaks againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo do they; though they will own him in Words, in Form, in Shew, and Pretence, yet in Deed, in Works, really, they deny him: The <hi>Devil</hi> will own the <hi>Scriptures in words,</hi> as he does <hi>Chriſt in words,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Thou art the Holy one of God;</hi> ſo will thoſe who are <hi>one ſpirit with him,</hi> but will <hi>deny him really,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Truth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Devil</hi> will own the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and Argue from them, to attain his ends, but never to prove a Neceſſary Truth: So <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> are unanimous
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:103245:59"/>with him in theſe things; for he that is <hi>joyned to the Devil, is one Spirit,</hi> even as he that is <hi>joyned to the Lord, is one Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How great then is the ſin of theſe Men,
<note place="margin">Spiritual ſins are greater than fleſhly ſins.</note> who <hi>Conceive in their Minds, and bring forth the Births of the Devil;</hi> as all <hi>Doctrines of Devils</hi> are! Surely, Theſe <hi>Spiritual ſins</hi> are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than <hi>fleſhly ſins;</hi> as <hi>Drunkenneſs, Gluttony, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Murder,</hi> &amp;c. (If Robbery, or Murder of a Man be ſo great a ſin, what is it to Rob God, and to Crucifie, and be guilty of the Blood of Chriſt.) Though for theſe, and ſuch like, when Men will not be reclaimed from them, God often gives them up to a <hi>Reprobate Mind,</hi> Rom. 1. Even ſo he does alſo for theſe <hi>ſpiritual ſins, falſe Opinions, Doctrines, and Principles:</hi> Concerning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Natures, Righteouſneſs, Merits,</hi> and the <hi>things of God,</hi> when they will not be Inſtructed, but hate to be Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and change their Mind, when they will not hearken to the <hi>Truth,</hi> but ſtill reſiſt it, diſown it, contradict, and Blaſpheme; when the Truths of the Goſpel have been often Offered, and tendred to them, yet they will not hear, nor regard, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>believe Lyes,</hi> than the <hi>Truth,</hi> then God gives them up to <hi>strong deluſion,</hi> to believe Lyes, and to hearken, and give heed to <hi>ſeducing ſpirits:</hi> this is a very dreadful ſtate indeed, they draw theſe <hi>ſpiritual Judgments</hi> upon themſelves by theſe <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Quakers</hi> ſetting up this <hi>Idol, The Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every Man and Woman,</hi> is a greater ſin in them, than for <hi>Jezebels falſe Prophets</hi> to ſet up <hi>Baal,</hi> and Pray unto it, and truſt in it, inſtead of the <hi>God of Iſrael.</hi> May it not <hi>(Ironically)</hi> be ſaid to them,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:103245:59"/>as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to thoſe <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> Cry aloud, for he is a god (as ye ſay) but he is but a <hi>Blind god,</hi> he hath <hi>Eyes indeed, but he cannot ſee; Ears, but he cannot hear; Hands and Feet, but he cannot move,</hi> to help, or do any thing for thoſe who Truſt in him, without help from another.</p>
               <p>If theſe Men will not be <hi>pleaded,</hi> nor <hi>perſwaded</hi> out of their Vain, Ignorant, ſottiſh Opinion of <hi>the Light within every Man and Woman,</hi> being <hi>Chriſt;</hi> let Men endeavour to Shame them out of it; for it hath not ſo much as a ſhew, or ſhadow of Truth in it; but is plainly <hi>a moſt dreadful deluſion of the Devil, and a great Blaſphemy againſt Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Opinion of theirs,
<note place="margin">The falſe Opinions of the Quakers ſpring from Pride and Ignorance.</note> with other of their falſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, ſprings from <hi>Pride and Ignorance:</hi> And this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Obſerves concerning ſuch Men, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3, 4. <hi>If any Man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to wholſome words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the Doctrine which is according to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> Ver. 4. <hi>He is Proud, knowing nothing, but Doting about Queſtions, and ſtrife of words, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cometh Envy, Strife, Railing, Evil ſurmiſings.</hi> Ver. 5. <hi>Perverſe Diſputings of Men of Corrupt Minds, and Deſtitute of the Truth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Such kind of men were alſo in the Apoſtle <hi>Johns</hi> time, as we ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17. They were <hi>Proud and Ignorant;</hi> They thought themſelves <hi>Rich, and had need of Nothing; whereas indeed they were poor and miſerable, and blind and naked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is our duty to diſcover theſe kind of people, to try them, and to make them manifeſt to the world as much as may be: for their <hi>falſe Opinions of God, of Themſelves, and of Others,</hi> is no leſs than <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:103245:60"/>Rev. 2.9. <hi>I know the blaſphemy of them that ſay they are Jewes, and are not, but are the Synagogue of Sathan,</hi> The Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> is commended for this, That as they cannot bear theſe <hi>falſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> ſo alſo to <hi>diſcover them, to try them,</hi> and make them manifeſt to others, <hi>by Scripture Characters and Marks,</hi> by which they may be known: Rev. 2.2. <hi>I know thy workes, and thy labour, and thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and how thou canſt not bear them which are evil; And thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and haſt found them Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſpeaking of <hi>deceiving and deceived perſons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Quakers deceive, weak and ſimple minds.</note> he tells us, they ſhall not long continue thus to <hi>deceive; for their folly ſhall be made manifeſt to all men:</hi> 2 Tim. 3.8, 9. The Apoſtle by the Teachings, and Inſpirations of the Spirit of God, having in the former verſes told us, <hi>that in the laſt dayes perillous times ſhall come,</hi> That <hi>men ſhall be lovers of themſelves, proud, boaſters, blaſphemers, &amp;c.</hi> in the next verſe he ſhewes us a <hi>Token,</hi> and ſets a <hi>Mark of diſtinction</hi> upon them: <hi>Of this ſort</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are they which creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women, laden with ſins, led away with divers luſts,</hi> ver. 7. <hi>ever learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee here, what ſort of men are active to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; what they do <hi>privately, creep into houſes;</hi> and alſo the <hi>ſubjects</hi> they work upon; by their <hi>cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning craftineſs,</hi> whereby they lye in wait to deceive (as the Apoſtle ſaith) That is, <hi>ſilly women, ſimple people,</hi> perſons of <hi>weak underſtandings, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall faculties; of ſhallow capacities,</hi> eaſily led away, with divers Luſts, and Errors; ſuch kind of <hi>weak
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:103245:60"/>and ſimple minds</hi> are eaſily deceived: They know not how to diſtinguiſh between <hi>Truth and Errors;</hi> they are ſtill <hi>Hearing and Learning,</hi> but are never able to come to the knowledge of the <hi>Truth:</hi> at leaſt they are never able to come to the knowledge of <hi>ſome Truths,</hi> for ſome <hi>Truths</hi> lye more deep than others. Some are more eaſie to be apprehended, than ſome others: ſome <hi>Truths are hard to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,</hi> as the the Apoſtle obſerves; which they that are unſtable, pervert; yea, and they that are but weak, and ſhallow of underſtanding, do alſo pervert, miſtake, miſapprehend, and miſapply.</p>
               <p>As for inſtance <hi>in this very thing; This Principle and Opinion</hi> of the Quakers, concerning the <hi>Light within:</hi> We know how they apprehend it; Their Teachers, and their hearers, they call it <hi>Chriſt:</hi> who lighteth every man and woman that cometh into the world; This Notion borders upon a <hi>Truth,</hi> and hath ſome ſmall ſhaddowy reſemblance of a <hi>Truth,</hi> but is not <hi>a Truth,</hi> as theſe weak people apprehend it. For there is <hi>a light within</hi> which ſees, and works, and moves ſeveral wayes, toward that which appeares good, according as it apprehends it, and againſt what it thinks to be evil; now this herein hath ſome reſemblance <hi>of Chriſt; and his Spirit:</hi> and ſo <hi>weak minds, ſilly men, and women,</hi> may think it to be ſo indeed; eſpecially when they hear it poſitively, and plainly aſſerted, affirmed, and contended for, by men who have gained their affections, by their demure Countenances, modeſt behaviour, and apparell, and many good words, and fair ſpeeches, with ſeeming zeal; they are thereby confirmed in this perſwaſion, that ſurely it is Chriſt indeed.</p>
               <p>But <hi>this perſwaſion cometh not of him that calleth
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:103245:61"/>us:</hi> Gal. 5.8. (as the Apoſtle here ſaith) but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from <hi>weakneſs and ignorance;</hi> from the <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the underſtanding,</hi> helped on, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by that <hi>deceiver of deceivers, the ſeducing ſpirit;</hi> who is ſtill ready, as to <hi>beget,</hi> ſo alſo to <hi>feed and nouriſh falſe Opinions,</hi> in the minds of all; as God permits him.</p>
               <p>Certain it is, <hi>Reaſon and Natural Conſcience is a Light within,</hi> and diſcerns many things, both <hi>good and evil;</hi> and acts towards, or againſt them, accordingly; ſo far as it ſees and diſcerns, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>meaſure of Light</hi> that is in the <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> This is clear from <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. where the Apoſtle ſpeakes of the worſt of men, who had <hi>this Light</hi> in them, and therefore were inexcuſable in going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. <hi>This Light within,</hi> though it be not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet it was created <hi>by Chriſt,</hi> as all things elſe were, but it cannot go beyond its bounds; No more than <hi>Natural water</hi> can of it ſelf, riſe higher than <hi>the ſpring head,</hi> the <hi>light within cannot ſee Chriſt,</hi> nor <hi>the way, and means of Salvation by him, without the light of the Scriptures, and of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Quakers are ſtrongly confirmed, That <hi>the Light within every man and woman is Chriſt;</hi> let all men ſay what they will to the contrary: yet moſt certain it is that <hi>this Opinion</hi> of theirs, was <hi>begotten by ignorance,</hi> and is <hi>nouriſhed and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Pride:</hi> for they having aſſerted it, and ſo long ſtood to it, in upholding it; they have not the <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> to retract, and acknowledge an Errour, (though ſome may be ſecretly convinced that it is ſo) for it is <hi>Natural</hi> to men to maintain, and ſtand to what they have once <hi>owned and aſſerted;</hi> they are loth to ſtoop, and acknowledge <hi>ignorance,</hi> no
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:103245:61"/>not unto <hi>God himſelf,</hi> much leſs to Men.</p>
               <p>I am perſwaded, There were never any Sect, or ſort of People from the Creation of the World to this day, that were <hi>more irrational, and leſs ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> than theſe People the Quakers are in all their <hi>Diſcourſes, Principles, Books, and Practices;</hi> nor <hi>greater Enemies to Chriſt, his Goſpel, and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> 
                  <q>As the Lord Liveth, who hath delivered me out of great Tribulations, and ſaved me from the hand of the Enemy, I will contribute my utmoſt abilities to throw down the Enemies of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and theſe, and all Doctrines of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and Lyes in Hypocriſie, and whatſoever elſe ſhall Oppoſe him, or his Intereſt in the World.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now,
<note place="margin">The Quakers ſhall not long continue to deceive.</note> this being manifeſt by all <hi>theſe Marks and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> that have been mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That theſe Men, the <hi>falſe Teachers among the Quakers,</hi> are the <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> ſpoken of in the Scriptures, that ſhould come <hi>in theſe laſt days:</hi> The Apoſtle alſo tells us, that <hi>they ſhall not long continue to deceive,</hi> they ſhall be of no long ſtanding, <hi>for their Folly ſhall be made manifeſt unto all men,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.9.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle here compares them to <hi>Jannes and Jambres,</hi> two of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s <hi>Magicians</hi> (whoſe Names are to be ſeen in ſome Ancient Authors) who withſtood <hi>Moſes</hi> in his time; ſo do theſe <hi>reſiſt the Truth, Men of Corrupt minds, Reprobate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Teachers</hi> (Men of Corrupt minds) <hi>reſiſt the Truth, a moſt dreadful ſign of Reprobation;</hi> though the Truths of the Goſpel are brought, and plainly laid before them, to turn them from <hi>the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:103245:62"/>of their way,</hi> in their <hi>falſe unchriſtian Principles and Practices,</hi> yet <hi>they reſiſt the Truth,</hi> they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own it, and reject it, and they that Offer it to them; and that with many <hi>reviling hard ſpeeches againſt them</hi> for ſo doing: Like <hi>Swine</hi> they <hi>trample Pearls under their Feet, and turn again and rent you:</hi> Being <hi>Men of Corrupt minds, and Reprobate concerning the Faith;</hi> their minds are <hi>Corrupt, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Filthy, Defiled with falſe Notions, Erroneous Opinions, and Conceptions of things,</hi> according to their <hi>dark, carnal apprehenſions,</hi> mixed alſo with <hi>Satans falſe gloſſes, and deceitful appearances in their minds;</hi> and ſo they become <hi>Reprobate concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Faith:</hi> That is, <hi>without Judgment, or any true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding in Matters of Faith,</hi> according as the <hi>Scriptures</hi> have revealed them.</p>
               <p>But it follows, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>They ſhall proceed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for their folly ſhall be made manifeſt unto all men, as theirs alſo was.</hi> After they have <hi>done their work, and filled up the meaſure of their Iniquity, and fulfilled the Scriptures,</hi> what was fore-told of them; then they ſhall be <hi>Diſcovered and made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt,</hi> and that <hi>to all men,</hi> even to <hi>their own party alſo</hi> (as well as to others) who have been <hi>long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and ſeduced by them:</hi> they ſhall then <hi>fall off from them by degrees, and leave them, and forſake their meetings.</hi> They ſhall be known to be <hi>deceitful workers,</hi> their folly ſhall be made manifeſt, as theirs alſo was, that is as the folly of <hi>Jannes and Jambres, the Sorcerers or Magicians</hi> which deceived the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for a while with <hi>falſe ſhews and appearances of things</hi> which were not ſo in <hi>Reality and Truth;</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards they were diſcovered to be but a Cheat, and deceitful workings.</p>
               <p>So theſe men with all their <hi>Counterfeit Coin and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:103245:62"/>Deceitful Wares,</hi> which they <hi>expoſe and offer to Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the dark,</hi> and which they will not (by their good will) bring unto <hi>the Light of the Scriptures,</hi> which would make things manifeſt unto all; yet they ſhall in due time be brought <hi>to the Light; their folly ſhall be made manifeſt unto all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And is not <hi>this Scripture</hi> in a great meaſure ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled <hi>already, even at this day?</hi> The Men, <hi>theſe falſe Teachers, their Opinions, Principles, and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> have been <hi>of late time,</hi> more than ever before, laid open, <hi>and their Folly, and groſs Ignorance, and Errors made manifeſt unto all,</hi> and ſo will be ſtill more and more.</p>
               <q>See three Dialogues between a Chriſtian and a Quaker, by <hi>Tho. Hicks,</hi> where they are made Naked before all Men to their ſhame.</q>
               <p>God hath (of late time more eſpecially) ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up the Spirits of ſome of his People, to <hi>ſearch into, and Examine their Opinions and Doctrines, and to try them by the Scriptures, ſpoken by God himſelf;</hi> and they find that theſe Men have ſpoken contrary to what God hath ſpoken: The <hi>Doctrine of theſe falſe Teachers is contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt</hi> made known to us in the Goſpel, they are <hi>detected, diſcovered, and made manifeſt to all,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome of their own Party, (Friends as they call them) who it's like are ſo Charmed by them, as that they will not hear, nor hearken to any thing that is ſaid <hi>againſt them or their Principles,</hi> though ſpoken according to truth: Nay, they will not hear <hi>God himſelf ſpeak,</hi> for they <hi>Neglect and Deſpiſe the Scriptures,</hi> and prefer <hi>their own ſimple Pamphlets</hi> before them.</p>
               <p>Now,
<note place="margin">Good Councel to the Quakers.</note> ſeeing theſe things are ſo, I ſhall in ſincere Love
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:103245:63"/>and Pity to the Souls of theſe People, the Quakers, give them my Advice and Councel according to Truth, whether they will hear it, or whether they will reject it; I am perſwaded there are <hi>ſome amongſt them who have true and real intentions and deſires after the truth, to hear it, and to do it;</hi> and therefore there is ſome hopes <hi>of ſuch,</hi> that if they would give themſelves to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Principles of their Teachers,</hi> and be earneſt with God to give them <hi>his Spirit to Open their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings,</hi> they might clearly ſee the groſs Folly and Errors of theſe Men; and that they would read <hi>other mens Books</hi> (wherein they are concern'd) as well as <hi>their Friends Books:</hi> thereby alſo <hi>their Light within would be the clearer:</hi> But whilſt they Neglect or Decline the <hi>means of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> no marvel though they remain <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and are ſeduced.</p>
               <p>My Advice and Councel is further,
<note place="margin">Leave the Quakers Meetings.</note> That you would <hi>leave the Aſſemblies of theſe Men, ſeparate your ſelves from their Congregations and Meetings: Now is ſeparation ſeaſonable,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures, <hi>ſeparate from them,</hi> becauſe <hi>they have ſeparated from Christ, and from his Church and People;</hi> they are <hi>gone from the truth,</hi> and are <hi>turned unto Fables;</hi> and they give <hi>heed unto ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſpirits, and Doctrines of Devils, ſpeaking lyes in Hypocriſie, having their Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron;</hi> ſo that they will not hear, nor heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to the Truth as it is in Jeſus.</p>
               <p>They <hi>ſlight and deſpiſe the Scriptures,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>what Light is</hi> in them, <hi>what Wiſdom</hi> is in them? Nothing but <hi>Darkneſs and Ignorance,</hi> improved alſo by <hi>ſubtil ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> which (except they
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:103245:63"/>ſpeedily Repent) will draw them down into the <hi>Bottomleſs Pit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And next I adviſe you,
<note place="margin">Come to the Aſſemblies of the Saints.</note> 
                  <hi>Come and joyn your ſelves to the Lord, and to his People;</hi> come into their <hi>Aſſemblies, Societies, and Congregations;</hi> there ye ſhall hear <hi>Chriſt truly Preached, and ſet forth according to the Goſpel,</hi> whereby your minds may be <hi>enlightned to ſee the Beauty of Chriſt indeed,</hi> with all his <hi>Benefits and Priviledges</hi> purchaſed for his People; and this may make you fall <hi>in Love with him, and to chuſe him for your Lord and Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> O take heed of forſaking, or Neglecting the <hi>Aſſemblies of the People of the Lord,</hi> as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſome is; it is a very Dangerous thing. See the Conſequences of it, which the Apoſtle tells us of in the 10. of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> it is a Sign, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of <hi>that great ſin, the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as it is there ſet forth. Come then to the <hi>Aſſemblies of the Saints, for the Lord is among them, and in them, and Communicates himſelf unto them;</hi> he reveals his Mind, his Secrets to them that fear him. Ye are now <hi>in a dry and barren Wilderneſs,</hi> where there is <hi>no Water, no Water of Life,</hi> your Souls will be lean, and ſtarved for want of <hi>Food, for want of the Bread and Water of Life,</hi> unleſs ye come unto him, that ye may have Life; your <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers themſelves</hi> want this, having forſaken the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Living Waters,</hi> and run to <hi>broken Ciſterns,</hi> which hold <hi>not a drop of Water. The Light within is but Darkneſs</hi> to the <hi>true Light Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Your Teachers themſelves <hi>want water,</hi> being <hi>Wells with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water, and Clouds without water, carried about with winds.</hi> Therefore come to the <hi>Fountain of Living waters, to the Fountain of Gardens,</hi> that
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:103245:64"/>waters <hi>all the Gardens, all his Churches,</hi> and every <hi>particular ſoul;</hi> and <hi>their ſouls are as watred Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and as ſprings of water, whoſe waters fail not:</hi> For there is in them <hi>a Well of water, ſpringing up unto Eternal Life.</hi> Come then, and be partakers of <hi>theſe Priviledges;</hi> be <hi>one with Chriſt, and with his People;</hi> and ye ſhall be <hi>enlightned by Chriſt the true Light indeed, and Life indeed,</hi> who will guide you, and lead you into <hi>Green Paſtures by the Rivers of waters;</hi> who will feed you with the <hi>Bread and Water of Life, unto Eternal Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:103245:64"/>
            <p>THere are lately Publiſhed Three Dialogues Between a Chriſtian and a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, wherein are faithfully Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented ſome of the Chief and moſt Concerning Opinions of the Quakers; together with their Method and Manner of Reaſoning in the Defence thereof. Alſo the Quakers Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal Anſwered. All Written by <hi>Tho. Hicks.</hi> Sold by <hi>Peter Parker</hi> at the <hi>Leg</hi> and <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
